<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 13:28:04 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic movie binge</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/07/25/pandemic-movie-binge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 13:28:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/07/25/pandemic-movie-binge/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With the pandemic preventing us from attending cinemas, I &amp;ldquo;splurged&amp;rdquo; for the HBO+Movies streaming package on Crave TV and spent a whole month binging movies until the subscription expired. It was a lot of fun and I definitely got my fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;5-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;5 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/ask_dr_ruth&#34;&gt;Ask Dr. Ruth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_hate_u_give&#34;&gt;The Hate U Give&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/joker_2019&#34;&gt;Joker&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;excellent movie although I can understand the controversy around it glorifying violence, which is a shame because there was another message in there about mental health patients falling through the cracks due to funding cuts.. and with a few very minor tweaks that could have been the takeaway message&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/james_vs_his_future_self&#34;&gt;James vs His Future Self&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;nerdy, Canadian.. yep I&amp;rsquo;m here for this!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/giant_little_ones&#34;&gt;Giant Little Ones&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;one of my favs so far.. found out afterwards it was also a Canadian movie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/maiden&#34;&gt;Maiden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;4-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;4 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/men_in_black_international&#34;&gt;MIB International&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;surprisingly quite enjoyed this, went in with zero expectations (that probably helped) but liked the general irreverent tone throughout&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/abominable_2019&#34;&gt;Abominable&lt;/a&gt; (2019) - &lt;em&gt;a good choice if you&amp;rsquo;re in the mood for a kids movie (and aren&amp;rsquo;t we all from time to time?)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_peanut_butter_falcon&#34;&gt;The Peanut Butter Falcon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/isnt_it_romantic_2019&#34;&gt;Isn&amp;rsquo;t It Romantic&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;a rom-com that pokes fun at rom-coms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/us_2019&#34;&gt;Us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/bohemian_rhapsody&#34;&gt;Bohemian Rhapsody&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Mr. Robot as Mr. Mercury&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/bohemian_rhapsody&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;lighthearted fare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;3-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;3 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/blood_quantum&#34;&gt;Blood Quantum&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;was super pumped for this, and it was a 5-star start but didn&amp;rsquo;t sustain, I found out later the filming was &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; finished when they ran out of funds, I guess that might explain it.. still alright for a low budget film if you are type to enjoy zombie violence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_immortal_life_of_henrietta_lacks&#34;&gt;The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/ready_or_not_2019&#34;&gt;Ready or Not&lt;/a&gt; (2019) - &lt;em&gt;would have got 4 from me if it had slanted slightly more to the humour side, but that&amp;rsquo;s more of a personal style preference on my part&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/fast_color&#34;&gt;Fast Color&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;liked the story but it was a tad slow paced for my tastes, wish it were 10 minutes shorter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/once_upon_a_time_in_hollywood&#34;&gt;Once Upon a Time in Hollywood&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;definitely a few LOL moments, but unless you love Tarantino or 1960s nostalgia it&amp;rsquo;s not worth 2h40m of your time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_mustang&#34;&gt;The Mustang&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;nice animal/human connection story without falling into Disney&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/blinded_by_the_light&#34;&gt;Blinded by the Light&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;if you like Springsteen I imagine you&amp;rsquo;d really like this movie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/good_boys_2019&#34;&gt;Good Boys&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;quite a few LOLs, but I was finding it somewhat tiresome by the end&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/clemency_2019&#34;&gt;Clemency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_miseducation_of_cameron_post_2018&#34;&gt;The Miseducation of Cameron Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/godzilla_king_of_the_monsters_2019&#34;&gt;Godzilla: King of Monsters&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;comes as advertised, if that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for (yes please)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stuber&#34;&gt;Stuber&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;good one for a laugh, for when you don&amp;rsquo;t want to think&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;2-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;2 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/it_chapter_two&#34;&gt;IT Chapter Two&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;chapter 1 was 5 stars for me. I really love the IT franchise and I wanted to like this too.. but can&amp;rsquo;t recommend it, too repetitive especially after the first chapter.. By the end of it you&amp;rsquo;ll be sick of CGI fight scenes in the sewers. The self-aware moments were the best parts but they don&amp;rsquo;t save the movie. Also the gratuitous hate crime against homosexuals to open things was extremely off-putting and in this day and age should have been cut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/climax&#34;&gt;Climax&lt;/a&gt; (2018) - &lt;em&gt;the buildup had me intrigued but the roller coaster ride itself was a letdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_art_of_self_defense_2019&#34;&gt;The Art of Self-Defence&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;was hoping for more of a comedy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;1-star:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;1 Star&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/in_fabric&#34;&gt;In Fabric&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;92% critics score, 48% audience score.. I side with the audience on this one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/alpha_2018&#34;&gt;Alpha&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;a visually pretty movie, but so many small touches felt unrealistic about how a prehistoric culture would have been.. maybe if you turn off your analytical brain it would be enjoyable&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StudioTax 2019 on Ubuntu</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/05/24/studiotax-2019-on-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 14:44:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/05/24/studiotax-2019-on-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.studiotax.com&#34;&gt;StudioTax&lt;/a&gt; is free tax software for Canadians. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty great to have this free way to file your taxes, but the supported operating systems are Windows, Mac, iOS and Android.. unfortunately no Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watering_hole_attack&#34;&gt;security reasons&lt;/a&gt;, I never do work with sensitive/confidential information on the same system I use for browsing/social media/general use.. This rules out doing anything tax-related on my phone. But luckily it&amp;rsquo;s quite easy to spin up a secure Ubuntu system on any old laptop or desktop you may have lying around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how I got StudioTax running on Ubuntu with VirtualBox:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Ubuntu 20.04. Make sure you&amp;rsquo;ll have 20-30 GB free disk space after ubuntu is installed (needed to start windows in VirtualBox).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply all the latest patches on Ubuntu to be sure you have the latest security updates before starting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.virtualbox.org/&#34;&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/software-download/windows10&#34;&gt;Windows 10&lt;/a&gt; ISO file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use VirtualBox to install a Windows 10 system inside of your Ubuntu system. (Link the ISO file into the &amp;ldquo;Storage&amp;rdquo; settings to get the Windows installation going).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once Windows is installed and running, apply all Windows updates to make sure you have the latest security updates before you start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Windows now, you can download StudioTax. Install StudioTax as administrator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good to go!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To transfer files between Ubuntu and Windows, you can do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In VirtualBox menu of the running Windows system, go to &amp;ldquo;Devices -&amp;gt; Insert Guest Additions CD Image&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Windows now, open the File explorer and navigate to the newly added &amp;ldquo;CD Drive&amp;rdquo;. Run the application VBoxWindowsAdditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In VirtualBox menu go to &amp;ldquo;Machine -&amp;gt; Settings -&amp;gt; Shared Folders&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add new shared folder. Select the Ubuntu folder you would like to share, and for the mount point you can just put &lt;code&gt;G:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;G:&lt;/code&gt; location should now appear in Windows File Explorer and you can use it like any other folder. (If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t show, check under the &amp;ldquo;Network&amp;rdquo; section of File Explorer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: 2019</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 09:48:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A year&amp;rsquo;s worth of reading and no book blog posts? Well, better late than never! In addition to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/&#34;&gt;new parent selections&lt;/a&gt;, here are a few of the books I read this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;team-human:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Team Human&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Douglas Rushkoff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/teamHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Team Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt; is a podcast and now a book which I read around the time of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/&#34;&gt;his visit to the Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s well worth a read and captures the main thesis that even more technology won&amp;rsquo;t solve our problems so long as we keep treating problems as unconnected; but as humans we&amp;rsquo;re fully equipped to form communities and launch a modern renaissance that respects humanity - if only we would recognize and choose to do so. Probably the most important book of 2019, in my opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lana-and-lilly-wachowski:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cáel M. Keegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wachowskis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dense academic book within a series on &lt;em&gt;Contemporary Film Directors&lt;/em&gt;, this text looks at the Wachowskis oeuvre through a trans* lens, giving a whole new meaning to &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, one of my favourite movies. It also leads an insightful reading into &lt;em&gt;Sense8&lt;/em&gt;, probably my favourite TV show in recent memory. This book introduced me to &lt;em&gt;Bound&lt;/em&gt;, the Wachowskis&amp;rsquo; first major film, which is excellent and worth watching if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book is a simply terrific interview with Lana Wachowski.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;] A lot of your work seems to be very concerned with the idea of moving through space and time differently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s an opposing narrative. The dominant cultural narrative is that things are static. There&amp;rsquo;s a foundational myth about America, about identity, about heteronormativity. [&amp;hellip;] &amp;ldquo;This is the way it is.&amp;rdquo; This is even the concept of normalcy. Normalcy is non-moving. It&amp;rsquo;s a fixed idea. All of my narratives are an assault against this idea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;Would you describe yourself as utopian, then?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;Obviously I would resist any label&amp;hellip;but I think the making of art is inherently optimistic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-doesn-t-have-to-be-crazy-at-work:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;It Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/itDoesntHaveToBeCrazyAtWork.png&#34; alt=&#34;It Doesn&#39;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manual for setting a &lt;em&gt;calm&lt;/em&gt; work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s constantly crazy at work, we have two words for you: Fuck that. And two more: Enough already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of it all is an unhealthy obsession with rapid growth. Towering, unrealistic expectations drag people down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time for companies to stop asking their employees to breathlessly chase ever-higher, ever-more artificial targets set by ego, not need. It’s time to stop celebrating this way of working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few topics that really resonated with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FOMO? JOMO!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People should be missing out. Most people should be missing out on most things most of the time. [&amp;hellip;] JOMO! The joy of missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be a knee-jerk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person making the pitch has presumably put a lot of time, thought, and energy into gathering their thoughts and presenting them clearly to an audience. But the rest of the people in the room are asked to react. Not absorb, not think it over, not consider - just react. Knee-jerk it. That&amp;rsquo;s no way to treat fragile new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t want reactions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want first impressions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want knee-jerks. We want considered feedback. Read it over. Read it twice, three times even. Sleep on it. Take your time to gather and present your thoughts - just like the person who pitched the original idea took their time to gather and present theirs. That&amp;rsquo;s how you go deep on an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All subject matter experts at Basecamp now publish office hours. [&amp;hellip;] This might seem inefficient at first glance. Bureaucratic, even. But we&amp;rsquo;ve seen otherwise. Office hours have been a big hit at Basecamp. It turns out that waiting is no big deal most of the time. But the time and control regained by our experts is a huge deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your company is a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company is like software. It has to be usable, it has to be useful. And it probably also has bugs, places where the company crashes because of bad organizational design or cultural oversights. When you start to think of your company as a product, all sorts of new possibilities for improvement emerge. When you realize the way you work is malleable, you can start molding something new, something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;prediction-machines:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ajay Agrawal, Joshua Gans, Avi Goldfarb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/predictionMachines.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prediction Machines&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by three economists, &lt;em&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/em&gt; takes the &amp;ldquo;mystery&amp;rdquo; out of AI by re-casting it within an economic framework and simply treating it as cheaper prediction, and then following the consequences of seeing it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t love this book but I don&amp;rsquo;t have much argument with the premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-after-the-end:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Love After the End&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2019)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/loveAfterTheEnd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Love After the End&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sci-fi anthology of short stories about Two-Spirit utopias and dystopias, a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you survive a perfect world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, how do you grow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an imperfect world, how do you resist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]
Imagine the future of our people after the end of colonization. Read stories of survival and love lost and found, across all bodies and genders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered this book through a Kickstarter campaign. The introduction by Joshua Whitehead was a beautiful way to set the context for the reader (probably my favourite part of the book actually, which is not taking anything away from the stories but more a statement on how great of an introduction it was).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite stories were Darcie Little Badger&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Story for a Bottle&lt;/em&gt;, jaye simpson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Ark of the Turtle&amp;rsquo;s Back&lt;/em&gt;, and Adam Garnet Jones&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;The New World&lt;/em&gt;. Highly recommend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;permanent-record:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Permanent Record&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/permanentRecord.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Permanent Record&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am halfway through reading Snowden&amp;rsquo;s autobiography. It&amp;rsquo;s a great read thus far, but I&amp;rsquo;m only just getting to the famous parts of his story. When you know the ending, it&amp;rsquo;s tempting to look back and pick out only the events that supported the outcome (which is of course a common bias). I feel as though that&amp;rsquo;s what Snowden has done with his memoir when describing his early days; probably a more rounded story would be a bit more nuanced, but hey he&amp;rsquo;s writing for an audience after all. And it&amp;rsquo;s all very interesting stuff. Looking forward to the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;democracy-may-not-exist-but-we-ll-miss-it-when-it-s-gone:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Democracy May Not Exist But We&amp;rsquo;ll Miss It When It&amp;rsquo;s Gone&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Astra Taylor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/democracyMayNotExist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Democracy May Not Exist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m only a few chapters into this one and I need to re-request it from the library again to finish it. This is an eye-opening book about how the public doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a good idea of what democracy is (although we think we do) and how it&amp;rsquo;s really more about straight up conflicting principles (eg. equality versus freedom) and how the tensions between these principles are perpetually at play and continuously needing resolution through community. Put in another form: democracy is more of a verb than a noun. I discovered this book through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-130-astra-taylor-democracy-is-a-verb/&#34;&gt;Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m really looking forward to completing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources for New Parents</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 20:11:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Having recently gone through the birth of our first child, the following were helpful resources that I felt worth documenting here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-birth-partner:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;The Birth Partner&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Complete Guide to Childbirth for Dads, Doulas, and All Other Labor Companions&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/birthPartner.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Birth Partner&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommended by our midwife. By far the best reference about what goes on during labour and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cribsheet:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;Cribsheet&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/cribsheet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cribsheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;A data-driven guide to better, more relaxed parenting&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released this year, this book takes a data-driven approach to answer all kinds of choices facing parents regarding their newborn. We liked this one for the non-judgmental tone and the evidence-based advice. The author also has another book in the same style which covers pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-to-expect-when-you-re-expecting-the-first-year:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;What to Expect (When You&amp;rsquo;re Expecting | The First Year)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/whatToExpect.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;What to Expect&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quintessential classic is a great reference. I use this whenever I want to ask &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;what do most people do&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. It really does cover a lot of ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;24-hour-cribside-assistance:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;24 Hour Cribside Assistance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newdadmanual.ca/&#34;&gt;24 Hour Cribside Assistance&lt;/a&gt; is an online guide for new fathers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Douglas Rushkoff at Writersfest</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 10:26:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I had the pleasure of listening to Douglas Rushkoff speak at the spring edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writersfestival.org/&#34;&gt;Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. Rushkoff is one of my favourite thinkers and host of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; podcast, as well as author of the new book &lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very little prompting is needed by the host to set off intriguing ruminations from Rushkoff about technology, media and society. Rushkoff walks us through the medieval inventions of the corporation and growth-based currency (currency that has to be borrowed and paid back with interest), both of which were introduced for the purpose of suppressing the middle class so that the ruling class could preserve their wealth in an increasingly peer-to-peer marketplace environment. These concepts have continued straight through to today and now form the unquestioned &amp;ldquo;operating system&amp;rdquo; upon which our whole economy is built. Rushkoff points to these two as the root cause of many of the strange effects that technology is having on society today, and how tech companies, for all their talk of disruption, have not considered challenging these basic assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff talks about reversals that happen with technology (in his own terms, the &lt;em&gt;figure&lt;/em&gt; vs the &lt;em&gt;ground&lt;/em&gt;), whereby over time the users of a technology become themselves used by it (the book goes into this concept much more). Rushkoff draws a parallel between colonization (a term we are familiar with in Canada to describe the structural violence against Indigenous peoples) and the effect that digital technology is having on us today. There is no denying the harm that technology can cause to our wellbeing and to that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff points out that the best consumer is an isolated consumer. As such, growth-based technologies act to push us apart. He recalls watching TV together as a family while growing up, and going to the theatres to watch a movie. These days we consume media in individualistic ways designed to make us more susceptible to surveillance and targeted advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff warns that we can lose our human souls (or just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/JamesBrownOfficial&#34;&gt;soul&lt;/a&gt; with reference to James Brown, for those who don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the former concept) by profit-focused algorithms that try to &amp;ldquo;auto-tune&amp;rdquo; our behaviour so that we better fit our algorithmically predicted buckets. Weirdness is what makes us human, and should be celebrated. Life is everything that happens in between the &amp;ldquo;notes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are warned to think of digital technologies as drugs - you&amp;rsquo;re on Facebook, on Twitter, on-line.. He quotes Timothy Leary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Before you take a drug, look into the eye of someone who&amp;rsquo;s done that drug. Decide if that&amp;rsquo;s a place you want to be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have the choice not to do so. Rushkoff suggests we try practicing a &lt;em&gt;Tech Sabbath&lt;/em&gt; - consuming no digital technologies on Sundays. Then, level that up further by cutting out cars as well. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple idea but one can easily imagine how that would foster local communities in a serious way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff peppers the talk with repeated calls to respecting human dignity and human values. He calls on us to make local connections, be a part of &lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;Breathe together&amp;rdquo; he instructs us, explaining how this is literally the etymological basis for the term &lt;em&gt;conspire&lt;/em&gt;. And by connecting and interacting offline, face-to-face we are also &lt;em&gt;conspiring&lt;/em&gt; against the companies that are trying to make a dollar off our interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Smart&#34; City coming to Ottawa?</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 08:50:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was stirred to write a blog post after stumbling across an op-ed titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/index.php/article/op-ed-forget-about-toronto-sidewalk-labs-build-smart-neighbourhood-ottawa-instead&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forget about Toronto, Sidewalk Labs – build a smart neighbourhood in Ottawa instead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been following Toronto&amp;rsquo;s efforts at smart city development for the past 9 months (aka the Sidewalk Labs debacle), and was alarmed to read this same group might bring their bad behaviour to Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sidewalk Labs&amp;rsquo; smart city in Toronto has woeful accountability (and its leaked plans are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalobserver.com/2019/02/15/news/alphabets-sidewalk-labs-was-secretly-considering-big-plans-toronto-neighbourhood&#34;&gt;terrifying&lt;/a&gt;), with high profile &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2018/10/20/privacy-expert-steps-down-from-advisory-role-with-sidewalk-labs.html&#34;&gt;resignations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://business.financialpost.com/technology/sidewalk-labs-advisory-panel-member-saadia-muzaffar-resigns-citing-deep-dismay&#34;&gt;leading tech experts&lt;/a&gt;. And yet they continue to go forward. Explain why would anyone would want that for their city?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The op-ed author says that a data policy is necessary upfront (which I absolutely agree with) while in the same breath telling us we should &amp;ldquo;inform these businesses they could start developing a smart community in Ottawa today&amp;rdquo;. Seems like a contradiction there. A public data policy must be something that is carefully debated and not rushed through. It&amp;rsquo;s exactly this kind of &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out as we go&amp;rdquo; mentality that got Toronto into trouble. It opens the door for corporate definition and interference in policy (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@biancawylie/sidewalk-toronto-gaslighting-toronto-residents-backfired-capacitys-built-and-power-s-shifted-77c455b150a3&#34;&gt;gas lighting&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Toronto&amp;rsquo;s failure, and with many thanks to the citizens advocating in opposition there, here is what Ottawa can and should do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start working on privacy and data governance policies. Today! This needs to happen ASAP or we &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get bullied by corporations into rushed or inadequate policies. This needs to be carefully debated and done so in a fully transparent way.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we have any smart city policies already? I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laughably, Ottawa&amp;rsquo;s published &lt;a href=&#34;https://documents.ottawa.ca/sites/default/files/smart_city_strategy_en.pdf&#34;&gt;Smart City 2.0 Strategy&lt;/a&gt; does not have a single reference to &amp;ldquo;privacy&amp;rdquo; or even &amp;ldquo;data governance&amp;rdquo; in its strategy. (Yes you read that correctly. I wish I was joking.). Really shows where the priorities are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, as a city let&amp;rsquo;s first be explicit about what features we want from our smart city, and debate those features in a public setting. Not all &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; technology is smart for society or the public as a whole. We should not give carte blanche to corporations to &amp;ldquo;disrupt&amp;rdquo; neighbourhoods however they see fit, as if breaking neighbourhoods was even a good thing.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s follow the principle of &lt;a href=&#34;http://spacing.ca/toronto/2019/02/19/did-the-sidewalk-labs-plot-just-thicken-or-is-the-story-coming-to-an-end/&#34;&gt;Consult first, then procure.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to OBJ for the balanced journalism in also including an article on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/article/web-data-collected-smart-city-tech-stokes-privacy-fears&#34;&gt;privacy concerns&lt;/a&gt; surrounding smart city development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blocksidewalk.ca/&#34;&gt;BlockSidewalk&lt;/a&gt; movement to stay up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life Insurance Calculator</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/19/life-insurance-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 20:19:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/19/life-insurance-calculator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With a baby on the way later this year, it&amp;rsquo;s the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve had to contemplate taking care of a dependent (not counting pets of course). One of the duties in this regard is ensuring that your dependent will be financially supported in the event of your death. Not a pleasant topic to think about, unless maybe you are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/travel/story/20150408-bhutans-dark-secret-to-happiness&#34;&gt;from Bhutan&lt;/a&gt;, but a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main question is how much insurance do I need? To answer, I threw together &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/LifeInsuranceCalculator.ods&#34;&gt;this LibreOffice spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; as a &amp;ldquo;back of the napkin&amp;rdquo; type calculator. It is definitely only meant as a rough guide and does not rigorously examine inflation nor taxes to a fine precision (although it does take them into account somewhat). The cells in blue are what you will edit to set the parameters for your specific case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing a parent is probably not going to easy for a child, so I am erring on the side of overcompensation. Post-secondary education is one such example that others might consider optional, but I wanted to ensure it was fully covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised at the cost of post-secondary education compared to 15-20 years ago. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what form education will even take in 20 years, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to imagine the costs continuing to rise and the value proposition still being there in an age of information abundance. Nevertheless, I am including it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;both parents die&amp;rdquo; case was also interesting to examine. I thought for sure it would be the worst case scenario, financially speaking, but turns out it&amp;rsquo;s a non-issue when both parents have some retirement savings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soundtrack of 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/soundtrack-of-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 21:03:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/soundtrack-of-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Music has a curious way of permeating your life, such that years later a song can stir up forgotten memories and emotions. Each song is precious in a way that only we can fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These songs formed the soundtrack of my life in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-violin-stereotypes-album-2015:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Black Violin - Stereotypes (album 2015)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mix of hip hop and classical, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blackviolin.net/videos/&#34;&gt;Black Violin&lt;/a&gt; pushes the boundaries of each genre. I&amp;rsquo;ve actually been listening to this album for a couple years now and still not tired of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/blackViolin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Stereotypes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-toast-light:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Dr. Toast - Light&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A constant at the yoga studio, this song takes me straight to my centered happy place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://music.drtoast.com/track/light&#34;&gt;https://music.drtoast.com/track/light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonobo-sweetness-bootleg-album-2002:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Bonobo - Sweetness (bootleg album 2002)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my album of choice to listen while coding this year. Enough repetition to let your mind focus, enough complexity to keep things interesting when you surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wdpDtAjZuWQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-balconies-show-you-album-2012:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;The Balconies - Show You (album 2012)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Balconies&#34;&gt;The Balconies&lt;/a&gt; are a local Ottawa rock/pop band who I was into 10 years ago. This album was recorded in 2012 but never released because the band&amp;rsquo;s style had changed in the intervening time, so they kept it hidden away for all these years. I was more a fan of their old style anyway so once the band folded and released the forgotten album I was very happy to have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/8721557&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;various-irish-artists-musical-pub-crawl-album:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Various Irish artists - Musical Pub Crawl (album)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our travels in Ireland this year took as to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.musicalpubcrawl.com&#34;&gt;musical pub crawl&lt;/a&gt; in Dublin. We were able to purchase an album of traditional Irish music which is exceptional but I cannot find it online. It&amp;rsquo;s become our staple soundtrack this year while cooking and doing stuff around the house.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/advent-of-code-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 13:20:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/advent-of-code-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This past December I discovered the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; challenge, in which you get a different coding puzzle for each day in December leading up to Christmas. The puzzles can be solved in any programming language of your choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to solve the puzzles in Elixir, which is a newer language that I am starting to use at work. The creator of Elixir, José Valim, was solving the puzzles as well and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.plataformatec.com.br/2018/11/lets-learn-elixir-together-with-advent-of-code/&#34;&gt;live streaming his solutions&lt;/a&gt;. Other Elixir experts were also publishing solutions, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sasa1977/aoc&#34;&gt;Saša Jurić&lt;/a&gt;. This was so cool! A fabulous way to learn a new language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints I only attempted about half of the puzzles with my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/advent-of-code-2018&#34;&gt;solutions posted here&lt;/a&gt;. I was hoping to go back and finish the rest of the puzzles but that hasn&amp;rsquo;t happened so I&amp;rsquo;m wrapping this up with a blog post now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;commentary:0647481dad1b7f4b21d4a5bad3077cd7&#34;&gt;Commentary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partway through I realized it would be helpful to myself to capture personal insights for each solution, so I left some commentary in the code solutions themselves which I am reproducing here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td style=&#34;width: 20%&#34;&gt;
Day 5 
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
    For this solution, I found that converting each individual character to a String for purpose of doing downcase() 
    was performance impacting (total 30 seconds to solve puzzle). So I switched to using assumption
    that input was only ascii letters (and added a validation check to ensure this assumption holds). 
    Thus I could compare upper/lower case by adding 32 to the value instead of converting to string. Solution runs 15x faster.
    &lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 6
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
The performance of my solution is lacking, it took 30 seconds to solve Part 1 on my laptop.
Part 2 solution was even worse - 2 min 26 s.
If I had more time I would go back and optimize!
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 7
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
    First part was OK, second part took a long time to solve.
    First puzzle where my code worked for the test data but didn&#39;t work for the full solution.
    (Turned out I read the challenge wrong.. was using wrong number of workers).
    Passing a lot of parameters around. Might be easier to pass state around as a
    single map structure than as individual parameters.
    
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
 Day 8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Got bitten by elixir when doing efficient building a list by appending to the start
    but then forgetting to reverse list at the end (when order became important)!
    This caused some grief. I could have noticed this error sooner if I ran the tests more frequently
    during development.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Nice to use Stream.unfold for the first time, also learned how to sleep in elixir.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Things I learned today, you can do pattern matching in anonymous functions!
    Part 1 was solved in a straightforward, albeit not great performance way.
    Part 2 The non-performant solution was no longer reasonable. I tried a few
     optimizations but couldn&#39;t make it fast enough. Then I found this hint:
     https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summed-area_table
     but by that point it was the end of the night and I didn&#39;t feel like implementing it.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
  Felt really good about solving this one, my growing familiarity with the elixir
  modules is starting to pay off. Assist to my wife for talking through Part 2 strategy with me.
  
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up Visual Studio Code for Elixir</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/12/31/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-elixir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 13:50:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/12/31/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-elixir/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Elixir is a programming language that I am in the process of learning, and which I use at work. This post documents the settings I am using to develop in elixir using the VSCode editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-language-support:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;1. Language Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install extension &lt;code&gt;ElixirLS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the box this gives you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;autocomplete, navigation, dialyzer (aka static analysis/linting) and debugging capabilities. Hooray!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-formatting:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;2. Formatting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elixir is an auto-formatted language for &lt;a href=&#34;https://hashrocket.com/blog/posts/format-your-elixir-code-now&#34;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;, hence &lt;code&gt;mix format&lt;/code&gt; is your friend. In your VSCode Settings, hit the checkbox for &amp;ldquo;Editor: Format on Save&amp;rdquo; to run this on every save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-test-execution:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;3. Test Execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commonly run tests three different ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a single test. Most frequently used while developing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the tests. Used for regression testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run all the tests from a single file. Sometimes useful while developing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set these up as Tasks in your tasks.json as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      }
  },
  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;single test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test ${relativeFile}:${lineNumber}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      },
      &amp;quot;runOptions&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;reevaluateOnRerun&amp;quot;: false
      }
  },
  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test current file&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test ${relativeFile}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      },
      &amp;quot;runOptions&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;reevaluateOnRerun&amp;quot;: false
      }
  }

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also create hotkeys to launch your tests. I do it like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[
   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl-s&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+s&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;single test&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;when&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;editorTextFocus&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+w&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test current file&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+r&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.reRunTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;when&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;editorTextFocus&amp;quot;
   }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s super easy to run a single test, or all the tests, on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use in combination with the standard &amp;ldquo;Rerun Last Task&amp;rdquo; (new in vscode 1.30) to run your single test over and over again without having to switch windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With credit to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pragdave.me/blog/2018/06/13/visual-studio-code-elixir-tests.html&#34;&gt;https://pragdave.me/blog/2018/06/13/visual-studio-code-elixir-tests.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Way of the Peaceful Warrior</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 15:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This month I read  &lt;em&gt;Way of the Peaceful Warrior&lt;/em&gt; by Dan Millman. In short, it is a story about how to live your best life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because I had pre-internalized several of these ideas already from my own lived experience, I found the first half a slow and painful slog (also because I kind of loathed the main character, but that was mostly by design). It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until around page 100 that I settled in and felt like I was getting something out of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those insights is a way of looking at emotions. Here I pulled three separate quotes from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to control emotion &amp;hellip; The key is to transform the energy of emotion into constructive action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger is a powerful tool to transform old habits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear and sorrow inhibit action; anger generates it. When you learn to make proper use of your anger, you can change fear and sorrow to anger, then turn anger to action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is to use your emotions with intention. Take a moment to acknowledge the emotion, then turn around and use it for whatever help it can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another insight is that action is the way of the warrior. Knowledge and meditation only go so far. Turning your knowledge into action is what counts. This is a good reminder for me, that a quiet life of learning is entirely insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some more nuggets of wisdom from the book that I am recording here so that I can come back to later from time to time to remind myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any unconscious, compulsive ritual is a problem.&lt;/em&gt; [&amp;hellip;] &lt;em&gt;Responsibility means recognizing both pleasure and price, action and consequence, then making a choice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My actions are conscious, spontaneous, intentional, and complete.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t live according to anyone&amp;rsquo;s expectations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are no ordinary moments&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extend razor-sharp attention to every moment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The mind stores tension in the body. Worries, anxieties, and other mental debris are stored as chronic tension&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meditating an action is different from doing it. To do, there is a doer, a self-conscious &amp;lsquo;someone&amp;rsquo; performing. But when you meditate an action, you&amp;rsquo;ve released attachment to outcomes. There&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;lsquo;you&amp;rsquo; left to do it. In forgetting yourself, you become what you do, so your action is free, spontaneous, without ambition, inhibition, or fear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The secret of happiness, you see, is not found in seeking more, but in developing the capacity to enjoy less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find the book a roundabout way of sharing this wisdom. Having to slog through the experience of Danny is, I guess, one example for readers to work with. But I found so many more examples in my own lived experience to relate to that I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to be guided this way. And there was a strange side-story about a woman named Joy which became a weird metaphor that felt awkward and unnecessary. As such, I felt the presentation of these ideas overall did not resonate well for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However one thing I did like was how these ideas were presented without any religious context. I have a vague sense that many of them could be compatible with Taoist ideas, however not being very well-versed in that domain myself I cannot comment much further (it does remind me that I am overdue to read a different book involving Taoism that my sister gave me: &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Names for Joy&lt;/em&gt;). On his Q&amp;amp;A webpage, Millman states that many readers have found religious teachings in his work but that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t subscribe &amp;ldquo;to any other philosophical stool, but to simple humanity&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite part of the book is the challenge to the reader to &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;be unreasonably happy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. I do believe happiness is a choice, so this resonates with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feelings change &amp;hellip; Sometimes sorrow, sometimes joy. But beneath it all remember the innate perfection of your life unfolding. That is the secret of unreasonable happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a master at anything, and there are always ways to improve, but this is one lesson, at least, worth taking to heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three sequels were written to this book, including one that come out just last year (&lt;em&gt;The Hidden School&lt;/em&gt;). I don&amp;rsquo;t feel the urge to read further, but if anyone else has then I&amp;rsquo;m interested to hear what you thought about them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: Spring/Summer 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 20:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It has been a busy time but I am still reading! Here is a quick recap of memorable books finished in Spring and Summer 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/books2018.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Books in 2018&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;49th-parallels:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;49th Parallels&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published during Canada&amp;rsquo;s 150-year celebration, a compilation of short stories and alternative histories involving Canada and our place in the world. Example: what if Canada had been first to develop the atomic bomb? I supported this publication through crowdfunding, and am quite pleased with the result: uniquely Canadian! Re-imagining our story helps answer questions about who we are and who we could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-beyond-body-space-time:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indigenous LGBT sci-fi short story compilation. It&amp;rsquo;s a rare intersection to find in one publication and worth checking out for that alone. In particular I really enjoyed Cherie Dimaline&amp;rsquo;s and Nathan Adler&amp;rsquo;s stories and still find myself thinking about them from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-marrow-thieves:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;The Marrow Thieves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cherie Dimaline (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A genius premise. Brings Indigenous history and culture to the forefront. Very well done! I only wish Rose was a more interesting character&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;legacy-of-heorot:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Legacy of Heorot&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Larry Niven, Jerry Pournelle, Steven Barnes (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;200 pioneers arrive to colonize a new planet, but things start to go wrong. I remember enjoying this one as a teenager so thought I&amp;rsquo;d see how it holds up today. Reads like an 80s action movie. Still love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;watch:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Watch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Sawyer (2010)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion about the origin and implications of consciousness, told through an array of interesting characters such as an ape, an emergent AI, a blind teenager who has regained her sight, and an autistic man. Optimistic take on what technology might do for humanity, we need more like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-reconciliation-manifesto:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;The Reconciliation Manifesto&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arthur Manuel (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A straight-forward overview of the legal situation of Indigenous nations in Canada: how we arrived in this situation, and where to go next. The three phases of colonialism: dispossession, dependency, oppression. Manuel argues that pressing for progress in international forums will be more effective than any resolutions being proposed by Canada which are more about extinguishment of Indigenous land title than about rights. Grassroots involvement will be necessary as so-called indigenous &amp;ldquo;leaders&amp;rdquo; have been compromised due to the systemic nature of dependency on government funds. It makes me angry to realize the extent of how Canada is an abuser of human rights. We need more people to understand this now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: My Conversations With Canadians</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 16:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/MyConversationsWithCanadians.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My Conversations With Canadians&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Conversations With Canadians&lt;/em&gt; by Lee Maracle is a thoughtful journey across many topics central to Canada-Indigenous relations (or to use Maracle&amp;rsquo;s suggested term: Canada-&lt;em&gt;Turtle Islander&lt;/em&gt; relations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; this book. It was super approachable and a great education for a non-Turtle Islander like myself, challenging many preconceived ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle recounts conversations she has shared with Canadians ranging in time from the 1970s to the present. She will often linger over questions posed to her by non-Indigenous Canadians, turning the question around for the reader and instead exploring the biases of the questioner - what assumptions do they already have in place, in order to even ask that question? Really eye-opening and I enjoyed this style thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many questions, I also enjoyed how she would confess to the reader how she really wanted to reply, then share what she actually responded with. I admire her grace in what must have been some astonishingly ignorant or rude questions! (And I confess to being one of those ignorant people myself who might be heading along those same lines)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I have come to through all of these experiences is that Canadians don&amp;rsquo;t know much about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education is a cultural process and, of course, the education citizens receive in Canada is all about British contact with Indigenous people and the development and maintenance of Canada. No one studies what was here before in any serious way. It is as though the 150-year history of Canada is far more significant than the 15,000 years previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a sobering thought and so very true. I certainly did not retain much in the way of Indigenous history or knowledge from my Canadian education. That probably means there are at least a generation of people, if not more, who likely have no clue, really (other than stereotypes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle does a good job of imparting the full richness of Turtle Islander culture to her readers, a culture dismissed by settlers, but nevertheless whose influence can be seen on today&amp;rsquo;s world (although that goes unacknowledged).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s humbling to think of all the things we missed learning about in school. What a curriculum it would have made!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was brought up in story. No one disciplined me by spanking or scoldings; rather the old people watching me told a story and I was expected to figure out my behavioural issues from the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I was raised on story, I brought my children up on story. We work with story. We begin with an old tale and, as we progress through the story, we tell it back different but the same, changing it so it becomes a modern new story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle also makes clear that being nice people doesn&amp;rsquo;t give Canadians a pass; she drives home that we are all actively complicit in the genocide of Turtle Islanders, quoting articles from the UN Genocide Convention to support her case. Ignorance may be bliss for some, but morally that stance just doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold up. We have a responsibility to educate ourselves on affairs that are being conducted in our name. It&amp;rsquo;s time for Canadians to get with it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase a statement in the book: de-colonization is not about how the Indigenous world fits into ours, but how we fit into theirs. With this in mind, I sample from Chapter 12 which describes the Turtle Islander belief system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humility is critical to recognizing and examining our failures, our mistakes, our contribution to broken relations [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage gives us the determination to overcome our fear of self-examination, of admitting to our neglect. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honesty teaches us to own our self&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the above be a guide to us Canadians as we reach to build true relations with Turtle Islanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would urge all non-Indigenous folk to pick up this book and see Canada differently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Wrist</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 18:48:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wrist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrist-by-nathan-niigan-noodin-adler:be8d3886104ef6a4ba40f052b87ecea4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; by Nathan Niigan Noodin Adler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; is an Anishinaabe-inspired horror story that I picked up at the Ottawa &lt;em&gt;Writersfest&lt;/em&gt; last year. One of the fun things about this book is that you&amp;rsquo;re never totally certain if the monsters are real. Adler keeps you guessing about whether this is playing out in the imagination of Church, the protagonist, even going so far as to include other characters who themselves don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the monsters. As Adler states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I]t will still devour you, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t believe.
Things that are real don&amp;rsquo;t need you to believe in them, they&amp;rsquo;ll consume you just the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we learn that Church is the son of a Residential school survivor on one side, and a Holocaust survivor on the other, we begin to recognize that perhaps the true horror story being told is the evil of intergenerational trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it was just a delusion [&amp;hellip;], it was real in every sense that mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about this book is that it&amp;rsquo;s not over-edited, so the voice of the author shines through unobscured, almost as though he&amp;rsquo;s reading aloud to you in the oral tradition of the First Nations. In fact, he provides substantial Anishinaabemowin dialog and terminology throughout the book, giving mild language lessons to his readers. I enjoyed reading the Anishinaabek words aloud softly as I went along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique aspect is the scientific emphasis throughout the story. Adler firmly places Indigenous lore within a natural, scientific world, for example beautifully comparing the hunger of the wiindigo to a black hole. Not only does this make the book feel real, almost alive, in a living, breathing kind of way, but also serves as a nice counterpoint to how colonialist society tends to portray Indigenous culture as cliché and static (&lt;em&gt;The Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt;*). Here we are given very much the opposite of that, with a cultural viewpoint that follows along with our evolving understanding of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunger is the central theme in this story, and Adler invites us to consider hunger as something abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we are driven to eat to fill other hungers that can&amp;rsquo;t be filled with food&amp;hellip;Loneliness, sadness, trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading this book during a period of personal grief, had me relating to this. Even though hunger is pain, hunger should not be indulged too deeply, but neither should it be ignored. Excess in either direction will turn one into a monster. That is the warning delivered in &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;. However hunger is also what makes us who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Church is not always sure exactly who he is supposed to be, yet he&amp;rsquo;s proof that one can derive tremendous power and self-worth out of personal beliefs and life experiences, even if many of those are hard experiences. And proof that nobody should be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;wrist&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is given in a preface to the book, with a secondary definition being &lt;em&gt;sleight-of-hand&lt;/em&gt;. So what sleight-of-hand is the author pulling with this novel &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;?  For me, it was filling my spirit with nature, language and appreciation for all that life has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a unique and very original book with many layers to unpack. I look forward to reading more of Adler&amp;rsquo;s work in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt; per Thomas King&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Inconvenient Indian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wristTwitter.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Enterprise Unleashed 2017</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 16:57:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday I was invited by &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; to attend the Social Enterprise Unleashed conference in Ottawa. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-procurement:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Social procurement:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procurement generally follows the &amp;ldquo;Lowest Price Wins&amp;rdquo; model, which misses opportunities to benefit communities and can even cause harm by not respecting the environment nor paying living wages. The triple-bottom-line approach of social enterprise (People, Planet, Profit) needs to be the ultimate goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inroads have been made in recent years on the &amp;ldquo;Planet&amp;rdquo; portion of this - when one thinks &amp;ldquo;sustainable&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s often environmental sustainability that comes to mind, however the &amp;ldquo;People&amp;rdquo; component is what needs focus next to make it truly sustainable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hospitals and police have been promoting social enterprise because they understand that social factors are required to keep people healthy and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.winnipegfreepress.com/opinion/analysis/social-solution-to-budget-woes-a-job-instead-of-prison-414837654.html&#34;&gt;reduce incarceration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should be aiming for a requirement such that when public money is spent on procurement it should include some form of social impact. Scotland is leading the way by requiring all government contracts to add social impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;storytelling-for-impact:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Storytelling for Impact:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General fundamentals of a story involve:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a character (the customer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who has a problem (villain, internal, external, philosophical)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who meets a guide (empathy/trust, authority)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who gives them a plan (process, agreement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and calls them to action (direct call, transitional call)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that ends in a success and helps them avoid failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and also results in a character transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer is the hero, not your brand. Brands that position themselves as heroes unknowingly compete with the customer. Position your brand in terms of what your customers want, not what you&amp;rsquo;re about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good story can not only promote the company externally but have transformational impact on employee engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78mNZeDaMtk?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the customer trust you? The answer is emotional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People want to be taken somewhere - transformation of character. Who does your customer want to become?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clusters-and-accelerators:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Clusters and Accelerators:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we stimulate demand?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we &amp;ldquo;pull&amp;rdquo; social enterprises in rather than enterprises having to push their product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clusters - why?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joint tendering (teaming up with other enterprises to deliver on large opportunities)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;purchasing power, economies of scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shared resources (space, transport, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;promotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning from each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food cluster in Ottawa is 30 enterprises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>