<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chad Adams</title>
    <link>http://cadams.ca/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 16:20:11 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://cadams.ca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Into the Silence</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 16:20:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/images/into-the-silence.png&#34; alt=&#34;Into the Silence&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-great-war-mallory-and-the-conquest-of-everest:430078025ad00d05681f6e91e31d9b31&#34;&gt;The Great War, Mallory, and the Conquest of Everest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; by Wade Davis recounts the failed 1920s Everest expeditions, the first ever attempts on the mountain. But it&amp;rsquo;s much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the climbers were shaped by the Great War, and so the book begins there. This leads into an engrossing look at the chaos, the folly, and the haunting reality of a generation of men who would return from war with wounds that could never heal. If the book had been solely these initial chapters on the war, and that was it, I would have been perfectly satisfied. What a treat to realize this was only the introduction, a springboard for what was still yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that stood out to me while reading this book is how these events were happening in a fairly modern, yet entirely different time. From a sensibilities point of view, the Great War had largely broken the spell of idealism, nobility, and purpose in many. Yet for others, it spurred a retreat away from the misery of daily life and towards a more idealistic meaning. The Everest expeditions could be seen as an outlet for the latter, and the men who volunteered were sometimes spiritual, sometimes adventure seekers, always in pursuit of something bigger than themselves. Davis does a nice job of interpreting these distinctions for the modern reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to tell you were being transported into another time is the wonderful collection of correspondence (yes, letter writing was a daily thing!) and it was at times extremely eloquent.. This was a vast wealth of primary material which Davis spent a decade researching, and it led to convincing character portraits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Death&amp;rsquo;s power lies in fear, which flourishes in the imagination and the unknown. For Wheeler there was nothing more that death could show him, short of his own.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tricky things as a reader is dealing with the large cast of characters involved, spanning three expeditions, and I admit to having some difficulty keeping all the persons straight in my head. In the first expedition, Davis had you cheering for the Canadian surveyor Wheeler who was not originally participating in a climbing role but nevertheless won over Mallory and the rest of the team and was ultimately appointed to the climbing party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the storylines in the second expedition, none resonated more than George Finch, the skinny scientist whose revolutionary tactics about bottled oxygen led him to achieve a new height record, despite far worse support than the main climbing party.  A Mallory/Finch climbing tandem is one of those &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; the reader can only wonder about..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that over the course of the book, neither through the author&amp;rsquo;s lens nor through Mallory&amp;rsquo;s personal writings, did I ever fully connect or empathize with Mallory. Hence the fateful end was not a tear jerker for me in the same way as other Everest &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Into_Thin_Air&#34;&gt;stories have been&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, Davis delivers an extremely powerful conclusion to the book. In stark contrast to all the earlier climbing activities, where every action can be analyzed and scrutinized through the heaps of correspondence, private writings, and post reflections by the principle actors, at the moment when Mallory and Irvine depart up the mountain together never to return, the author and his readers are left with a big hole of information to wonder about. We&amp;rsquo;re simply left with&amp;hellip; the silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s powerful and it will have your imagination running in overdrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the recounting of this climbing history leaves the reader a lasting impression of &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What If&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; as each expedition made mistakes (either through membership composition or on the mountain itself) or suffered unpreventable setbacks that taxed the climbers, preventing them from reaching their full potential. In ideal conditions, who can say how far they would have climbed? Or so the book suggests. But I think the real lesson of Everest, clear even in these first attempts at the mountain, is how normal this kind of result is. Sure you may be fit enough to climb the mountain, but count on dealing with any two or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;altitude sickness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inadequate support/teammates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avalanche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;illness/lack of nutrition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unforgiving weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical malfunction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of these obstacles, the early 1920&amp;rsquo;s expeditions were indisputably heroic achievements. From the personalities involved, to the politics of the region, to the sensibilities of the time, &lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; is a very human look at mount Everest and pushing into new frontiers. It is told through Davis&amp;rsquo; flowing prose, and it is a beautiful read. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration Testing with Node and Mongo</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/10/14/integration-testing-with-node-and-mongo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 22:31:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/10/14/integration-testing-with-node-and-mongo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been building &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cised-ca/social-enterprise-directory&#34;&gt;an application&lt;/a&gt; using Node.js with a MongoDB datastore. Now I want to perform some integration testing (&lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; mocking the DB layer) to ensure full end-to-end success of the application. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I went about doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;using-a-test-database:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Using a test database&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the goal is to execute code paths that go through Mongo, it will still be acceptable to execute against a different db than the one used for production deployments. This will ensure the test data never ends up in production by accident, and also avoids production data getting deleted by accident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, I&amp;rsquo;ll have the application connect to Mongo using a test connection string. This will be specified in a configuration file with suitable default value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the application creates the db collections on start up, there are no further pre-requisite Mongo commands to setup the test database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;starting-the-application:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Starting the application&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before any tests can run, the application needs to start up. So I wrote a simple &lt;code&gt;app_starter.js&lt;/code&gt; utility to boot the application into service with the appropriate test configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;starting-each-test-with-a-clean-datastore:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Starting each test with a clean datastore&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each test needs to be independent, so we can&amp;rsquo;t leave remnants in the datastore from a previous test. Hence the first thing I do at the start of each test is clean the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using Mocha as my test framework, so this gets implemented as a &lt;code&gt;beforeEach&lt;/code&gt; hook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;beforeEach( function(done) {
    dbUtil.cleanDatabase(done);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cleaning-the-datastore:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Cleaning the datastore&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very straightforward way to clean the datastore, is to drop the database and re-create it again. My application connects to the datastore using &lt;a href=&#34;mongoosejs.com&#34;&gt;Mongoose&lt;/a&gt;. With Mongoose, the database can be dropped with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function cleanDatabase(done) {
  mongoose.connection.db.dropDatabase(done);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now how do we re-create the database? Turns out Mongoose is kind enough to do this for you automatically under the hood, so nothing else to do. However there&amp;rsquo;s one more wrinkle to deal with&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mongoose will re-create the collections in the database on demand, but not the indexes. The indexes are only built during mongoose connection establishment. This means our tests won&amp;rsquo;t be able to execute successfully because the database indexes won&amp;rsquo;t be present. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at how to address that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;rebuilding-the-indexes:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Rebuilding the indexes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily Mongoose supplies an API to rebuild the indexes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mongoose.model(modelName).ensureIndexes();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes a little time to complete, so I had to register on &lt;code&gt;index&lt;/code&gt; event to listen for when it finishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mongoose.model(myModel).on(&#39;index&#39;, done);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the indexes are ready, the database is set for your test to begin. Here is the updated &lt;code&gt;cleanDatabase&lt;/code&gt; function which delegates to a rebuildIndexes helper function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function cleanDatabase(done) {
  mongoose.connection.db.dropDatabase( function() {
    rebuildIndexes(done);
  });
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find the full implementation &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cised-ca/social-enterprise-directory/blob/dd0c588843ffe014b0befd36e316beefa6bc181b/test/api/helpers/db/db_util.js&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;results:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That puts a simple automated integration test framework in place for application developers to work with. This should help ensure stability of the application over time as new features get added, while also allowing developers to take a TDD approach to feature development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my system it does take a few 100 ms to run each test due to the extra database overhead. Given the number of tests at the moment, this is not a concern. In the future if it somehow grows into a problem there are alternatives to dropping the database, such as removing the collections, which I&amp;rsquo;ve heard may improve execution performance. This would be easy to refactor in the future if needed, but I expect the current implementation will be just fine for a long while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation Skills Training</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/09/20/presentation-skills-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 22:31:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/09/20/presentation-skills-training/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently completed a two-day training course on presentation skills. While I have been known to give a killer presentation (or speech) in my time, doing so takes &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of preparation on my end and it&amp;rsquo;s never as natural as I would like. By taking this course, my goal was to hone my skills, practice a little more, and discover some new tips and tricks. Here are the main takeaways for me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a world of partial attention, so we &lt;strong&gt;cannot assume that our audience is engaged with us&lt;/strong&gt;. The presenter is competing for the audience&amp;rsquo;s attention with many other available sources of information (email, phones, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to compete with that, the key is to give a &lt;strong&gt;simple, authentic and meaningful&lt;/strong&gt; experience to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five principles can help us carry out this mission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passion (infectious, spreads energy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep it simple (only 3 key messages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less is more (don&amp;rsquo;t overload your messages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authenticity (something real)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storytelling (adds interest)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;planning-your-presentation:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Planning Your Presentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-based-presentations:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Goal based presentations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, decide what the goal of your presentation will be. Sounds obvious? Yet it&amp;rsquo;s fairly typical for me to jump straight into some random details in the middle of the presentation and start building up my slides from there without really knowing where I ultimately want the presentation to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think partly that has to do with the fear not wanting to lose the creative juices in the moment.. but creating anything that way can lead all over the map unless you manage to stay focused. Think about how many slides you throw out in the end because they are not relevant, don&amp;rsquo;t help support the main message, or else get cut due to time constraints for the presentation. That&amp;rsquo;s a lot of wasted time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead think about building scalable presentations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;45 second (elevator pitch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;45 minute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start small because that will force you to focus on the main message only. Then build out the details around it to fill in the time.
As a bonus, by creating your presentations this way, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to better adapt to being given less/more time on the day of the presentation, while also being ready to give the same presentation again in a different format should the need arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;know-the-audience:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Know the audience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know your audience! Can you find out any more about them and what they want before the presentation? This has burned me before by making wrong assumptions about what level of knowledge the audience was starting from. A simple question could have clarified that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to get your priorities right. Start with most important things for the audience. Sometimes that means beginning with the bottom line and getting into the justifications later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;designing-a-presentation:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Designing a Presentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;typical-presentation-flow:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Typical presentation flow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical presentation might flow like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question/Issue (the why)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key Message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples (stories, points to back up message)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat message and call to action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get to your central message &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;power-of-3-s:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Power of 3&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have short attention spans and a finite memory. Assume they can only take away &lt;strong&gt;3 things&lt;/strong&gt; from your presentation and no more. Have no more than 3 key ideas. Under each idea introduce no more than 3 related concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;opening-and-closing:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Opening and closing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The audience is most likely to remember your first and last words. So it&amp;rsquo;s definitely worth investing some extra time in your opening and closing remarks. Start with a hook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s a magical place in the world that not many have a chance to visit&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hooks work even for technical presentations. Change your opening from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Well not everyone is here yet, but let&amp;rsquo;s get started anyway..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Imagine a world where your network installs itself with one command..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which presentation would you rather be at?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the closing, saying &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;In conclusion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; is a good trick to get your audience perk up if they were not already awake. Try that with a louder voice, and use the extra attention gained to reinforce your key message or make a call to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;slide-design:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Slide design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen cluttered slides before? I knew that slides should be kept simple, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until this course that I realized just how simple that should be. Our instinct says &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I want to add as much content as I can to support my key message&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; but that line of thinking makes it very easy to overdo it. Think back to the world of partial attention: if someone is only going to glance at your slide for a short period of time, it needs to be extremely simple, clear and effective. Every word should be essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides should support the presentation, not replace it. It is not a handout. If you need a handout, make a different deck. That&amp;rsquo;s not the goal of presentation slides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep it to one message per slide. As few slides as possible.
And think about the Power of 3, no more than 3 bullet points per slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;handling-nerves:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Handling nerves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerves always get me. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter how friendly the room is. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter how much I&amp;rsquo;ve prepared (sometimes the more preparation the worse). It&amp;rsquo;s pretty normal for me to feel even slightly physically ill before a presentation, although I&amp;rsquo;m pretty good at hiding it and people have told me I don&amp;rsquo;t look nervous at all. Usually it goes away after the first minute or two of the presentation, but by then the damage has been done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course offered pretty rote advice for nerves:
&lt;em&gt;Acknowledge nervousness, use that energy. Visualize success, anticipate what parts might be tricky and plan through them, breathe, prepare, Smile!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rationally I agree, but I submit that those tips don&amp;rsquo;t exactly solve the problem for me. Ultimately, I think practice is really the only medicine here. Both practice in terms of simulating giving the specific presentation, as well as practice in terms of doing many presentations in general. If you were to give a big presentation every week, I think your coping mechanisms would eventually adapt. It reminds me of my university days, interviewing for co-op jobs each semester. The first interview is nervous as hell, but by the 10th interview you&amp;rsquo;ve got your delivery nailed and are actually looking forward to selling yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally there is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_shapes_who_you_are&#34;&gt;this talk by Amy Cuddy&lt;/a&gt; that provides a scientifically proven way to reduce your stress hormones before high pressure situations. I&amp;rsquo;m a bit skeptical but I guess it&amp;rsquo;s worth a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;passion:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Passion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the material is not something you are actually passionate about. That&amp;rsquo;s OK. Just know the message well, and make sure to lead the presentation (and don&amp;rsquo;t get led by the slides), and it will go over very well with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If audience is not looking involved, start a dialogue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are asked a question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank and acknowledge the person (or their emotion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;You make an excellent point&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I can see why this concerns you so let&amp;rsquo;s address that..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I think many others are probably feeling the same&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I can see you feel very strongly about that..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clarify and repeat the question to ensure broad understanding and give yourself time to answer. &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; be judgmental&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep excellent eye contact throughout the question and answer, then break off contact and deliberately move away to communicate that you are moving on in your presentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Often deadly questions are based on assumptions. Challenge the assumption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Change emphasis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Negative to positive like &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;yes, that&amp;rsquo;s true we do charge more, but&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General to specific or specific to general.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Break into long winded questioners when they take a breath with &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I believe I can answer that&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember your time frame and move on&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;remote-presentations:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Remote presentations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When presenting remotely or by conference call make sure to smile and keep good posture because it will show in your voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, this was a valuable training course for me. The biggest eye opener was seeing how principles like storytelling and hooks can apply even for technical presentation topics, which is my main domain of interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t see many presentations doing that in my workplace. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping I can take these lessons and apply them going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mindset</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 23:11:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carol Dweck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Success-Carol-Dweck/dp/0345472322&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindset: The New Psychology of Success&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; summarizes the ground-breaking research she and others have been leading on the subjects of motivation, identity, self-awareness and ability. All of these, it turns out, can be influenced significantly by one&amp;rsquo;s mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her most famous experiment involves taking two groups of kids and giving each kid an easy puzzle to solve. She then praised one group of kids for being smart, but praised the other group for their effort. Then she observed how the performance of these two groups differed over time, and they did dramatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those praised for being smart were less willing to take on harder challenges, did worse on subsequent administered challenges (even when a challenge similar to the original in difficulty was re-administered), and even lied about their performance scores. She was quite surprised to find that her praise transformed kids into liars! The book was written a decade ago, with over a million copies sold, so I&amp;rsquo;m hoping this has become more common knowledge now to many people as it&amp;rsquo;s quite important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first group, as a result of the praise, the children were nudged into taking a &lt;em&gt;fixed mindset&lt;/em&gt; about intelligence. This is the idea that your natural abilities are permanent. In this view, while anybody can learn new things, the overall intelligence (or ability) that you bring to the table is fixed. Similar to thinking that everyone has pretty much one IQ score and it won&amp;rsquo;t change. Do you share this mindset?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other group was nudged into the &lt;em&gt;growth mindset&lt;/em&gt;. That is, believing that our abilities can be developed through experience - including our intelligence. It is the belief that by working through difficult things we can improve ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might find you have a fixed mindset about some things and not others. Consider the two paragraphs above, but what if you replace &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;artistic ability&amp;rdquo;? &amp;hellip;sports? &amp;hellip;leadership?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has since done all kinds of experiments on people of all ages to test these beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that people who have a growth mindset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more willing, even eager, to take on harder challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tend to view mistakes as learning opportunities rather than attacks on their identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more resilient when hit by negative labels, negative stereotyping, or depression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have more accurate estimations about their own abilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generally end up succeeding/performing better over time, even showing bumps in IQ in some studies on kids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems the growth mindset is the way to go, no? Trouble is you might have one mindset or the other and not even be aware of it. Luckily, it is possible to switch mindsets. The scary thing to me is just how easy it can be to do so at times. Many of the mentioned studies were able to switch their subjects into one mindset or the other before evaluating them (as she demonstrated with those kids). Makes you wonder how we all individually and as a society contribute towards inadvertently conjuring one mindset over the other in those around us. This truly has serious implications on parenting, teaching and coaching. Never call your kids smart! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all really interesting for sure, but how about the book itself? Dweck begins by presenting the mindset concepts to the reader (so far so good), but then she takes us on a journey of looking at the world through a &amp;ldquo;mindset&amp;rdquo; lens. She focuses on celebrities in history across various domains (business, sports, coaching), and shows us examples of both fixed mindset and growth mindset people. For example, she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s who she thinks hold a fixed mindset and explains how this contributed to their failure at business. Then she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s with a growth mindset and shows how it contributed to their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the book at its worst, in my opinion. This is anecdotal evidence at best. She is making assumptions about their mindsets based on observed behaviour, but she has not actually tested these people, or if she did she does not mention it. Anyone can cherry pick examples to prove a point, and I quickly got frustrated and fed up of reading these anecdotal examples that weren&amp;rsquo;t adding any substance to the argument. Unfortunately these are &lt;em&gt;littered&lt;/em&gt; throughout the book. She has a tendency to follow up each proposition with an anecdote. This shows up in the form: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A study by ABC has shown that fixed mindset people are less resilient to XYZ. For example, Billy was an elementary school student and&amp;hellip; [Billy&amp;rsquo;s story goes here]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I am more technically-inclined than most, but these anecdotes are fluff and I would prefer if she had included more experiment details and their specific results. She also avoided almost any discussion of quantitative results, perhaps thinking percentages and the like might scare aware her audience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the sheer significance of the research being shared here overcomes any failings in the presentation. &lt;strong&gt;Read this book&lt;/strong&gt; if you have the chance. My recommendation is to read the first couple of chapters on the basic concepts, then &lt;strong&gt;skip entirely&lt;/strong&gt; the fluff chapters on business, sports, and coaching (you can return to them later if you really want to). Instead proceed straight to the parenting and teaching chapter, which is the most important I think.  Also feel free to skip any anecdotal stories if you are getting fed up with them, you won&amp;rsquo;t miss anything! I read the book aloud this way to my wife as she drove us across the Yukon, and we both enjoyed the book much better that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has written a few articles since the book was published. Further reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-secret-to-raising-smart-kids1/&#34;&gt;The Secret to Raising Smart Kids - Scientific American article by Carol Dweck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edweek.org/ew/articles/2015/09/23/carol-dweck-revisits-the-growth-mindset.html&#34;&gt;Carol Dweck Revisits the &amp;lsquo;Growth Mindset&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Quantum Night</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 17:02:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/1/18/Quantum_Night_by_Robert_J._Sawyer_Book_Cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_Night&#34;&gt;Quantum Night&lt;/a&gt; is the latest from Canadian sci-fi author Robert Sawyer. In it, two researchers independently discover two techniques to identify psychopaths objectively, and they come together to try and figure out the implications of their discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting themes raised in the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are the ethics for research on human subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;why are there so many people all over the world doing terrible things, all the time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are people still responsible for their actions even if they are physically &amp;ldquo;hard-wired&amp;rdquo; to be that way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;herd mentality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tensions between tribal loyalty and the greater good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me about this book is how &amp;ldquo;un-fictiony&amp;rdquo; it felt for sci-fi. I am glad that Sawyer took on the topic of psychology which is extremely relevant in today&amp;rsquo;s society.. In the age of Brexit and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://qz.com/723537/in-the-post-factual-democracy-politicians-win-by-getting-feelings-right-and-facts-wrong/&#34;&gt;post-factual democracy&lt;/a&gt;, human psychology has been harnessed/exploited by corporations, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.ca/Enlightenment-2-0-Restoring-Politics-Economy/dp/0062342894&#34;&gt;politicians&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rushkoff.com/staying-human-machine-age-interview-douglas-rushkoff/&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, military, and on and on.. It can get a little depressing to think about, knowing we are mostly helpless agents against ourselves. Of course there are good guys working other angles too (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nudge_(book)&#34;&gt;Nudge&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is possible to become self-aware of our own individual psychological tendencies, and to recognize if someone is using questionable tactics to convince us of something, this takes &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&#34;&gt;a lot of effort&lt;/a&gt;, and thus it&amp;rsquo;s practically impossible to completely eliminate our innate tendencies entirely. Even if one person could do it, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly not possible to achieve this at the larger level of a society. Ultimately, then, I think our society is bound to suffer further Brexit and Trump-like eventualities, until such time we consciously reorganize our institutions (political systems, corporations, etc) to properly take into account the fallibilities of human psychology and put in guards against their exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds a bit crazy, but machines might actually be able to help us here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pzs:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;PZs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another topic raised in the book is the concept of &amp;ldquo;pz&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; as Sawyer called them, people who act and behave just like normal people but internally (unbeknownst to anyone), are not actually conscious. While these people were viewed with horror and disdain (at least by the characters in the novel), it did occur to me that this notion of a clear mind / living entirely in the moment, is something of an achievement if you are an existentialist or a Buddhist. There are people actively trying to blot out their consciousness for a few moments of zen. So maybe a lifetime of pz would represent the ultimate fulfillment? Or does it only count if you consciously surrender your consciousness? ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really enjoyed the book although the ending felt a little rushed, and I kept hoping for one final twist that never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I love about Sawyer&amp;rsquo;s novels are the education factor. While you keep turning the pages to see how the story unfolds, there are plenty of interesting ideas and references scattered throughout, bread crumbs to return to later and revisit should you wish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: What Does It Mean To Be Human</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/06/29/book-review-what-does-it-mean-to-be-human/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 19:49:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/06/29/book-review-what-does-it-mean-to-be-human/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/images/whatDoesItMeanToBeHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;What Does It Mean to Be Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.ca/books?id=DgE8ITskDEcC&#34;&gt;What Does it Mean to be Human&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the companion book for the Smithsonian Natural History Museum&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://humanorigins.si.edu/&#34;&gt;Human Origins&lt;/a&gt; initiative. The book takes the reader on a breathtaking journey through our ancient past to explain when and how we acquired the traits we most closely associate with modern humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-of-these-are-human-but-not-homo-sapiens:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;All of these are human, but not &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Although you could be forgiven for mistaking one!)
&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/images/humans.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Humans&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book covers many topics on the history of our species, I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on three of the items that I found most fascinating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Eating meat was a factor in our advanced intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Climate change made us who we are&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. We almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meat-fuels-our-brains:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Meat Fuels Our Brains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important aspect of our ancestry is that we became heavy meat eaters. Stone tools (used for over a million years) let us hunt and carve up bigger game. As our meat consumption increased, our digestive system evolved and shortened in order to rapidly extract nutrients from meat, as opposed to taking days to digest plants as they pass through a long intestine. This reduction in gut size allowed humans to divert precious energy to other organs in the body, such as the brain, which today uses as much as 25% of our total energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The dietary shift toward meat and the reduction in gut size are likely to have proved crucial in fueling the evolution of an enlarged brain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that eating meat caused our brains to grow, but rather as other stresses pushed us toward a need for greater intelligence, meat gave us the means to evolve our bodies in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While meat is now classified a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.who.int/features/qa/cancer-red-meat/en/&#34;&gt;probable carcinogen&lt;/a&gt;, and limited consumption is suggested for both health and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cowspiracy.com/infographic&#34;&gt;environmental&lt;/a&gt; reasons, it was nevertheless a key factor in getting us where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climate-change-made-us-human:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Climate Change Made Us Human&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans developed in one of the most geologically volatile eras of the Earth. Wild fluctuations from cold to hot, wet to dry, and back meant that survival was always dependent on being adaptable. In the last 100,000 years for example the Earth went from hippos living in England to permafrost covering almost all of Europe. Even the cold-hardened Neanderthals had to retreat all the way down to Gibraltar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fluctuations in climate led us to where we are today. The ability to stand upright gave us the opportunity to travel long distances efficiently, allowing us to move with, and according, to the changing environment. The stresses of continuous climate change led to advances in imagination, planning, symbols and memory as our mental and social tools evolved to better respond to change and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A species that does a lot of things well retains more options when its surroundings change.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, our species &lt;strong&gt;optimized itself for change&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as for our ancestors, climate change continues to be a hot topic for us today, this time through our own actions. Fittingly, solving today&amp;rsquo;s problem will require us to attain a new level of humanity - large-scale co-operation is now required on a global scale. Just as before, the challenges we face define who we will become as a species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-almost-didn-t-make-it:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;We Almost Didn&amp;rsquo;t Make It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; is but one species in a large human family tree. Most branches led to evolutionary dead ends, including 20+ other hominid species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our closest evolutionary cousins - species that also walked upright, made tools, and had large brains - went extinct, even though these basic characteristics were at one time considered to be the hallmarks of evolutionary success in human beings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sorely wish that at least &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; other species in the &lt;em&gt;Homo&lt;/em&gt; group had survived to the present day. Most of us have likely heard about the existence of other human species (such as Neanderthals), along with the fact we actually share DNA with our cousin species (my immediate family is 2.1% Neanderthal for example, roughly average for those of non-African ethnicity). Yet these links do not feel as immediate as they might if there were a living breathing community sharing the Earth with us. Imagine the new perspective this would inform, about our place in the universe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Or not - on the other hand I shudder to think how we would have treated our cousin species, given how poorly we behave to members of our own species who are merely different.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, just like our cousin species, Homo sapiens almost went extinct in our own right. DNA evidence suggests that at one point our breeding population may have been as low as 2,000 people, possibly even as few as 600 individuals. It makes you realize how much of our success was left to chance, as it could easily have been another hominid species, perhaps the Neanderthals or some new descendent, writing the history books about us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What Does it Mean to be Human&lt;/em&gt; tells us that we are a species very much in flux; not a polished product but a moment in time. We have a long history. Older than culture, spanning species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book is focused solely on the past, it cannot help but lead to questions about our future. If part of being human means innovating, or having an imagination, as these distinguish us from earlier species - then what happens when machines can also innovate and dream? Will some different human characteristic take larger significance to us in the future and provide deep meaning to our descendants, such as perhaps, death? What does it really mean to be human, after all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you find yourself in Washington DC, check out the exhibit at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://humanorigins.si.edu/&#34;&gt;Smithsonian Natural History museum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/&#34;&gt;Genographic Project&lt;/a&gt; by National Geographic is an interesting way to learn about your own personal lineage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Hacks of Kindness 2016</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/06/25/random-hacks-of-kindness-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 21:28:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/06/25/random-hacks-of-kindness-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I participated in a hackathon for &lt;a href=&#34;http://rhok.ca/&#34;&gt;Random Hacks of Kindness&lt;/a&gt; where the goal is to support community organizations with tech solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the project for the Centre for Social Enterprise Development (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cised.ca/&#34;&gt;CISED&lt;/a&gt;). A &lt;em&gt;social enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is a venture whose purpose is to achieve a social mission. There are about 150 social enterprises in Ottawa, which includes ventures such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ReStore - accepts donated home products then refurbishes and resells them in their retail stores with all proceeds going to Habitat for Humanity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laundry Matters - employees with developmental disabilities provide residential and commercial laundry services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good Nature Groundskeeping:  provides professional landscape maintenance services while also providing employment to people who are economically disadvantaged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge for CISED is to grow the social enterprise sector. While there is increasing awareness about social enterprises and a willingness on the purchasing side to procure their services, currently the main challenges are the lack of awareness of what services are available (for example I had only heard of about 3 of the 150 companies myself), and the ability to connect the buyers with the sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hackathon began with an energizing discussion with the stakeholders from CISED about how to connect purchasers and suppliers in an online marketplace. We went into details such as the three main types of purchasers involved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large business procurement (government or companies looking to support social enterprises, perhaps to meet internal procurement targets)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small to medium independent business owners (perhaps looking to reinforce their brands or support the community)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The general public (people like you and me who would like to have their snow cleared all the while knowing the proceeds will support people in need in the community)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While CISED felt that the large procurers would be the most important clients to focus on as it would be the best shot at growing the social enterprise sector, the use cases involved with these purchasers were rather complex, such as dealing with scenarios where demand outstrips supply. Since social enterprises often have limited resources, if an order came in from a big client, such as a catering order, it might require two different catering companies to satisfy. It would be rather involved to support this kind of order on an online system, but could perhaps be achieved by allowing buyers to post RFPs or a similar concept (kind of like wanted ads on kijiji).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, we knew we could not build an online marketplace in 24 hours. However, there was something we could do to further the cause for all types of purchasers: build an online directory of social enterprises in Ottawa. This would satisfy an immediate need, as CISED often gets asked about what services are on offer, and currently this info is only available in a spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals of the directory would be online, public, fully searchable, and managed by CISED. New enterprises would apply to CISED for inclusion, and get vetted before being accepted. The directory would replace the current spreadsheet tracking system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we decided that Wordpress was a good technology choice for this problem. A CMS system would allow CISED to manage the list of social enterprises on an ongoing basis with minimal technical expertise required. Plugins could be used to import and export the database as needed. We could deliver the solution in 24 hours in a state that was actually useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivered code is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rhok2016-cised/cised-directory&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rhok2016-cised/cised-directory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that CISED will find this useful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with Hugo Templates</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/06/04/working-with-hugo-templates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 10:53:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/06/04/working-with-hugo-templates/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Hugo uses templates to generate HTML pages. This lets you control your generated HTML content with the help of simple logic. For example, logic such as ranging over all blog posts so that you can print them one at a time onto the page. Hugo uses the &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/pkg/html/template/&#34;&gt;Go html/template&lt;/a&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A template can describe an entire page, or just a small portion of a page (for example, just the copyright notice, the header, the footer, etc.). When this happens it is called a &lt;em&gt;partial template&lt;/em&gt;, and that template can be reused just about anywhere else in your website.  Partials are especially useful in Hugo themes, as it gives you the option to override just a small part of the layout to suit your needs. As mentioned in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/29/customizing-hugo-themes/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, overriding any file in a theme is as simple as dropping in your own version of the file with the same name. Thus templates can be overriden the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;modifying-the-hyde-x-theme:aca756b519d0e7970786722619fbfdb0&#34;&gt;Modifying the Hyde-X theme&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zyro/hyde-x&#34;&gt;Hyde-X&lt;/a&gt; theme by default provides nice looking links at the top of each post, based on the post&amp;rsquo;s meta content (such as the links marked &amp;ldquo;hugo&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;blog&amp;rdquo; which you can see at the top of this post). However, Hyde-X only supports those links for &lt;em&gt;categories&lt;/em&gt;, and I wanted links for &lt;em&gt;tags&lt;/em&gt;, which are two different meta data taxonomies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brought me to my first encounter with Hugo templating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this, first I extracted the links section into its own partial template, where it could be customized independently from the rest of the theme. Then I made a configuration item to control which taxonomies to create links for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the quirks I encountered along the way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Appending strings&lt;/em&gt;. The Hugo template language has limited support for many of the features available in Go. I needed to append the &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; character to a variable, but there is no append function. Turns out this can be done with &lt;a href=&#34;https://discuss.gohugo.io/t/concatenating-strings-with-print/711&#34;&gt;print function&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;(print $itemToLink &amp;quot;/&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Passing values to partial templates&lt;/em&gt;. After generating the links, the theme either needs to print a newline following the links (in case of blog post), or else print a dot separator (in case of list view, as seen when you click on one of the tag links). Hence I wanted to give a parameter to my partial template to specify how to handle the separator. Solution: this can be achieved by &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/templates/functions#dict&#34;&gt;passing a map into a partial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Variable scope&lt;/em&gt;. I needed a way to check if a post had any links to display, and so I wanted to store this in a flag variable. However, ranging over a collection creates a new scope and so all modifications to variables within (such as the flag) are lost outside this scope. The solution was to use Hugo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/extras/scratch/&#34;&gt;Scratch&lt;/a&gt; feature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;contributing-back:aca756b519d0e7970786722619fbfdb0&#34;&gt;Contributing back&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of overriding the theme just on my own personal website, I thought this feature could be generally useful to others who are using the theme. So I made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zyro/hyde-x/pull/65&#34;&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; to contribute this back to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Customizing Hugo Themes</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/29/customizing-hugo-themes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 15:46:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/29/customizing-hugo-themes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hugo.spf13.com/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; has a straight forward yet powerful strategy for theming websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to &lt;a href=&#34;http://themes.gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;choose a theme&lt;/a&gt; to use, as your baseline. In an &lt;a href=&#34;http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/24/getting-started-with-hugo/&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned that I picked &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zyro/hyde-x&#34;&gt;Hyde-X&lt;/a&gt; for this website. I liked the general design of Hyde but wanted the extra features provided by Hyde-X such as pagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point your website will take on the default appearance of the theme. Most themes will also support some kind of configuration parameters out of the box, so this is usually the first step towards customization. For example, Hyde-X lets you configure your social media links, what syntax highlighting to use, and how you want your content paginated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point you might want to tweak your website in a way that is not directly configurable through the theme. This is normal and expected, since everyone has unique needs for their sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately Hugo has a general convention for &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/themes/customizing/&#34;&gt;overriding themes&lt;/a&gt;. Hugo lets you supplement or override any template or static file (which includes stuff like CSS, etc). Hence when you customize a theme, you don&amp;rsquo;t edit the theme&amp;rsquo;s files directly. Rather, you supply your own versions of those files, which then take precendence over that of the theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One simple example is the favicon. I simply dropped my custom icon into&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;static/favicon.png
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that takes precendence over the theme&amp;rsquo;s file of the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next post I will go a bit further into more complex customizations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting a Hugo site on GitHub Pages</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/26/hosting-a-hugo-site-on-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 11:57:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/26/hosting-a-hugo-site-on-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/24/getting-started-with-hugo/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I created a static website using Hugo. This article explains how to host such a site for free, using GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-pages:880a44ed049d0dd561a1cb819f7c9037&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub Pages is a website hosting service provided by GitHub. If you are willing to publish your website in a git repository on GitHub then GitHub Pages will serve your website for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The requirements are that your github repo must be named &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.github.io&lt;/code&gt; and the repo should contain an index.html file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-pages-and-hugo:880a44ed049d0dd561a1cb819f7c9037&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages and Hugo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/24/getting-started-with-hugo/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; Hugo generates a &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; directory with the full contents of the website. In order to host that on GitHub Pages, we&amp;rsquo;ll simply need to put the contents of the &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; folder in an appropriately named github repo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/chad-g-adams.github.io&#34;&gt;chad-g-adams.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few minutes, the website will be live at &lt;a href=&#34;http://chad-g-adams.github.io/&#34;&gt;http://chad-g-adams.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;syncing-hugo-content-with-github-pages:880a44ed049d0dd561a1cb819f7c9037&#34;&gt;Syncing Hugo content with GitHub Pages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have two git repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One for holding the website content: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/chad-g-adams-hugo&#34;&gt;chad-g-adams-hugo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And one for holding the actual generated website which is used for hosting: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/chad-g-adams.github.io&#34;&gt;chad-g-adams.github.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue is, when I make changes to my site content (by working in the first repo), I would like to see those changes applied to second repo so that it can take effect on &lt;a href=&#34;http://chad-g-adams.github.io/&#34;&gt;http://chad-g-adams.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While inside my first repository, when I generate my website using command &lt;code&gt;hugo serve&lt;/code&gt;a folder called &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; is generated in the working directory. Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be great if that folder could be automatically part of the second git repo? In other words, having one git repo inside of another?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be accomplished in different ways. Probably the simplest way is to add &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; of the parent repo, and then clone the child repo separately into that directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way is to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Tools-Submodules&#34;&gt;git submodules&lt;/a&gt;. This allows you to keep a git repository as a subdirectory of another git repository. The advantage is that when you run &lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt; in the parent repo it will now also summarize the status of the child repo to remind you if there are outstanding changes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;modified:   public/ (new commits, modified content)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, Hugo will now generate the site content directly into the second repo where it can then be easily committed and pushed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-hugo-generation:880a44ed049d0dd561a1cb819f7c9037&#34;&gt;A note on Hugo generation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo assumes the &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; directory is empty when it generates the content. For that reason you should clean out the directory before re-generation or you risk deleted posts/pages living on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;automating-the-deploy-steps:880a44ed049d0dd561a1cb819f7c9037&#34;&gt;Automating the Deploy Steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to automate the various steps required to deploy my website, I created a simple script &lt;code&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; to run all the steps in one shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/usr/bin/sh

# clean any old website data
rm -r public/*

# generate new website data
hugo

# commit and push the new content
cd public
git add -A
git commit -m &amp;quot;website update&amp;quot;
git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started With Hugo</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/24/getting-started-with-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 09:27:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/24/getting-started-with-hugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up a website these days can be done at no cost other than a bit of time. I thought it would be interesting to spend a weekend playing around with some of the available tools. This article covers how I set up my site, using &lt;a href=&#34;http://hugo.spf13.com/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; to generate my content, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; to host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;hugo:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simple sites, such as blogs, there are good reasons to prefer static site generators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better security&lt;/strong&gt;: everything becomes simple static content so it significantly limits the areas of exposure to hackers; there are no logins, passwords, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt;: the site will load quickly and be responsive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline editing&lt;/strong&gt;: I can continue to create content when I&amp;rsquo;m offline, although that is becoming less and less of an issue these days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hugo.spf13.com/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; is a static site generator written in Go. I chose Hugo because it was open source with an active community, and because I also have an interest in learning the Go language (not that you need worry about that when building your website with Hugo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;hugo-workflow:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Hugo Workflow&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Hugo was an absolute pleasure. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/quickstart/&#34;&gt;good tutorials&lt;/a&gt; on Hugo available, so I will just cover some of the highlights here to demonstrate how easy it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-new-site:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Creating a new site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One simple command will create you a new site&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo new site mySiteName
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create a new folder called &lt;code&gt;mySiteName/&lt;/code&gt; and bootstrap it with the required directory structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;create-new-content:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Create new content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a new post is as simple as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo new post/my-post-name.md
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post file &lt;code&gt;my-post-name.md&lt;/code&gt; appears in the &lt;code&gt;mySiteName/content/post/&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic premise of Hugo is that your content is organized in a specific way on purpose. Hence the filesystem organization of your content matches the URL at which it is hosted. For example content file at &lt;code&gt;content/foo/bar/myFirstPost.md&lt;/code&gt; will be hosted at &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;site&amp;gt;/foo/bar/myFirstPost&lt;/code&gt; (By default - however that is fully configurable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;editing-content:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Editing content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post content is generally a plain text file (which means I am writing everything in vim, hooray!). Hugo has native support for &lt;a href=&#34;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/basics&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every content file begins with a section of metadata that allows you to specify information about the content, like the title, date, tags, or any arbitrary data you would use to classify your content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pick-a-theme:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Pick a Theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next you pick a theme for your site. I used &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zyro/hyde-x&#34;&gt;hyde-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, with a few tweaks (more to come on that in a later post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preview-your-site:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Preview Your Site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, we have some content now, let&amp;rsquo;s test it out. Hugo comes with a built-in HTTP server. Launch the server with a simple command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo serve
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And connect a browser to the endpoint to view your site. Boom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could it be any easier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a cool feature: your browser &lt;em&gt;automatically updates instantly&lt;/em&gt; as you edit your site&amp;rsquo;s content! This makes your web development cycle a very tight loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publish-your-site:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;Publish Your Site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;re satisfied with your site, it&amp;rsquo;s time to publish. Running the command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generates a folder &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; with all the static HTML, CSS, etc needed for your site.  That folder can then be dropped onto a web server, or hosted by an external service (such as GitHub Pages - I will be going into that in &lt;a href=&#34;http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/26/hosting-a-hugo-site-on-github-pages/&#34;&gt;my next post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-hugo-content:86024dcf7244259db6089302c01d25e4&#34;&gt;My Hugo Content&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, the Hugo code for this website can be found on my github repo &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/chad-g-adams-hugo&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Post</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/21/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 11:36:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/post/2016/05/21/first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Testing 1, 2, 3&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Lorem dim sum BBQ pork puff Pan friend pork dumpling Pot sticker water chestnut cake bitter melon beef dumplings turnip cake leek dumplings deep fried taro turnover Cha siu sou Cheong fan
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generated by &lt;a href=&#34;http://loremdimsum.com/&#34;&gt;Lorem Dim Sum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://hugo.spf13.com/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; blog. Hungry yet? :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/license/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;license:53e892b8b41cc4caece1cfd5ef21d6e7&#34;&gt;License&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All non-code content is licensed under &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All code content is licensed under MIT License&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MIT License&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright &amp;copy; 2016 Chad Adams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;ldquo;Software&amp;rdquo;), to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &amp;ldquo;AS IS&amp;rdquo;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>