<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Csed on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/csed/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Csed on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 14:53:22 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/csed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>RiseToTheOccasion.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 14:53:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/rtto.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;
A directory I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://RiseToTheOccasion.ca&#34;&gt;RiseToTheOccasion.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a provincial directory of social enterprises for the event planning sector. If you&amp;rsquo;re planning to put on an event in Ontario, you might like to see what&amp;rsquo;s available, with over 80 enterprises currently listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding on the product delivered by our previous project (the Ottawa directory &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt;), the new directory adds the following enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bilingual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location-based searching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;administrative interface, so that individual enterprises as well as directory administrators can control content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directory was officially launched at the &lt;em&gt;#SEUnleashed&lt;/em&gt; social enterprise conference in Ottawa on November 16th. As a contributor I was invited to attend the conference. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector. I posted more about the conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WeAllProfit.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/12/13/weallprofit.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 07:03:15 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/12/13/weallprofit.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A website I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a directory of social enterprises in Ottawa. A &lt;em&gt;social enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is a venture which has a  mission that goes beyond profit. This can mean offering employment to vulnerable or disabled people, protecting the environment, or passing their profits on to a charitable organization. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; for many examples of social enterprises in Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website will serve customers of the social enterprise sector by gathering all the local enterprises listings in one place, where a potential customer such as yourself can discover and browse the offerings. We hope this will inspire you to shop in the social enterprise sector, and we are looking forward to adding many more enterprises as we go!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>