<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 18:48:30 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://cadams.ca/blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Wrist</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 18:48:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/wrist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrist-by-nathan-niigan-noodin-adler:be8d3886104ef6a4ba40f052b87ecea4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; by Nathan Niigan Noodin Adler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; is an Anishinaabe-inspired horror story that I picked up at the Ottawa &lt;em&gt;Writersfest&lt;/em&gt; last year. One of the fun things about this book is that you&amp;rsquo;re never totally certain if the monsters are real. Adler keeps you guessing about whether this is playing out in the imagination of Church, the protagonist, even going so far as to include other characters who themselves don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the monsters. As Adler states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I]t will still devour you, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t believe.
Things that are real don&amp;rsquo;t need you to believe in them, they&amp;rsquo;ll consume you just the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we learn that Church is the son of a Residential school survivor on one side, and a Holocaust survivor on the other, we begin to recognize that perhaps the true horror story being told is the evil of intergenerational trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it was just a delusion [&amp;hellip;], it was real in every sense that mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about this book is that it&amp;rsquo;s not over-edited, so the voice of the author shines through unobscured, almost as though he&amp;rsquo;s reading aloud to you in the oral tradition of the First Nations. In fact, he provides substantial Anishinaabemowin dialog and terminology throughout the book, giving mild language lessons to his readers. I enjoyed reading the Anishinaabek words aloud softly as I went along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique aspect is the scientific emphasis throughout the story. Adler firmly places Indigenous lore within a natural, scientific world, for example beautifully comparing the hunger of the wiindigo to a black hole. Not only does this make the book feel real, almost alive, in a living, breathing kind of way, but also serves as a nice counterpoint to how colonialist society tends to portray Indigenous culture as cliché and static (&lt;em&gt;The Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt;*). Here we are given very much the opposite of that, with a cultural viewpoint that follows along with our evolving understanding of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunger is the central theme in this story, and Adler invites us to consider hunger as something abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we are driven to eat to fill other hungers that can&amp;rsquo;t be filled with food&amp;hellip;Loneliness, sadness, trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading this book during a period of personal grief, had me relating to this. Even though hunger is pain, hunger should not be indulged too deeply, but neither should it be ignored. Excess in either direction will turn one into a monster. That is the warning delivered in &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;. However hunger is also what makes us who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Church is not always sure exactly who he is supposed to be, yet he&amp;rsquo;s proof that one can derive tremendous power and self-worth out of personal beliefs and life experiences, even if many of those are hard experiences. And proof that nobody should be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;wrist&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is given in a preface to the book, with a secondary definition being &lt;em&gt;sleight-of-hand&lt;/em&gt;. So what sleight-of-hand is the author pulling with this novel &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;?  For me, it was filling my spirit with nature, language and appreciation for all that life has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a unique and very original book with many layers to unpack. I look forward to reading more of Adler&amp;rsquo;s work in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt; per Thomas King&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Inconvenient Indian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Enterprise Unleashed 2017</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 16:57:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday I was invited by &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; to attend the Social Enterprise Unleashed conference in Ottawa. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-procurement:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Social procurement:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procurement generally follows the &amp;ldquo;Lowest Price Wins&amp;rdquo; model, which misses opportunities to benefit communities and can even cause harm by not respecting the environment nor paying living wages. The triple-bottom-line approach of social enterprise (People, Planet, Profit) needs to be the ultimate goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inroads have been made in recent years on the &amp;ldquo;Planet&amp;rdquo; portion of this - when one thinks &amp;ldquo;sustainable&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s often environmental sustainability that comes to mind, however the &amp;ldquo;People&amp;rdquo; component is what needs focus next to make it truly sustainable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hospitals and police have been promoting social enterprise because they understand that social factors are required to keep people healthy and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.winnipegfreepress.com/opinion/analysis/social-solution-to-budget-woes-a-job-instead-of-prison-414837654.html&#34;&gt;reduce incarceration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should be aiming for a requirement such that when public money is spent on procurement it should include some form of social impact. Scotland is leading the way by requiring all government contracts to add social impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;storytelling-for-impact:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Storytelling for Impact:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General fundamentals of a story involve:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a character (the customer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who has a problem (villain, internal, external, philosophical)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who meets a guide (empathy/trust, authority)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who gives them a plan (process, agreement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and calls them to action (direct call, transitional call)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that ends in a success and helps them avoid failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and also results in a character transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer is the hero, not your brand. Brands that position themselves as heroes unknowingly compete with the customer. Position your brand in terms of what your customers want, not what you&amp;rsquo;re about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good story can not only promote the company externally but have transformational impact on employee engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78mNZeDaMtk?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the customer trust you? The answer is emotional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People want to be taken somewhere - transformation of character. Who does your customer want to become?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clusters-and-accelerators:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Clusters and Accelerators:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we stimulate demand?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we &amp;ldquo;pull&amp;rdquo; social enterprises in rather than enterprises having to push their product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clusters - why?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joint tendering (teaming up with other enterprises to deliver on large opportunities)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;purchasing power, economies of scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shared resources (space, transport, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;promotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning from each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food cluster in Ottawa is 30 enterprises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RiseToTheOccasion.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 14:53:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/rtto.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;
A directory I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://RiseToTheOccasion.ca&#34;&gt;RiseToTheOccasion.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a provincial directory of social enterprises for the event planning sector. If you&amp;rsquo;re planning to put on an event in Ontario, you might like to see what&amp;rsquo;s available, with over 80 enterprises currently listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding on the product delivered by our previous project (the Ottawa directory &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt;), the new directory adds the following enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bilingual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location-based searching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;administrative interface, so that individual enterprises as well as directory administrators can control content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directory was officially launched at the &lt;em&gt;#SEUnleashed&lt;/em&gt; social enterprise conference in Ottawa on November 16th. As a contributor I was invited to attend the conference. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector. I posted more about the conference &lt;a href=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Dirt Cure</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:15:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/dirtCure.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dirt-cure-by-maya-shetreat-klein:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; by Maya Shetreat-Klein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this book awhile ago with my wife, and wanted circle back and do a recap. &lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; argues that far from being something harmful to be avoided, dirt is actually rather healthy - more specifically, the microbes living in the dirt. This basic premise leads to insights into diet and illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maya’s philosophy is that the health of our inner terrain —our bodies– is a reflection of the health of our outer terrain, the natural world around us. Gut, immune and nervous system — and the many microbes therein — are a direct reflection of the food we eat and where that food comes from, from the soil it’s grown in to the water it swims in to the synthetic chemicals that it’s bathed in.
dirtcure.com/about/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems the scientific references may have been exaggerated in places (my wife is one to fact-check academic studies), there were still enough persuasive arguments in the book to influence how we do things around our household. Here are the key takeaways for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-microbiome-that-we-eat-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The microbiome that we eat, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of consuming bacteria in food I mainly think of probiotics like yogurt. But of course all the food we eat have microbes living in them. Now consider: what if those microbes matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something of a new way of looking at things for me. You&amp;rsquo;re not just sourcing nutrients from the food you eat, you&amp;rsquo;re sourcing microbes. In which case, it follows that where or how your food is grown can impact how healthy it is for you. Was the tomato grown in biodiverse soil? Was the tomato grown in depleted soil? They might look the same to the eye but one might have more benefit to your body. (I look forward to a time when technology is good enough to differentiate these two tomatoes for us in the grocery store!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-terrain-that-we-live-in-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The terrain that we live in, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t live in a vacuum. It was noted that people who grew up on farms had less allergies/asthma than city folks, likely due to the diversity of microbes they are exposed to. &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/804022/health-benefits-japanese-forest-bathing/&#34;&gt;Forest bathing&lt;/a&gt; is also a proven immune-boosting and healing activity. The benefits of being outdoors, especially in nature, are not to be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illness:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Illness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, bad terrain increases susceptibility to illness. The book introduces an analogy that I quite liked: the basin. When toxins (or viruses, germs, etc) enter our system, they go into our basin. Our body flushes the basin to clear the toxins. When the rate at which toxins enter exceeds the rate the body can clear them, the basin overflows. This results in illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a simple analogy but it explains how the cumulative effects of multiple exposures (each maybe harmless on its own) could affect your health. Reduction of a seemingly innocuous exposure (eg. eliminating a processed food from your diet) can have huge impacts when you are currently at, or close to, the tipping point. Even if you are not near the tipping point, you want to keep your basin as clear as possible so that when you do happen to catch a virus, your body has full power to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-book-changed-for-us-personally:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;What this book changed for us personally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think we were already practicing an approximation of the lifestyle promoted by this book. As CSA members we get the bulk of our veggies from local farms, picked the day before, often arriving with the dirt still clinging to them. We live across the street from a forest. Nevertheless, the book spurred us to make a few adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pantry-cleanout:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Pantry cleanout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this was the kick in the butt we needed to review our pantry and clear out a number of dubious foods. Anything processed, anything with additives (artificial sweeteners, food dyes, unpronounceable ingredients) was basically cut. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a strict elimination diet for us and we&amp;rsquo;ll happily enjoy some of those foods, but they don&amp;rsquo;t need to be in our main rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting thing we found is that sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll be using processed foods without even realizing it. Consider cocoa powder. Everyone knows that chocolate (the raw stuff) is healthy for you, so we had been using cocoa powder quite regularly. But look at the difference in nutrients between 20g of a &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; cocoa powder (Fry&amp;rsquo;s brand) vs Organic Traditions brand cacao powder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fry&amp;rsquo;s cocoa powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;140 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organic Traditions cacao powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought these were equivalent but clearly not. One must be more highly processed than the other (the internet seems to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.paleohacks.com/cacao-vs-cocoa/#&#34;&gt;confirm this&lt;/a&gt;). When you consume something regularly, it pays to check. What do you have in your pantry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-foods:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;New foods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was adding new foods into our rotation. Many foods were suggested by the book, but as mentioned we already had a pretty good diet. However, there are a few new items that stuck with us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kefir (loads of diverse microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kimchi (again microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blackstrap molasses (more antioxidants than blueberries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;soups / bone broths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also dabbled in growing our own sprouts, but that was put on hold once we got our CSA and had more than enough greens to consume each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing we&amp;rsquo;ve been doing is making our own stocks, rather than using bouillon cubes. It&amp;rsquo;s super easy to do and a great way to use all the ends of your veggies rather than throwing away those nutrients in the garbage. We collect them in a container in the freezer, then every couple of weeks boil them into a stock that gets used in our soups and other recipes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;has-it-helped:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Has it helped?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not being scientific about it, but my wife was often one to fall sick with colds. It&amp;rsquo;s been more than half a year and she has not had a serious cold yet, which must be a record. I have only taken one sick day over the same period. So far, at least, it seems to be helping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would be interesting to check back a year from now and see how we&amp;rsquo;re doing. I will try to post an update here if I remember&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Do Not Say We Have Nothing</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 16:31:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/doNotSayWeHaveNothing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-not-say-we-have-nothing-by-madeleine-thien:c82c375baf10ac0da7e6de1e08fcf4ef&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do Not Say We Have Nothing&lt;/em&gt; by Madeleine Thien&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess this one took me a while to sink into. There came a point early on when I happened to pause the book and I almost never picked it up again. It sat there on my night table, a reminder, but I&amp;rsquo;d find something else to occupy my time with. Eventually I did continue and I&amp;rsquo;m glad for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is a history of modern China told from the perspective of an everyday family comprising of artists and musicians. One of the fascinating things to me was the role of music in this story. How can an author, any author, truly describe music in a language such as English? It&amp;rsquo;s a tough challenge, but Thien really did justice to it. However the idea of translating one language to another is bound to leave omissions; a more considered reading of this book would involve listening to these pieces yourself (unfortunately I was not committed enough for that, although I am listening as I write this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting topic was seeing how different people react when externally imposed pressures are applied on them from society at large. Some can&amp;rsquo;t go on, some conform, some thrive in resistance. At times I could see myself in Sparrow. I have been known to become a bit of a chameleon of sorts. But if you can&amp;rsquo;t do the things you love, the things you were meant to do.. who are you, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this book won me over by creating very real characters who behaved in ways I did not understand at all. It&amp;rsquo;s powerful to live in someone else&amp;rsquo;s place and be reminded that your way of looking at things is not the only or the best way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up a (free) Password Manager</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/05/07/setting-up-a-free-password-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 15:39:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/05/07/setting-up-a-free-password-manager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of remaining skeptical about password managers (do I really want to put all my eggs in one basket?), I finally caved after realizing that (a) there were simply too many accounts to remember and (b) my email is effectively a basket holding all the eggs already (anyone who gains access to your email account can use the password reset feature to access your other accounts). With that in mind a password manager didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to increase my risk profile any further from it&amp;rsquo;s current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like the popular &lt;em&gt;1Password&lt;/em&gt; offer cloud-based password management across all your devices.. at a cost. $3/month for their basic plan. I was looking for something cheaper than that. Free, ideally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://keepass.info/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;KeePass&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lightweight open source password manager. The Windows client is so lightweight you don&amp;rsquo;t even have to install it. It&amp;rsquo;s just an &lt;code&gt;exe&lt;/code&gt; file that sits in a folder. After opening KeePass, you add new entries for each of your passwords, or you can import passwords from other password managers (although I was starting from scratch so I didn&amp;rsquo;t explore this further). The resulting password database is just an encrypted file that is safe to move around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to make your passwords available to other devices, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to share this file with those devices. For my purposes, my phone is the only other device I deal with. I installed the Android app &lt;em&gt;KeePassDroid&lt;/em&gt;, copied over the password database by USB, and now I&amp;rsquo;m set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawback with this approach is it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have cloud sync. I could have hosted my password database in my own cloud if I really wanted to, but actually I&amp;rsquo;ve found a simpler way to sync. These days, I always have my phone nearby! Hence the password database on my phone becomes my primary database, and all edits are done in my phone (it&amp;rsquo;s pretty rare that I have to add or change a password anyway). Then periodically about once a month or so, when I normally backup my phone I also transfer my password database over at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple approach to password management, but it meets my needs. I guess you can look at it as a cheap alternative to the pay services out there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Architectus Oryzus</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/03/03/architectus-oryzus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 16:02:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/03/03/architectus-oryzus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Martin Fowler wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.in-gmbh.eu/uploads/media/whoNeedsArchitect.pdf&#34;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; on software architecture almost 15 years ago. I just discovered it now while in the midst of changing jobs, and I found this part where he contrasts architect styles to be very relevant for me in this moment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Architectus Reloadus&lt;/em&gt; is the person who makes all the important decisions. The architect does this because a single mind is needed to ensure a system’s conceptual integrity,  and perhaps because the architect doesn’t think that the team members are sufficiently skilled to make those decisions. Often, such decisions must be made early on so that everyone else has a plan to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Architectus Oryzus&lt;/em&gt; is a different kind of animal. This kind of architect must be very aware of what’s going on in the project, looking out for important issues and tackling them before they become a serious problem. When I see an architect like this, the most noticeable part of the work is the intense collaboration. In the morning, the architect programs with a developer, trying to harvest some common locking code. In the afternoon, the architect participates in a requirements session, helping explain to the requirements people the technical consequences of some of their ideas in non-technical terms — such as development costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, the most important activity of &lt;em&gt;Architectus Oryzus&lt;/em&gt; is to mentor the development team, to raise their level so that they can take on more complex issues. Improving the development team’s ability gives an architect much greater leverage than being the sole decision maker and thus running the risk of being an architectural bottleneck. This leads to the satisfying rule of thumb that an architect’s value is inversely proportional to the number of decisions he or she makes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Martin Fowler in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.in-gmbh.eu/uploads/media/whoNeedsArchitect.pdf&#34;&gt;Who Needs An Architect?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that summarizes very well the role I played for my previous company. Without the benefit of the article&amp;rsquo;s description, I intuitively approached architecture in this way. It&amp;rsquo;s always been clear to me that collaboration is the key to a better product. That means always looking for feedback on designs (earlier the better), and being open to better ideas (often bubbling from the bottom up, sometimes from unexpected places). Raising the level of the development team is crucial, to both increase the pool of critical thinkers available for each problem (huge win), while also reducing the incidence of &amp;ldquo;misguided&amp;rdquo; code submissions (which can become dangerous precedents for future development if left unchecked). There is so much opportunity to learn in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, looking back on my experience now, if I can be critical in one area, it&amp;rsquo;s that I probably got a bit too involved with the teams at times, leading to over-reliance. I&amp;rsquo;m thinking in particular of the moments when I was overseeing three scrum teams. Teams came to rely on me to do reviews, especially code reviews. Even after raising their level and mentoring them to the point that they were capable of self-organizing and taking on that role themselves, I did not notice anyone rise up to truly champion the cause*. Partly I think, that&amp;rsquo;s because I was performing that role so consistently. Too consistently perhaps. Hence there may be a lesson here about stepping back when the time is right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*(At least, the team structures never lasted long enough to see if any champions would finally emerge. I do hope they have gone on to be leaders on their future teams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it was a very rewarding experience with my previous company, and I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to the new challenges ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Project Animal Farm</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/02/04/book-review-project-animal-farm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 21:10:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/02/04/book-review-project-animal-farm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.soniafaruqi.com/wp-content/themes/sonia/images/book-home.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most people, myself included, ignorance is bliss when it comes to meat. We prefer to pick up our vacuum wrapped cuts from the grocery stores with only a cursory thought to its journey there. So it was with some trepidation that I picked up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.soniafaruqi.com/book/&#34;&gt;Project Animal Farm&lt;/a&gt; by Sonia Faruqi. It&amp;rsquo;s the story of a Wall Street banker who followed her curiosity into the dark world of animal farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a very personal journey and mainly anecdotal, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t take away from it; in fact it enhances the connection with the reader. But it also means the reader needs to be careful about broad generalizations from her stories. Her statements on Malaysia, for example, are quite different than my experience of that country. Nevertheless, she takes the reader through a large cross-section of the farming industry, across many countries all over the world, providing personal accounts of everything she witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it comes as no surprise that current farming practices are downright unconscionable regarding animal welfare and it&amp;rsquo;s a real tragedy if you ask me. The factory farming industry is simply revolting. Unfortunately that&amp;rsquo;s where most of the food in our grocery stores come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to learn was that these farming practices are just as bad for society as they are for the animals. Public health is at risk due to increased communicable diseases and outbreaks, as well as the long-term threat of antibiotic resistance. Workers are at risk due to terrible working environments, being exposed to basically unbreathable air filled with ammonia. And the environment is at risk due to dumping of hormones and refuse, as well as carbon dioxide emissions. So even if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about animal welfare, you should be concerned about the side effects of this method of farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this book, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably come away convinced that as a society we can, and should, do better. Why do we put up with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrap it in a nice package, it seems, and the consumer doesn&amp;rsquo;t care to look any deeper. What can be done? Faruqi has a few ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-shop-at-farmer-s-markets:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;1) Shop at farmer&amp;rsquo;s markets.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now our food chain is so far removed from the actual producers, that ignorance reigns while profit becomes the driving force. But if you source your food from someone local, whose farm you can visit if you choose to, and who you can ask questions directly.. then there&amp;rsquo;s a much better chance that farmer will be following good practices on their farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few years I have been buying meat and vegetables from a CSA, whose farm I visit every week to collect my food, and let me tell you it&amp;rsquo;s a wonderful feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-read-the-labels:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;2) Read the labels.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following labels are useless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;family farm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural, or naturally raised&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grain-fed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organic is one of the better labels when it comes to dairy and meat. It means the animals are mandated a minimum of 120 days per year outside, which is not much, but still much better than the requirements for non-organic (0 days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-research:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;3) Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you buy at the grocery store, do some basic research on the companies you usually buy from. Visit their website and email/call with questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they permit public visits (it&amp;rsquo;s a good test, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t actually intend to visit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much space are animals allotted?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they go outdoors and if so how much?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are any mutilations done (castration, declawing, de-beaking, tail-docking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are animals confined to cages, crates or stalls? Are they chained?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Faruqi says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not receive a reply, you will have your reply. This legwork is easier than it looks, because once you find a company you&amp;rsquo;re comfortable with, you can stay with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you with a final statement from Faruqi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With every visit to a cash counter, we, consumers, cast votes for certain values over others. In democracies, politicians are beholden to their voters; in free-market economies, companies are beholden to their customers. It&amp;rsquo;s we who have immeasurable power, if only we choose to wield it. We must have opinions and we must express them loud and clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>America is stumbling, what can Canada do?</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/01/30/america-is-stumbling-what-can-canada-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 22:35:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/01/30/america-is-stumbling-what-can-canada-do/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last week, the US passed a law to ban refugees and Muslims. From a world that views America as a role model in freedom and opportunity, this is a shocking reversal on some core values. America is one of the strongest democracies in the world. If this can happen to America, then no country is safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Canada can do today to avoid a similar eventuality down the road:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;electoral-reform:298d32ef15d63faca68867e9af1ae4a3&#34;&gt;Electoral Reform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my lifetime, the Canadian political experience has always included numerous political parties. From this vantage point it seems quite obvious that a two-party system, such as that of the US, is a huge risk to the well-being of a democracy. By letting the political power consolidate down to only two parties, voters are left with an either-or choice, which encourages divisiveness, voting out of fear, and voting against things rather than for things. This also leads to voter apathy. If presented with two distasteful choices, what is a voter to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplified choices might look appealing in this age of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overchoice&#34;&gt;choice overload&lt;/a&gt;, but trying to boil down politics this way is troublesome and frankly, wrong-headed. Unfortunately there is nothing inherent to the Canadian political system that would prevent us from falling into America&amp;rsquo;s two-party trap. The conservative-leaning parties have successfully merged into one already. And while the merging and splitting of parties has happened throughout Canada&amp;rsquo;s history, given enough time it&amp;rsquo;s a mathematical probability that at some point, we&amp;rsquo;ll find ourselves in a situation with only two parties who are perceived as legitimate. And that&amp;rsquo;s dangerous, because as we have seen in the US, once you get into the two-party trap it&amp;rsquo;s very hard to get out; a vote for a third party becomes tantamount to throwing away your vote. Thus the two-party system is more of an inevitability than we would like to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we stop that from happening? An electoral system involving &lt;a href=&#34;www.fairvote.ca&#34;&gt;proportional representation&lt;/a&gt; would, by its very nature, defeat the notion of throwing away votes. That could act as a balance to prevent a two-party system from taking permanent hold, as an alternative party could quickly legitimize itself (since it would not be forced to win a majority in any specific riding before having a say in parliament). Thus in the long run, proportional representation could guard against our country devolving into a defunct two party system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proportional representation would also force more political viewpoints into play, and require parties to work together to pass legislation. This would help ensure that only those laws which are truly supported by a wide representation of Canadians get passed. An issue like a Muslim ban would be a non-starter in Canada when power is less consolidated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussions on electoral reform are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.canada.ca/en/campaign/electoral-reform.html&#34;&gt;currently underway in Canada&lt;/a&gt;. The trouble is, for incumbent political parties, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to convince themselves to switch the very electoral system that got them into power in the first place. For the long-term benefit of Canada, and for the reasons listed above, I would encourage all Canadians to reflect on the American experience and to consider supporting these changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;increased-connectedness:298d32ef15d63faca68867e9af1ae4a3&#34;&gt;Increased connectedness&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are biologically hard-wired to be afraid of others who are different than them. And yet, diversity is an enormous driver for innovation and adds so much value to life. Getting past the unknown is a fundamental dilemma that everyone has to confront at some point in their life experiences, and it&amp;rsquo;s not always easy! But with more exposure to different people, different ideas, and different places, the fear disappears. That means broad inclusiveness. Large cities intuitively understand the power of diversity. Rural communities simply don&amp;rsquo;t have the same opportunity to interact with so many Canadians in the same way. What can we do to address that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, getting high-speed internet to every Canadian is a no-brainer. It won&amp;rsquo;t solve everything but it&amp;rsquo;s a start. Connecting digitally is still better than no connection at all. There&amp;rsquo;s an initiative currently underway for universal broadband that &lt;a href=&#34;https://openmedia.org/en/we-won-internet-basic-service-all-canadians-0&#34;&gt;could use your support&lt;/a&gt; right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: there are fundamental problems with today&amp;rsquo;s technology that actually &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rushkoff.com/new-nationalism-brexit-trump-product-digital-age/&#34;&gt;raise levels of divisiveness&lt;/a&gt; rather than lower them. That still need to be solved. But it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t stop us from getting everyone plugged in as soon as we can.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing Canada can do is heavily promote, and subsidize, more exchange programs for elementary and high school students, with a specific focus on exchanges between rural and urban students. It&amp;rsquo;s one thing to travel to Ottawa for a weekend, it&amp;rsquo;s quite another to literally live in someone else&amp;rsquo;s shoes for a month or two. The insight gained would lead to more understanding, empathy, and tolerance in our society, while serving as a valuable educational experience. Perhaps this could be organized as summer programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, learning doesn&amp;rsquo;t stop when you grow up. Could we create incentives for Canadians to do more touring around the country as adults and as families? Think about the travels you have done already in Canada. Have you ever visited a First Nation territory? Did you connect at all with the local people? If not, how can we encourage more of that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Travel is fatal to prejudice, bigotry, and narrow-mindedness, and many of our people need it sorely on these accounts. Broad, wholesome, charitable views of men and things cannot be acquired by vegetating in one little corner of the earth all one&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.
  -Mark Twain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;election-holiday:298d32ef15d63faca68867e9af1ae4a3&#34;&gt;Election Holiday&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty simple idea that&amp;rsquo;s used already by other countries. When there&amp;rsquo;s a federal election, make it a public holiday. There are current laws that mandate employers to give their employees time off to vote, but that&amp;rsquo;s not good enough. Many people won&amp;rsquo;t request that, especially vulnerable people for whom that job is their lifeline. These are also the same people who can least afford to take the time to visit a voting station. For a more inclusive turnout, and to give everyone a chance to meaningfully reflect on their civic duty, we should give everyone the day off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the idea one step further, we could also have a &amp;ldquo;Voter Registration Day&amp;rdquo; as the election kicks off, and make that a national holiday as well. I&amp;rsquo;m sure our economy can survive a couple extra holidays every few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there you have some ideas on what Canada can do. I don&amp;rsquo;t normally comment much on politics but the global situation seems to be getting a bit extreme so I wanted to weigh in with a few thoughts. Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WeAllProfit.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/12/13/weallprofit.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 07:03:15 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/12/13/weallprofit.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A website I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a directory of social enterprises in Ottawa. A &lt;em&gt;social enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is a venture which has a  mission that goes beyond profit. This can mean offering employment to vulnerable or disabled people, protecting the environment, or passing their profits on to a charitable organization. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; for many examples of social enterprises in Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website will serve customers of the social enterprise sector by gathering all the local enterprises listings in one place, where a potential customer such as yourself can discover and browse the offerings. We hope this will inspire you to shop in the social enterprise sector, and we are looking forward to adding many more enterprises as we go!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Into the Silence</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 16:20:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/into-the-silence.png&#34; alt=&#34;Into the Silence&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-great-war-mallory-and-the-conquest-of-everest:430078025ad00d05681f6e91e31d9b31&#34;&gt;The Great War, Mallory, and the Conquest of Everest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; by Wade Davis recounts the failed 1920s Everest expeditions, the first ever attempts on the mountain. But it&amp;rsquo;s much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the climbers were shaped by the Great War, and so the book begins there. This leads into an engrossing look at the chaos, the folly, and the haunting reality of a generation of men who would return from war with wounds that could never heal. If the book had been solely these initial chapters on the war, and that was it, I would have been perfectly satisfied. What a treat to realize this was only the introduction, a springboard for what was still yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that stood out to me while reading this book is how these events were happening in a fairly modern, yet entirely different time. From a sensibilities point of view, the Great War had largely broken the spell of idealism, nobility, and purpose in many. Yet for others, it spurred a retreat away from the misery of daily life and towards a more idealistic meaning. The Everest expeditions could be seen as an outlet for the latter, and the men who volunteered were sometimes spiritual, sometimes adventure seekers, always in pursuit of something bigger than themselves. Davis does a nice job of interpreting these distinctions for the modern reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to tell you were being transported into another time is the wonderful collection of correspondence (yes, letter writing was a daily thing!) and it was at times extremely eloquent.. This was a vast wealth of primary material which Davis spent a decade researching, and it led to convincing character portraits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Death&amp;rsquo;s power lies in fear, which flourishes in the imagination and the unknown. For Wheeler there was nothing more that death could show him, short of his own.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tricky things as a reader is dealing with the large cast of characters involved, spanning three expeditions, and I admit to having some difficulty keeping all the persons straight in my head. In the first expedition, Davis had you cheering for the Canadian surveyor Wheeler who was not originally participating in a climbing role but nevertheless won over Mallory and the rest of the team and was ultimately appointed to the climbing party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the storylines in the second expedition, none resonated more than George Finch, the skinny scientist whose revolutionary tactics about bottled oxygen led him to achieve a new height record, despite far worse support than the main climbing party.  A Mallory/Finch climbing tandem is one of those &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; the reader can only wonder about..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that over the course of the book, neither through the author&amp;rsquo;s lens nor through Mallory&amp;rsquo;s personal writings, did I ever fully connect or empathize with Mallory. Hence the fateful end was not a tear jerker for me in the same way as other Everest &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Into_Thin_Air&#34;&gt;stories have been&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, Davis delivers an extremely powerful conclusion to the book. In stark contrast to all the earlier climbing activities, where every action can be analyzed and scrutinized through the heaps of correspondence, private writings, and post reflections by the principle actors, at the moment when Mallory and Irvine depart up the mountain together never to return, the author and his readers are left with a big hole of information to wonder about. We&amp;rsquo;re simply left with&amp;hellip; the silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s powerful and it will have your imagination running in overdrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the recounting of this climbing history leaves the reader a lasting impression of &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What If&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; as each expedition made mistakes (either through membership composition or on the mountain itself) or suffered unpreventable setbacks that taxed the climbers, preventing them from reaching their full potential. In ideal conditions, who can say how far they would have climbed? Or so the book suggests. But I think the real lesson of Everest, clear even in these first attempts at the mountain, is how normal this kind of result is. Sure you may be fit enough to climb the mountain, but count on dealing with any two or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;altitude sickness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inadequate support/teammates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avalanche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;illness/lack of nutrition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unforgiving weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical malfunction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of these obstacles, the early 1920&amp;rsquo;s expeditions were indisputably heroic achievements. From the personalities involved, to the politics of the region, to the sensibilities of the time, &lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; is a very human look at mount Everest and pushing into new frontiers. It is told through Davis&amp;rsquo; flowing prose, and it is a beautiful read. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration Testing with Node and Mongo</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/10/14/integration-testing-with-node-and-mongo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 22:31:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/10/14/integration-testing-with-node-and-mongo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been building &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cised-ca/social-enterprise-directory&#34;&gt;an application&lt;/a&gt; using Node.js with a MongoDB datastore. Now I want to perform some integration testing (&lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; mocking the DB layer) to ensure full end-to-end success of the application. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I went about doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;using-a-test-database:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Using a test database&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the goal is to execute code paths that go through Mongo, it will still be acceptable to execute against a different db than the one used for production deployments. This will ensure the test data never ends up in production by accident, and also avoids production data getting deleted by accident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, I&amp;rsquo;ll have the application connect to Mongo using a test connection string. This will be specified in a configuration file with suitable default value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the application creates the db collections on start up, there are no further pre-requisite Mongo commands to setup the test database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;starting-the-application:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Starting the application&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before any tests can run, the application needs to start up. So I wrote a simple &lt;code&gt;app_starter.js&lt;/code&gt; utility to boot the application into service with the appropriate test configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;starting-each-test-with-a-clean-datastore:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Starting each test with a clean datastore&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each test needs to be independent, so we can&amp;rsquo;t leave remnants in the datastore from a previous test. Hence the first thing I do at the start of each test is clean the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m using Mocha as my test framework, so this gets implemented as a &lt;code&gt;beforeEach&lt;/code&gt; hook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;beforeEach( function(done) {
    dbUtil.cleanDatabase(done);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cleaning-the-datastore:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Cleaning the datastore&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very straightforward way to clean the datastore, is to drop the database and re-create it again. My application connects to the datastore using &lt;a href=&#34;mongoosejs.com&#34;&gt;Mongoose&lt;/a&gt;. With Mongoose, the database can be dropped with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function cleanDatabase(done) {
  mongoose.connection.db.dropDatabase(done);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now how do we re-create the database? Turns out Mongoose is kind enough to do this for you automatically under the hood, so nothing else to do. However there&amp;rsquo;s one more wrinkle to deal with&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mongoose will re-create the collections in the database on demand, but not the indexes. The indexes are only built during mongoose connection establishment. This means our tests won&amp;rsquo;t be able to execute successfully because the database indexes won&amp;rsquo;t be present. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at how to address that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;rebuilding-the-indexes:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Rebuilding the indexes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily Mongoose supplies an API to rebuild the indexes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mongoose.model(modelName).ensureIndexes();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes a little time to complete, so I had to register on &lt;code&gt;index&lt;/code&gt; event to listen for when it finishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mongoose.model(myModel).on(&#39;index&#39;, done);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the indexes are ready, the database is set for your test to begin. Here is the updated &lt;code&gt;cleanDatabase&lt;/code&gt; function which delegates to a rebuildIndexes helper function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function cleanDatabase(done) {
  mongoose.connection.db.dropDatabase( function() {
    rebuildIndexes(done);
  });
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find the full implementation &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cised-ca/social-enterprise-directory/blob/dd0c588843ffe014b0befd36e316beefa6bc181b/test/api/helpers/db/db_util.js&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;results:6648ac7d9852b157cbf2d7b2e6ff1536&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That puts a simple automated integration test framework in place for application developers to work with. This should help ensure stability of the application over time as new features get added, while also allowing developers to take a TDD approach to feature development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my system it does take a few 100 ms to run each test due to the extra database overhead. Given the number of tests at the moment, this is not a concern. In the future if it somehow grows into a problem there are alternatives to dropping the database, such as removing the collections, which I&amp;rsquo;ve heard may improve execution performance. This would be easy to refactor in the future if needed, but I expect the current implementation will be just fine for a long while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation Skills Training</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/09/20/presentation-skills-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 22:31:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/09/20/presentation-skills-training/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently completed a two-day training course on presentation skills. While I have been known to give a killer presentation (or speech) in my time, doing so takes &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of preparation on my end and it&amp;rsquo;s never as natural as I would like. By taking this course, my goal was to hone my skills, practice a little more, and discover some new tips and tricks. Here are the main takeaways for me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a world of partial attention, so we &lt;strong&gt;cannot assume that our audience is engaged with us&lt;/strong&gt;. The presenter is competing for the audience&amp;rsquo;s attention with many other available sources of information (email, phones, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to compete with that, the key is to give a &lt;strong&gt;simple, authentic and meaningful&lt;/strong&gt; experience to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five principles can help us carry out this mission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passion (infectious, spreads energy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep it simple (only 3 key messages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less is more (don&amp;rsquo;t overload your messages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authenticity (something real)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storytelling (adds interest)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;planning-your-presentation:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Planning Your Presentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-based-presentations:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Goal based presentations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, decide what the goal of your presentation will be. Sounds obvious? Yet it&amp;rsquo;s fairly typical for me to jump straight into some random details in the middle of the presentation and start building up my slides from there without really knowing where I ultimately want the presentation to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think partly that has to do with the fear not wanting to lose the creative juices in the moment.. but creating anything that way can lead all over the map unless you manage to stay focused. Think about how many slides you throw out in the end because they are not relevant, don&amp;rsquo;t help support the main message, or else get cut due to time constraints for the presentation. That&amp;rsquo;s a lot of wasted time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead think about building scalable presentations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;45 second (elevator pitch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;45 minute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start small because that will force you to focus on the main message only. Then build out the details around it to fill in the time.
As a bonus, by creating your presentations this way, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to better adapt to being given less/more time on the day of the presentation, while also being ready to give the same presentation again in a different format should the need arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;know-the-audience:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Know the audience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know your audience! Can you find out any more about them and what they want before the presentation? This has burned me before by making wrong assumptions about what level of knowledge the audience was starting from. A simple question could have clarified that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to get your priorities right. Start with most important things for the audience. Sometimes that means beginning with the bottom line and getting into the justifications later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;designing-a-presentation:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Designing a Presentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;typical-presentation-flow:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Typical presentation flow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical presentation might flow like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question/Issue (the why)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key Message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples (stories, points to back up message)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat message and call to action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get to your central message &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;power-of-3-s:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Power of 3&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have short attention spans and a finite memory. Assume they can only take away &lt;strong&gt;3 things&lt;/strong&gt; from your presentation and no more. Have no more than 3 key ideas. Under each idea introduce no more than 3 related concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;opening-and-closing:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Opening and closing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The audience is most likely to remember your first and last words. So it&amp;rsquo;s definitely worth investing some extra time in your opening and closing remarks. Start with a hook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s a magical place in the world that not many have a chance to visit&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hooks work even for technical presentations. Change your opening from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Well not everyone is here yet, but let&amp;rsquo;s get started anyway..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Imagine a world where your network installs itself with one command..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which presentation would you rather be at?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the closing, saying &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;In conclusion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; is a good trick to get your audience perk up if they were not already awake. Try that with a louder voice, and use the extra attention gained to reinforce your key message or make a call to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;slide-design:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Slide design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen cluttered slides before? I knew that slides should be kept simple, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until this course that I realized just how simple that should be. Our instinct says &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I want to add as much content as I can to support my key message&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; but that line of thinking makes it very easy to overdo it. Think back to the world of partial attention: if someone is only going to glance at your slide for a short period of time, it needs to be extremely simple, clear and effective. Every word should be essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides should support the presentation, not replace it. It is not a handout. If you need a handout, make a different deck. That&amp;rsquo;s not the goal of presentation slides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep it to one message per slide. As few slides as possible.
And think about the Power of 3, no more than 3 bullet points per slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;handling-nerves:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Handling nerves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerves always get me. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter how friendly the room is. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter how much I&amp;rsquo;ve prepared (sometimes the more preparation the worse). It&amp;rsquo;s pretty normal for me to feel even slightly physically ill before a presentation, although I&amp;rsquo;m pretty good at hiding it and people have told me I don&amp;rsquo;t look nervous at all. Usually it goes away after the first minute or two of the presentation, but by then the damage has been done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course offered pretty rote advice for nerves:
&lt;em&gt;Acknowledge nervousness, use that energy. Visualize success, anticipate what parts might be tricky and plan through them, breathe, prepare, Smile!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rationally I agree, but I submit that those tips don&amp;rsquo;t exactly solve the problem for me. Ultimately, I think practice is really the only medicine here. Both practice in terms of simulating giving the specific presentation, as well as practice in terms of doing many presentations in general. If you were to give a big presentation every week, I think your coping mechanisms would eventually adapt. It reminds me of my university days, interviewing for co-op jobs each semester. The first interview is nervous as hell, but by the 10th interview you&amp;rsquo;ve got your delivery nailed and are actually looking forward to selling yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally there is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_shapes_who_you_are&#34;&gt;this talk by Amy Cuddy&lt;/a&gt; that provides a scientifically proven way to reduce your stress hormones before high pressure situations. I&amp;rsquo;m a bit skeptical but I guess it&amp;rsquo;s worth a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;passion:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Passion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the material is not something you are actually passionate about. That&amp;rsquo;s OK. Just know the message well, and make sure to lead the presentation (and don&amp;rsquo;t get led by the slides), and it will go over very well with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If audience is not looking involved, start a dialogue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are asked a question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank and acknowledge the person (or their emotion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;You make an excellent point&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I can see why this concerns you so let&amp;rsquo;s address that..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I think many others are probably feeling the same&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I can see you feel very strongly about that..&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clarify and repeat the question to ensure broad understanding and give yourself time to answer. &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; be judgmental&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep excellent eye contact throughout the question and answer, then break off contact and deliberately move away to communicate that you are moving on in your presentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Often deadly questions are based on assumptions. Challenge the assumption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Change emphasis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Negative to positive like &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;yes, that&amp;rsquo;s true we do charge more, but&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General to specific or specific to general.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Break into long winded questioners when they take a breath with &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I believe I can answer that&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember your time frame and move on&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;remote-presentations:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Remote presentations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When presenting remotely or by conference call make sure to smile and keep good posture because it will show in your voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary:12f0b3828d93c178603e2824f7304353&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, this was a valuable training course for me. The biggest eye opener was seeing how principles like storytelling and hooks can apply even for technical presentation topics, which is my main domain of interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t see many presentations doing that in my workplace. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping I can take these lessons and apply them going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mindset</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 23:11:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carol Dweck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Success-Carol-Dweck/dp/0345472322&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindset: The New Psychology of Success&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; summarizes the ground-breaking research she and others have been leading on the subjects of motivation, identity, self-awareness and ability. All of these, it turns out, can be influenced significantly by one&amp;rsquo;s mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her most famous experiment involves taking two groups of kids and giving each kid an easy puzzle to solve. She then praised one group of kids for being smart, but praised the other group for their effort. Then she observed how the performance of these two groups differed over time, and they did dramatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those praised for being smart were less willing to take on harder challenges, did worse on subsequent administered challenges (even when a challenge similar to the original in difficulty was re-administered), and even lied about their performance scores. She was quite surprised to find that her praise transformed kids into liars! The book was written a decade ago, with over a million copies sold, so I&amp;rsquo;m hoping this has become more common knowledge now to many people as it&amp;rsquo;s quite important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first group, as a result of the praise, the children were nudged into taking a &lt;em&gt;fixed mindset&lt;/em&gt; about intelligence. This is the idea that your natural abilities are permanent. In this view, while anybody can learn new things, the overall intelligence (or ability) that you bring to the table is fixed. Similar to thinking that everyone has pretty much one IQ score and it won&amp;rsquo;t change. Do you share this mindset?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other group was nudged into the &lt;em&gt;growth mindset&lt;/em&gt;. That is, believing that our abilities can be developed through experience - including our intelligence. It is the belief that by working through difficult things we can improve ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might find you have a fixed mindset about some things and not others. Consider the two paragraphs above, but what if you replace &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;artistic ability&amp;rdquo;? &amp;hellip;sports? &amp;hellip;leadership?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has since done all kinds of experiments on people of all ages to test these beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that people who have a growth mindset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more willing, even eager, to take on harder challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tend to view mistakes as learning opportunities rather than attacks on their identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more resilient when hit by negative labels, negative stereotyping, or depression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have more accurate estimations about their own abilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generally end up succeeding/performing better over time, even showing bumps in IQ in some studies on kids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems the growth mindset is the way to go, no? Trouble is you might have one mindset or the other and not even be aware of it. Luckily, it is possible to switch mindsets. The scary thing to me is just how easy it can be to do so at times. Many of the mentioned studies were able to switch their subjects into one mindset or the other before evaluating them (as she demonstrated with those kids). Makes you wonder how we all individually and as a society contribute towards inadvertently conjuring one mindset over the other in those around us. This truly has serious implications on parenting, teaching and coaching. Never call your kids smart! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all really interesting for sure, but how about the book itself? Dweck begins by presenting the mindset concepts to the reader (so far so good), but then she takes us on a journey of looking at the world through a &amp;ldquo;mindset&amp;rdquo; lens. She focuses on celebrities in history across various domains (business, sports, coaching), and shows us examples of both fixed mindset and growth mindset people. For example, she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s who she thinks hold a fixed mindset and explains how this contributed to their failure at business. Then she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s with a growth mindset and shows how it contributed to their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the book at its worst, in my opinion. This is anecdotal evidence at best. She is making assumptions about their mindsets based on observed behaviour, but she has not actually tested these people, or if she did she does not mention it. Anyone can cherry pick examples to prove a point, and I quickly got frustrated and fed up of reading these anecdotal examples that weren&amp;rsquo;t adding any substance to the argument. Unfortunately these are &lt;em&gt;littered&lt;/em&gt; throughout the book. She has a tendency to follow up each proposition with an anecdote. This shows up in the form: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A study by ABC has shown that fixed mindset people are less resilient to XYZ. For example, Billy was an elementary school student and&amp;hellip; [Billy&amp;rsquo;s story goes here]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I am more technically-inclined than most, but these anecdotes are fluff and I would prefer if she had included more experiment details and their specific results. She also avoided almost any discussion of quantitative results, perhaps thinking percentages and the like might scare aware her audience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the sheer significance of the research being shared here overcomes any failings in the presentation. &lt;strong&gt;Read this book&lt;/strong&gt; if you have the chance. My recommendation is to read the first couple of chapters on the basic concepts, then &lt;strong&gt;skip entirely&lt;/strong&gt; the fluff chapters on business, sports, and coaching (you can return to them later if you really want to). Instead proceed straight to the parenting and teaching chapter, which is the most important I think.  Also feel free to skip any anecdotal stories if you are getting fed up with them, you won&amp;rsquo;t miss anything! I read the book aloud this way to my wife as she drove us across the Yukon, and we both enjoyed the book much better that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has written a few articles since the book was published. Further reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-secret-to-raising-smart-kids1/&#34;&gt;The Secret to Raising Smart Kids - Scientific American article by Carol Dweck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edweek.org/ew/articles/2015/09/23/carol-dweck-revisits-the-growth-mindset.html&#34;&gt;Carol Dweck Revisits the &amp;lsquo;Growth Mindset&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Quantum Night</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 17:02:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/1/18/Quantum_Night_by_Robert_J._Sawyer_Book_Cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_Night&#34;&gt;Quantum Night&lt;/a&gt; is the latest from Canadian sci-fi author Robert Sawyer. In it, two researchers independently discover two techniques to identify psychopaths objectively, and they come together to try and figure out the implications of their discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting themes raised in the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are the ethics for research on human subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;why are there so many people all over the world doing terrible things, all the time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are people still responsible for their actions even if they are physically &amp;ldquo;hard-wired&amp;rdquo; to be that way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;herd mentality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tensions between tribal loyalty and the greater good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me about this book is how &amp;ldquo;un-fictiony&amp;rdquo; it felt for sci-fi. I am glad that Sawyer took on the topic of psychology which is extremely relevant in today&amp;rsquo;s society.. In the age of Brexit and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://qz.com/723537/in-the-post-factual-democracy-politicians-win-by-getting-feelings-right-and-facts-wrong/&#34;&gt;post-factual democracy&lt;/a&gt;, human psychology has been harnessed/exploited by corporations, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.ca/Enlightenment-2-0-Restoring-Politics-Economy/dp/0062342894&#34;&gt;politicians&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rushkoff.com/staying-human-machine-age-interview-douglas-rushkoff/&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, military, and on and on.. It can get a little depressing to think about, knowing we are mostly helpless agents against ourselves. Of course there are good guys working other angles too (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nudge_(book)&#34;&gt;Nudge&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is possible to become self-aware of our own individual psychological tendencies, and to recognize if someone is using questionable tactics to convince us of something, this takes &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&#34;&gt;a lot of effort&lt;/a&gt;, and thus it&amp;rsquo;s practically impossible to completely eliminate our innate tendencies entirely. Even if one person could do it, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly not possible to achieve this at the larger level of a society. Ultimately, then, I think our society is bound to suffer further Brexit and Trump-like eventualities, until such time we consciously reorganize our institutions (political systems, corporations, etc) to properly take into account the fallibilities of human psychology and put in guards against their exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds a bit crazy, but machines might actually be able to help us here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pzs:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;PZs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another topic raised in the book is the concept of &amp;ldquo;pz&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; as Sawyer called them, people who act and behave just like normal people but internally (unbeknownst to anyone), are not actually conscious. While these people were viewed with horror and disdain (at least by the characters in the novel), it did occur to me that this notion of a clear mind / living entirely in the moment, is something of an achievement if you are an existentialist or a Buddhist. There are people actively trying to blot out their consciousness for a few moments of zen. So maybe a lifetime of pz would represent the ultimate fulfillment? Or does it only count if you consciously surrender your consciousness? ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really enjoyed the book although the ending felt a little rushed, and I kept hoping for one final twist that never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I love about Sawyer&amp;rsquo;s novels are the education factor. While you keep turning the pages to see how the story unfolds, there are plenty of interesting ideas and references scattered throughout, bread crumbs to return to later and revisit should you wish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>