<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 10:26:29 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Douglas Rushkoff at Writersfest</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 10:26:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I had the pleasure of listening to Douglas Rushkoff speak at the spring edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writersfestival.org/&#34;&gt;Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. Rushkoff is one of my favourite thinkers and host of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; podcast, as well as author of the new book &lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very little prompting was needed by the host to set off intriguing ruminations from Rushkoff about technology, media and society. Rushkoff walked us through the medieval inventions of the corporation and growth-based currency (currency that has to be borrowed and paid back with interest), both of which were introduced for the purpose of suppressing the middle class so that the ruling class could preserve their wealth in an increasingly peer-to-peer marketplace environment. These concepts have continued straight through to today and now form the unquestioned &amp;ldquo;operating system&amp;rdquo; upon which our whole economy is built. Rushkoff points to these two as the root cause of many of the strange effects that technology is having on society today, and how tech companies for all their talk of disruption have not considered challenging these basic assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff talks about reversals that happen with technology (in his own terms, the &lt;em&gt;figure&lt;/em&gt; vs the &lt;em&gt;ground&lt;/em&gt;), whereby over time the users of a technology become themselves used by it (the book goes into this concept much more). Rushkoff draws a parallel between colonization (a term we are familiar with in Canada to describe the structural violence against Indigenous peoples) and the effect that digital technology is having on us today. There is no denying the harm that technology can cause to our wellbeing and to that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff points out that the best consumer is an isolated consumer. As such, growth-based technologies act to push us apart. He recalls watching TV together as a family while growing up, and going to the theatres to watch a movie. These days we consume media in individualistic ways designed to make us more susceptible to surveillance and targeted advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff warns that we can lose our human souls (or just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/JamesBrownOfficial&#34;&gt;soul&lt;/a&gt; with reference to James Brown, for those who don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the former concept) by profit-focused algorithms that try to &amp;ldquo;auto-tune&amp;rdquo; our behaviour so that we better fit our algorithmically predicted buckets. Weirdness is what makes us human, and should be celebrated. Life is everything that happens in between the &amp;ldquo;notes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are warned to think of digital technologies as drugs - you&amp;rsquo;re on Facebook, on Twitter, on-line.. He quotes Timothy Leary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Before you take a drug, look into the eye of someone who&amp;rsquo;s done that drug. Decide if that&amp;rsquo;s a place you want to be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have the choice not to do so. Rushkoff suggests we try practicing a &lt;em&gt;Tech Sabbath&lt;/em&gt; - consuming no digital technologies on Sundays. Then, level that up further by cutting out cars as well. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple idea but one can easily imagine how that would foster local communities in a serious way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff peppers the talk with repeated calls to respecting human dignity and human values. He calls on us to make local connections, be a part of &lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;Breathe together&amp;rdquo; he instructs us, explaining how this is literally the etymological basis for the term &lt;em&gt;conspire&lt;/em&gt;. And by connecting and interacting offline, face-to-face we are also &lt;em&gt;conspiring&lt;/em&gt; against the companies that are trying to make a dollar off our interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Smart&#34; City coming to Ottawa?</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 08:50:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was stirred to write a blog post after stumbling across an op-ed titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/index.php/article/op-ed-forget-about-toronto-sidewalk-labs-build-smart-neighbourhood-ottawa-instead&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forget about Toronto, Sidewalk Labs – build a smart neighbourhood in Ottawa instead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been following Toronto&amp;rsquo;s efforts at smart city development for the past 9 months (aka the Sidewalk Labs debacle), and was alarmed to read this same group might bring their bad behaviour to Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sidewalk Labs&amp;rsquo; smart city in Toronto has woeful accountability (and its leaked plans are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalobserver.com/2019/02/15/news/alphabets-sidewalk-labs-was-secretly-considering-big-plans-toronto-neighbourhood&#34;&gt;terrifying&lt;/a&gt;), with high profile &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2018/10/20/privacy-expert-steps-down-from-advisory-role-with-sidewalk-labs.html&#34;&gt;resignations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://business.financialpost.com/technology/sidewalk-labs-advisory-panel-member-saadia-muzaffar-resigns-citing-deep-dismay&#34;&gt;leading tech experts&lt;/a&gt;. And yet they continue to go forward. Explain why would anyone would want that for their city?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The op-ed author says that a data policy is necessary upfront (which I absolutely agree with) while in the same breath telling us we should &amp;ldquo;inform these businesses they could start developing a smart community in Ottawa today&amp;rdquo;. Seems like a contradiction there. A public data policy must be something that is carefully debated and not rushed through. It&amp;rsquo;s exactly this kind of &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out as we go&amp;rdquo; mentality that got Toronto into trouble. It opens the door for corporate definition and interference in policy (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@biancawylie/sidewalk-toronto-gaslighting-toronto-residents-backfired-capacitys-built-and-power-s-shifted-77c455b150a3&#34;&gt;gas lighting&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Toronto&amp;rsquo;s failure, and with many thanks to the citizens advocating in opposition there, here is what Ottawa can and should do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start working on privacy and data governance policies. Today! This needs to happen ASAP or we &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get bullied by corporations into rushed or inadequate policies. This needs to be carefully debated and done so in a fully transparent way.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we have any smart city policies already? I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laughably, Ottawa&amp;rsquo;s published &lt;a href=&#34;https://documents.ottawa.ca/sites/default/files/smart_city_strategy_en.pdf&#34;&gt;Smart City 2.0 Strategy&lt;/a&gt; does not have a single reference to &amp;ldquo;privacy&amp;rdquo; or even &amp;ldquo;data governance&amp;rdquo; in its strategy. (Yes you read that correctly. I wish I was joking.). Really shows where the priorities are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, as a city let&amp;rsquo;s first be explicit about what features we want from our smart city, and debate those features in a public setting. Not all &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; technology is smart for society or the public as a whole. We should not give carte blanche to corporations to &amp;ldquo;disrupt&amp;rdquo; neighbourhoods however they see fit, as if breaking neighbourhoods was even a good thing.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s follow the principle of &lt;a href=&#34;http://spacing.ca/toronto/2019/02/19/did-the-sidewalk-labs-plot-just-thicken-or-is-the-story-coming-to-an-end/&#34;&gt;Consult first, then procure.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to OBJ for the balanced journalism in also including an article on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/article/web-data-collected-smart-city-tech-stokes-privacy-fears&#34;&gt;privacy concerns&lt;/a&gt; surrounding smart city development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blocksidewalk.ca/&#34;&gt;BlockSidewalk&lt;/a&gt; movement to stay up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life Insurance Calculator</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/19/life-insurance-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 20:19:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/19/life-insurance-calculator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With a baby on the way later this year, it&amp;rsquo;s the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve had to contemplate taking care of a dependent (not counting pets of course). One of the duties in this regard is ensuring that your dependent will be financially supported in the event of your death. Not a pleasant topic to think about, unless maybe you are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/travel/story/20150408-bhutans-dark-secret-to-happiness&#34;&gt;from Bhutan&lt;/a&gt;, but a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main question is how much insurance do I need? To answer, I threw together &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/LifeInsuranceCalculator.ods&#34;&gt;this LibreOffice spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; as a &amp;ldquo;back of the napkin&amp;rdquo; type calculator. It is definitely only meant as a rough guide and does not rigorously examine inflation nor taxes to a fine precision (although it does take them into account somewhat). The cells in blue are what you will edit to set the parameters for your specific case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing a parent is probably not going to easy for a child, so I am erring on the side of overcompensation. Post-secondary education is one such example that others might consider optional, but I wanted to ensure it was fully covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised at the cost of post-secondary education compared to 15-20 years ago. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what form education will even take in 20 years, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to imagine the costs continuing to rise and the value proposition still being there in an age of information abundance. Nevertheless, I am including it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;both parents die&amp;rdquo; case was also interesting to examine. I thought for sure it would be the worst case scenario, financially speaking, but turns out it&amp;rsquo;s a non-issue when both parents have some retirement savings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soundtrack of 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/soundtrack-of-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 21:03:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/soundtrack-of-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Music has a curious way of permeating your life, such that years later a song can stir up forgotten memories and emotions. Each song is precious in a way that only we can fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These songs formed the soundtrack of my life in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-violin-stereotypes-album-2015:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Black Violin - Stereotypes (album 2015)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mix of hip hop and classical, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blackviolin.net/videos/&#34;&gt;Black Violin&lt;/a&gt; pushes the boundaries of each genre. I&amp;rsquo;ve actually been listening to this album for a couple years now and still not tired of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/blackViolin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Stereotypes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-toast-light:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Dr. Toast - Light&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A constant at the yoga studio, this song takes me straight to my centered happy place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://music.drtoast.com/track/light&#34;&gt;https://music.drtoast.com/track/light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonobo-sweetness-bootleg-album-2002:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Bonobo - Sweetness (bootleg album 2002)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my album of choice to listen while coding this year. Enough repetition to let your mind focus, enough complexity to keep things interesting when you surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wdpDtAjZuWQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-balconies-show-you-album-2012:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;The Balconies - Show You (album 2012)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Balconies&#34;&gt;The Balconies&lt;/a&gt; are a local Ottawa rock/pop band who I was into 10 years ago. This album was recorded in 2012 but never released because the band&amp;rsquo;s style had changed in the intervening time, so they kept it hidden away for all these years. I was more a fan of their old style anyway so once the band folded and released the forgotten album I was very happy to have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/8721557&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;various-irish-artists-musical-pub-crawl-album:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Various Irish artists - Musical Pub Crawl (album)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our travels in Ireland this year took as to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.musicalpubcrawl.com&#34;&gt;musical pub crawl&lt;/a&gt; in Dublin. We were able to purchase an album of traditional Irish music which is exceptional but I cannot find it online. It&amp;rsquo;s become our staple soundtrack this year while cooking and doing stuff around the house.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/advent-of-code-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 13:20:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/advent-of-code-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This past December I discovered the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; challenge, in which you get a different coding puzzle for each day in December leading up to Christmas. The puzzles can be solved in any programming language of your choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to solve the puzzles in Elixir, which is a newer language that I am starting to use at work. The creator of Elixir, José Valim, was solving the puzzles as well and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.plataformatec.com.br/2018/11/lets-learn-elixir-together-with-advent-of-code/&#34;&gt;live streaming his solutions&lt;/a&gt;. Other Elixir experts were also publishing solutions, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sasa1977/aoc&#34;&gt;Saša Jurić&lt;/a&gt;. This was so cool! A fabulous way to learn a new language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints I only attempted about half of the puzzles with my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/advent-of-code-2018&#34;&gt;solutions posted here&lt;/a&gt;. I was hoping to go back and finish the rest of the puzzles but that hasn&amp;rsquo;t happened so I&amp;rsquo;m wrapping this up with a blog post now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;commentary:0647481dad1b7f4b21d4a5bad3077cd7&#34;&gt;Commentary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partway through I realized it would be helpful to myself to capture personal insights for each solution, so I left some commentary in the code solutions themselves which I am reproducing here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td style=&#34;width: 20%&#34;&gt;
Day 5 
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
    For this solution, I found that converting each individual character to a String for purpose of doing downcase() 
    was performance impacting (total 30 seconds to solve puzzle). So I switched to using assumption
    that input was only ascii letters (and added a validation check to ensure this assumption holds). 
    Thus I could compare upper/lower case by adding 32 to the value instead of converting to string. Solution runs 15x faster.
    &lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 6
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
The performance of my solution is lacking, it took 30 seconds to solve Part 1 on my laptop.
Part 2 solution was even worse - 2 min 26 s.
If I had more time I would go back and optimize!
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 7
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
    First part was OK, second part took a long time to solve.
    First puzzle where my code worked for the test data but didn&#39;t work for the full solution.
    (Turned out I read the challenge wrong.. was using wrong number of workers).
    Passing a lot of parameters around. Might be easier to pass state around as a
    single map structure than as individual parameters.
    
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
 Day 8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Got bitten by elixir when doing efficient building a list by appending to the start
    but then forgetting to reverse list at the end (when order became important)!
    This caused some grief. I could have noticed this error sooner if I ran the tests more frequently
    during development.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Nice to use Stream.unfold for the first time, also learned how to sleep in elixir.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Things I learned today, you can do pattern matching in anonymous functions!
    Part 1 was solved in a straightforward, albeit not great performance way.
    Part 2 The non-performant solution was no longer reasonable. I tried a few
     optimizations but couldn&#39;t make it fast enough. Then I found this hint:
     https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summed-area_table
     but by that point it was the end of the night and I didn&#39;t feel like implementing it.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
  Felt really good about solving this one, my growing familiarity with the elixir
  modules is starting to pay off. Assist to my wife for talking through Part 2 strategy with me.
  
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up Visual Studio Code for Elixir</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/12/31/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-elixir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 13:50:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/12/31/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-elixir/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Elixir is a programming language that I am in the process of learning, and which I use at work. This post documents the settings I am using to develop in elixir using the VSCode editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-language-support:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;1. Language Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install extension &lt;code&gt;ElixirLS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the box this gives you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;autocomplete, navigation, dialyzer (aka static analysis/linting) and debugging capabilities. Hooray!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-formatting:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;2. Formatting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elixir is an auto-formatted language for &lt;a href=&#34;https://hashrocket.com/blog/posts/format-your-elixir-code-now&#34;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;, hence &lt;code&gt;mix format&lt;/code&gt; is your friend. In your VSCode Settings, hit the checkbox for &amp;ldquo;Editor: Format on Save&amp;rdquo; to run this on every save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-test-execution:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;3. Test Execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commonly run tests three different ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a single test. Most frequently used while developing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the tests. Used for regression testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run all the tests from a single file. Sometimes useful while developing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set these up as Tasks in your tasks.json as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      }
  },
  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;single test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test ${relativeFile}:${lineNumber}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      },
      &amp;quot;runOptions&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;reevaluateOnRerun&amp;quot;: false
      }
  },
  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test current file&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test ${relativeFile}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      },
      &amp;quot;runOptions&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;reevaluateOnRerun&amp;quot;: false
      }
  }

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also create hotkeys to launch your tests. I do it like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[
   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl-s&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+s&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;single test&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;when&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;editorTextFocus&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+w&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test current file&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+r&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.reRunTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;when&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;editorTextFocus&amp;quot;
   }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s super easy to run a single test, or all the tests, on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use in combination with the standard &amp;ldquo;Rerun Last Task&amp;rdquo; (new in vscode 1.30) to run your single test over and over again without having to switch windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With credit to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pragdave.me/blog/2018/06/13/visual-studio-code-elixir-tests.html&#34;&gt;https://pragdave.me/blog/2018/06/13/visual-studio-code-elixir-tests.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Way of the Peaceful Warrior</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 15:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This month I read  &lt;em&gt;Way of the Peaceful Warrior&lt;/em&gt; by Dan Millman. In short, it is a story about how to live your best life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because I had pre-internalized several of these ideas already from my own lived experience, I found the first half a slow and painful slog (also because I kind of loathed the main character, but that was mostly by design). It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until around page 100 that I settled in and felt like I was getting something out of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those insights is a way of looking at emotions. Here I pulled three separate quotes from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to control emotion &amp;hellip; The key is to transform the energy of emotion into constructive action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger is a powerful tool to transform old habits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear and sorrow inhibit action; anger generates it. When you learn to make proper use of your anger, you can change fear and sorrow to anger, then turn anger to action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is to use your emotions with intention. Take a moment to acknowledge the emotion, then turn around and use it for whatever help it can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another insight is that action is the way of the warrior. Knowledge and meditation only go so far. Turning your knowledge into action is what counts. This is a good reminder for me, that a quiet life of learning is entirely insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some more nuggets of wisdom from the book that I am recording here so that I can come back to later from time to time to remind myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any unconscious, compulsive ritual is a problem.&lt;/em&gt; [&amp;hellip;] &lt;em&gt;Responsibility means recognizing both pleasure and price, action and consequence, then making a choice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My actions are conscious, spontaneous, intentional, and complete.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t live according to anyone&amp;rsquo;s expectations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are no ordinary moments&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extend razor-sharp attention to every moment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The mind stores tension in the body. Worries, anxieties, and other mental debris are stored as chronic tension&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meditating an action is different from doing it. To do, there is a doer, a self-conscious &amp;lsquo;someone&amp;rsquo; performing. But when you meditate an action, you&amp;rsquo;ve released attachment to outcomes. There&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;lsquo;you&amp;rsquo; left to do it. In forgetting yourself, you become what you do, so your action is free, spontaneous, without ambition, inhibition, or fear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The secret of happiness, you see, is not found in seeking more, but in developing the capacity to enjoy less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find the book a roundabout way of sharing this wisdom. Having to slog through the experience of Danny is, I guess, one example for readers to work with. But I found so many more examples in my own lived experience to relate to that I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to be guided this way. And there was a strange side-story about a woman named Joy which became a weird metaphor that felt awkward and unnecessary. As such, I felt the presentation of these ideas overall did not resonate well for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However one thing I did like was how these ideas were presented without any religious context. I have a vague sense that many of them could be compatible with Taoist ideas, however not being very well-versed in that domain myself I cannot comment much further (it does remind me that I am overdue to read a different book involving Taoism that my sister gave me: &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Names for Joy&lt;/em&gt;). On his Q&amp;amp;A webpage, Millman states that many readers have found religious teachings in his work but that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t subscribe &amp;ldquo;to any other philosophical stool, but to simple humanity&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite part of the book is the challenge to the reader to &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;be unreasonably happy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. I do believe happiness is a choice, so this resonates with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feelings change &amp;hellip; Sometimes sorrow, sometimes joy. But beneath it all remember the innate perfection of your life unfolding. That is the secret of unreasonable happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a master at anything, and there are always ways to improve, but this is one lesson, at least, worth taking to heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three sequels were written to this book, including one that come out just last year (&lt;em&gt;The Hidden School&lt;/em&gt;). I don&amp;rsquo;t feel the urge to read further, but if anyone else has then I&amp;rsquo;m interested to hear what you thought about them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: Spring/Summer 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 20:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It has been a busy time but I am still reading! Here is a quick recap of memorable books finished in Spring and Summer 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/books2018.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Books in 2018&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;49th-parallels:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;49th Parallels&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published during Canada&amp;rsquo;s 150-year celebration, a compilation of short stories and alternative histories involving Canada and our place in the world. Example: what if Canada had been first to develop the atomic bomb? I supported this publication through crowdfunding, and am quite pleased with the result: uniquely Canadian! Re-imagining our story helps answer questions about who we are and who we could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-beyond-body-space-time:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indigenous LGBT sci-fi short story compilation. It&amp;rsquo;s a rare intersection to find in one publication and worth checking out for that alone. In particular I really enjoyed Cherie Dimaline&amp;rsquo;s and Nathan Adler&amp;rsquo;s stories and still find myself thinking about them from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-marrow-thieves:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;The Marrow Thieves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cherie Dimaline (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A genius premise. Brings Indigenous history and culture to the forefront. Very well done! I only wish Rose was a more interesting character&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;legacy-of-heorot:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Legacy of Heorot&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Larry Niven, Jerry Pournelle, Steven Barnes (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;200 pioneers arrive to colonize a new planet, but things start to go wrong. I remember enjoying this one as a teenager so thought I&amp;rsquo;d see how it holds up today. Reads like an 80s action movie. Still love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;watch:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Watch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Sawyer (2010)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion about the origin and implications of consciousness, told through an array of interesting characters such as an ape, an emergent AI, a blind teenager who has regained her sight, and an autistic man. Optimistic take on what technology might do for humanity, we need more like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-reconciliation-manifesto:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;The Reconciliation Manifesto&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arthur Manuel (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A straight-forward overview of the legal situation of Indigenous nations in Canada: how we arrived in this situation, and where to go next. The three phases of colonialism: dispossession, dependency, oppression. Manuel argues that pressing for progress in international forums will be more effective than any resolutions being proposed by Canada which are more about extinguishment of Indigenous land title than about rights. Grassroots involvement will be necessary as so-called indigenous &amp;ldquo;leaders&amp;rdquo; have been compromised due to the systemic nature of dependency on government funds. It makes me angry to realize the extent of how Canada is an abuser of human rights. We need more people to understand this now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: My Conversations With Canadians</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 16:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/MyConversationsWithCanadians.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My Conversations With Canadians&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Conversations With Canadians&lt;/em&gt; by Lee Maracle is a thoughtful journey across many topics central to Canada-Indigenous relations (or to use Maracle&amp;rsquo;s suggested term: Canada-&lt;em&gt;Turtle Islander&lt;/em&gt; relations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; this book. It was super approachable and a great education for a non-Turtle Islander like myself, challenging many preconceived ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle recounts conversations she has shared with Canadians ranging in time from the 1970s to the present. She will often linger over questions posed to her by non-Indigenous Canadians, turning the question around for the reader and instead exploring the biases of the questioner - what assumptions do they already have in place, in order to even ask that question? Really eye-opening and I enjoyed this style thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many questions, I also enjoyed how she would confess to the reader how she really wanted to reply, then share what she actually responded with. I admire her grace in what must have been some astonishingly ignorant or rude questions! (And I confess to being one of those ignorant people myself who might be heading along those same lines)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I have come to through all of these experiences is that Canadians don&amp;rsquo;t know much about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education is a cultural process and, of course, the education citizens receive in Canada is all about British contact with Indigenous people and the development and maintenance of Canada. No one studies what was here before in any serious way. It is as though the 150-year history of Canada is far more significant than the 15,000 years previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a sobering thought and so very true. I certainly did not retain much in the way of Indigenous history or knowledge from my Canadian education. That probably means there are at least a generation of people, if not more, who likely have no clue, really (other than stereotypes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle does a good job of imparting the full richness of Turtle Islander culture to her readers, a culture dismissed by settlers, but nevertheless whose influence can be seen on today&amp;rsquo;s world (although that goes unacknowledged).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s humbling to think of all the things we missed learning about in school. What a curriculum it would have made!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was brought up in story. No one disciplined me by spanking or scoldings; rather the old people watching me told a story and I was expected to figure out my behavioural issues from the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I was raised on story, I brought my children up on story. We work with story. We begin with an old tale and, as we progress through the story, we tell it back different but the same, changing it so it becomes a modern new story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle also makes clear that being nice people doesn&amp;rsquo;t give Canadians a pass; she drives home that we are all actively complicit in the genocide of Turtle Islanders, quoting articles from the UN Genocide Convention to support her case. Ignorance may be bliss for some, but morally that stance just doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold up. We have a responsibility to educate ourselves on affairs that are being conducted in our name. It&amp;rsquo;s time for Canadians to get with it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase a statement in the book: de-colonization is not about how the Indigenous world fits into ours, but how we fit into theirs. With this in mind, I sample from Chapter 12 which describes the Turtle Islander belief system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humility is critical to recognizing and examining our failures, our mistakes, our contribution to broken relations [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage gives us the determination to overcome our fear of self-examination, of admitting to our neglect. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honesty teaches us to own our self&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the above be a guide to us Canadians as we reach to build true relations with Turtle Islanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would urge all non-Indigenous folk to pick up this book and see Canada differently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Wrist</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 18:48:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wrist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrist-by-nathan-niigan-noodin-adler:be8d3886104ef6a4ba40f052b87ecea4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; by Nathan Niigan Noodin Adler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; is an Anishinaabe-inspired horror story that I picked up at the Ottawa &lt;em&gt;Writersfest&lt;/em&gt; last year. One of the fun things about this book is that you&amp;rsquo;re never totally certain if the monsters are real. Adler keeps you guessing about whether this is playing out in the imagination of Church, the protagonist, even going so far as to include other characters who themselves don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the monsters. As Adler states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I]t will still devour you, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t believe.
Things that are real don&amp;rsquo;t need you to believe in them, they&amp;rsquo;ll consume you just the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we learn that Church is the son of a Residential school survivor on one side, and a Holocaust survivor on the other, we begin to recognize that perhaps the true horror story being told is the evil of intergenerational trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it was just a delusion [&amp;hellip;], it was real in every sense that mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about this book is that it&amp;rsquo;s not over-edited, so the voice of the author shines through unobscured, almost as though he&amp;rsquo;s reading aloud to you in the oral tradition of the First Nations. In fact, he provides substantial Anishinaabemowin dialog and terminology throughout the book, giving mild language lessons to his readers. I enjoyed reading the Anishinaabek words aloud softly as I went along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique aspect is the scientific emphasis throughout the story. Adler firmly places Indigenous lore within a natural, scientific world, for example beautifully comparing the hunger of the wiindigo to a black hole. Not only does this make the book feel real, almost alive, in a living, breathing kind of way, but also serves as a nice counterpoint to how colonialist society tends to portray Indigenous culture as cliché and static (&lt;em&gt;The Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt;*). Here we are given very much the opposite of that, with a cultural viewpoint that follows along with our evolving understanding of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunger is the central theme in this story, and Adler invites us to consider hunger as something abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we are driven to eat to fill other hungers that can&amp;rsquo;t be filled with food&amp;hellip;Loneliness, sadness, trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading this book during a period of personal grief, had me relating to this. Even though hunger is pain, hunger should not be indulged too deeply, but neither should it be ignored. Excess in either direction will turn one into a monster. That is the warning delivered in &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;. However hunger is also what makes us who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Church is not always sure exactly who he is supposed to be, yet he&amp;rsquo;s proof that one can derive tremendous power and self-worth out of personal beliefs and life experiences, even if many of those are hard experiences. And proof that nobody should be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;wrist&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is given in a preface to the book, with a secondary definition being &lt;em&gt;sleight-of-hand&lt;/em&gt;. So what sleight-of-hand is the author pulling with this novel &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;?  For me, it was filling my spirit with nature, language and appreciation for all that life has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a unique and very original book with many layers to unpack. I look forward to reading more of Adler&amp;rsquo;s work in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt; per Thomas King&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Inconvenient Indian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wristTwitter.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Enterprise Unleashed 2017</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 16:57:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday I was invited by &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; to attend the Social Enterprise Unleashed conference in Ottawa. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-procurement:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Social procurement:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procurement generally follows the &amp;ldquo;Lowest Price Wins&amp;rdquo; model, which misses opportunities to benefit communities and can even cause harm by not respecting the environment nor paying living wages. The triple-bottom-line approach of social enterprise (People, Planet, Profit) needs to be the ultimate goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inroads have been made in recent years on the &amp;ldquo;Planet&amp;rdquo; portion of this - when one thinks &amp;ldquo;sustainable&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s often environmental sustainability that comes to mind, however the &amp;ldquo;People&amp;rdquo; component is what needs focus next to make it truly sustainable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hospitals and police have been promoting social enterprise because they understand that social factors are required to keep people healthy and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.winnipegfreepress.com/opinion/analysis/social-solution-to-budget-woes-a-job-instead-of-prison-414837654.html&#34;&gt;reduce incarceration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should be aiming for a requirement such that when public money is spent on procurement it should include some form of social impact. Scotland is leading the way by requiring all government contracts to add social impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;storytelling-for-impact:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Storytelling for Impact:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General fundamentals of a story involve:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a character (the customer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who has a problem (villain, internal, external, philosophical)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who meets a guide (empathy/trust, authority)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who gives them a plan (process, agreement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and calls them to action (direct call, transitional call)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that ends in a success and helps them avoid failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and also results in a character transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer is the hero, not your brand. Brands that position themselves as heroes unknowingly compete with the customer. Position your brand in terms of what your customers want, not what you&amp;rsquo;re about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good story can not only promote the company externally but have transformational impact on employee engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78mNZeDaMtk?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the customer trust you? The answer is emotional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People want to be taken somewhere - transformation of character. Who does your customer want to become?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clusters-and-accelerators:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Clusters and Accelerators:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we stimulate demand?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we &amp;ldquo;pull&amp;rdquo; social enterprises in rather than enterprises having to push their product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clusters - why?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joint tendering (teaming up with other enterprises to deliver on large opportunities)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;purchasing power, economies of scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shared resources (space, transport, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;promotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning from each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food cluster in Ottawa is 30 enterprises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RiseToTheOccasion.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 14:53:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/rtto.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;
A directory I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://RiseToTheOccasion.ca&#34;&gt;RiseToTheOccasion.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a provincial directory of social enterprises for the event planning sector. If you&amp;rsquo;re planning to put on an event in Ontario, you might like to see what&amp;rsquo;s available, with over 80 enterprises currently listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding on the product delivered by our previous project (the Ottawa directory &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt;), the new directory adds the following enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bilingual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location-based searching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;administrative interface, so that individual enterprises as well as directory administrators can control content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directory was officially launched at the &lt;em&gt;#SEUnleashed&lt;/em&gt; social enterprise conference in Ottawa on November 16th. As a contributor I was invited to attend the conference. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector. I posted more about the conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Dirt Cure</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:15:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/dirtCure.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dirt-cure-by-maya-shetreat-klein:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; by Maya Shetreat-Klein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this book awhile ago with my wife, and wanted circle back and do a recap. &lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; argues that far from being something harmful to be avoided, dirt is actually rather healthy - more specifically, the microbes living in the dirt. This basic premise leads to insights into diet and illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maya’s philosophy is that the health of our inner terrain —our bodies– is a reflection of the health of our outer terrain, the natural world around us. Gut, immune and nervous system — and the many microbes therein — are a direct reflection of the food we eat and where that food comes from, from the soil it’s grown in to the water it swims in to the synthetic chemicals that it’s bathed in.
dirtcure.com/about/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems the scientific references may have been exaggerated in places (my wife is one to fact-check academic studies), there were still enough persuasive arguments in the book to influence how we do things around our household. Here are the key takeaways for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-microbiome-that-we-eat-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The microbiome that we eat, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of consuming bacteria in food I mainly think of probiotics like yogurt. But of course all the food we eat have microbes living in them. Now consider: what if those microbes matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something of a new way of looking at things for me. You&amp;rsquo;re not just sourcing nutrients from the food you eat, you&amp;rsquo;re sourcing microbes. In which case, it follows that where or how your food is grown can impact how healthy it is for you. Was the tomato grown in biodiverse soil? Was the tomato grown in depleted soil? They might look the same to the eye but one might have more benefit to your body. (I look forward to a time when technology is good enough to differentiate these two tomatoes for us in the grocery store!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-terrain-that-we-live-in-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The terrain that we live in, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t live in a vacuum. It was noted that people who grew up on farms had less allergies/asthma than city folks, likely due to the diversity of microbes they are exposed to. &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/804022/health-benefits-japanese-forest-bathing/&#34;&gt;Forest bathing&lt;/a&gt; is also a proven immune-boosting and healing activity. The benefits of being outdoors, especially in nature, are not to be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illness:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Illness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, bad terrain increases susceptibility to illness. The book introduces an analogy that I quite liked: the basin. When toxins (or viruses, germs, etc) enter our system, they go into our basin. Our body flushes the basin to clear the toxins. When the rate at which toxins enter exceeds the rate the body can clear them, the basin overflows. This results in illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a simple analogy but it explains how the cumulative effects of multiple exposures (each maybe harmless on its own) could affect your health. Reduction of a seemingly innocuous exposure (eg. eliminating a processed food from your diet) can have huge impacts when you are currently at, or close to, the tipping point. Even if you are not near the tipping point, you want to keep your basin as clear as possible so that when you do happen to catch a virus, your body has full power to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-book-changed-for-us-personally:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;What this book changed for us personally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think we were already practicing an approximation of the lifestyle promoted by this book. As CSA members we get the bulk of our veggies from local farms, picked the day before, often arriving with the dirt still clinging to them. We live across the street from a forest. Nevertheless, the book spurred us to make a few adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pantry-cleanout:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Pantry cleanout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this was the kick in the butt we needed to review our pantry and clear out a number of dubious foods. Anything processed, anything with additives (artificial sweeteners, food dyes, unpronounceable ingredients) was basically cut. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a strict elimination diet for us and we&amp;rsquo;ll happily enjoy some of those foods, but they don&amp;rsquo;t need to be in our main rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting thing we found is that sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll be using processed foods without even realizing it. Consider cocoa powder. Everyone knows that chocolate (the raw stuff) is healthy for you, so we had been using cocoa powder quite regularly. But look at the difference in nutrients between 20g of a &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; cocoa powder (Fry&amp;rsquo;s brand) vs Organic Traditions brand cacao powder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fry&amp;rsquo;s cocoa powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;140 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organic Traditions cacao powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought these were equivalent but clearly not. One must be more highly processed than the other (the internet seems to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.paleohacks.com/cacao-vs-cocoa/#&#34;&gt;confirm this&lt;/a&gt;). When you consume something regularly, it pays to check. What do you have in your pantry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-foods:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;New foods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was adding new foods into our rotation. Many foods were suggested by the book, but as mentioned we already had a pretty good diet. However, there are a few new items that stuck with us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kefir (loads of diverse microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kimchi (again microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blackstrap molasses (more antioxidants than blueberries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;soups / bone broths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also dabbled in growing our own sprouts, but that was put on hold once we got our CSA and had more than enough greens to consume each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing we&amp;rsquo;ve been doing is making our own stocks, rather than using bouillon cubes. It&amp;rsquo;s super easy to do and a great way to use all the ends of your veggies rather than throwing away those nutrients in the garbage. We collect them in a container in the freezer, then every couple of weeks boil them into a stock that gets used in our soups and other recipes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;has-it-helped:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Has it helped?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not being scientific about it, but my wife was often one to fall sick with colds. It&amp;rsquo;s been more than half a year and she has not had a serious cold yet, which must be a record. I have only taken one sick day over the same period. So far, at least, it seems to be helping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would be interesting to check back a year from now and see how we&amp;rsquo;re doing. I will try to post an update here if I remember&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Do Not Say We Have Nothing</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 16:31:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/doNotSayWeHaveNothing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-not-say-we-have-nothing-by-madeleine-thien:c82c375baf10ac0da7e6de1e08fcf4ef&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do Not Say We Have Nothing&lt;/em&gt; by Madeleine Thien&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess this one took me a while to sink into. There came a point early on when I happened to pause the book and I almost never picked it up again. It sat there on my night table, a reminder, but I&amp;rsquo;d find something else to occupy my time with. Eventually I did continue and I&amp;rsquo;m glad for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is a history of modern China told from the perspective of an everyday family comprising of artists and musicians. One of the fascinating things to me was the role of music in this story. How can an author, any author, truly describe music in a language such as English? It&amp;rsquo;s a tough challenge, but Thien really did justice to it. However the idea of translating one language to another is bound to leave omissions; a more considered reading of this book would involve listening to these pieces yourself (unfortunately I was not committed enough for that, although I am listening as I write this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting topic was seeing how different people react when externally imposed pressures are applied on them from society at large. Some can&amp;rsquo;t go on, some conform, some thrive in resistance. At times I could see myself in Sparrow. I have been known to become a bit of a chameleon of sorts. But if you can&amp;rsquo;t do the things you love, the things you were meant to do.. who are you, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this book won me over by creating very real characters who behaved in ways I did not understand at all. It&amp;rsquo;s powerful to live in someone else&amp;rsquo;s place and be reminded that your way of looking at things is not the only or the best way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up a (free) Password Manager</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/05/07/setting-up-a-free-password-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 15:39:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/05/07/setting-up-a-free-password-manager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of remaining skeptical about password managers (do I really want to put all my eggs in one basket?), I finally caved after realizing that (a) there were simply too many accounts to remember and (b) my email is effectively a basket holding all the eggs already (anyone who gains access to your email account can use the password reset feature to access your other accounts). With that in mind a password manager didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to increase my risk profile any further from it&amp;rsquo;s current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like the popular &lt;em&gt;1Password&lt;/em&gt; offer cloud-based password management across all your devices.. at a cost. $3/month for their basic plan. I was looking for something cheaper than that. Free, ideally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://keepass.info/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;KeePass&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lightweight open source password manager. The Windows client is so lightweight you don&amp;rsquo;t even have to install it. It&amp;rsquo;s just an &lt;code&gt;exe&lt;/code&gt; file that sits in a folder. After opening KeePass, you add new entries for each of your passwords, or you can import passwords from other password managers (although I was starting from scratch so I didn&amp;rsquo;t explore this further). The resulting password database is just an encrypted file that is safe to move around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to make your passwords available to other devices, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to share this file with those devices. For my purposes, my phone is the only other device I deal with. I installed the Android app &lt;em&gt;KeePassDroid&lt;/em&gt;, copied over the password database by USB, and now I&amp;rsquo;m set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawback with this approach is it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have cloud sync. I could have hosted my password database in my own cloud if I really wanted to, but actually I&amp;rsquo;ve found a simpler way to sync. These days, I always have my phone nearby! Hence the password database on my phone becomes my primary database, and all edits are done in my phone (it&amp;rsquo;s pretty rare that I have to add or change a password anyway). Then periodically about once a month or so, when I normally backup my phone I also transfer my password database over at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple approach to password management, but it meets my needs. I guess you can look at it as a cheap alternative to the pay services out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years later I am still using this system and find it works well for me. One gotcha is at one point my KeePassDroid app on my phone corrupted the password file (software bug that&amp;rsquo;s been fixed, apparently). The file still worked on my phone but I could not unlock the passwords on any other device and I had to rollback to a backup file. So it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep a backup, and also be careful not to overwrite the backup by mistake (everytime I take a backup I put the date in the backup filename like &amp;ldquo;passwords.May2019.kdbx&amp;rdquo;, this is a good practice to follow).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>