<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 07:36:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracing GitLab builds in Honeycomb</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/04/08/tracing-gitlab-builds-in-honeycomb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 07:36:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/04/08/tracing-gitlab-builds-in-honeycomb/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;By adding observability to your builds you can start to understand where your build time is being spent and how to optimize your builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.honeycomb.io/&#34;&gt;Honeycomb&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic observability platform, and they provide a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/honeycombio/buildevents&#34;&gt;buildevents&lt;/a&gt; tool you can use to instrument your builds. Here is a simple approach to instrumenting a GitLab build pipeline with Honeycomb tracing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-1-pre-post-build:4402c9a8a44846155fbda4ac86a91fde&#34;&gt;Step 1: Pre/Post build&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instrumenting your build requires some work at the start and end of your build. In GitLab one way to achieve this is by introducing a &lt;em&gt;stage&lt;/em&gt; at the start and and the end of your pipeline. Let&amp;rsquo;s call these stages &lt;code&gt;initialization&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;tracing&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;stages:
   - initialization
   - ...(your regular build stages remain here)...
   - tracing
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initialization stage sets us up by doing two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;storing the start time of the build (to be used later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;downloading the &lt;code&gt;buildevents&lt;/code&gt; tool, which is a small binary used for tracing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are exposed as artifacts to make them available later in the build. Here is what this stage looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;initialization:
  stage: initialization
  image: (your preferred image here, this example is based on an alpine image)
  script:
    - date +%s &amp;gt;build_start_time
    - apk add curl
    - curl -L -o buildevents https://github.com/honeycombio/buildevents/releases/latest/download/buildevents-linux-amd64
    - chmod 755 buildevents
  artifacts:
    paths:
      - buildevents
      - build_start_time
    expire_in: 3 days
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;tracing&lt;/code&gt; stage runs at the end of the build and closes off the trace. A trace URL is printed here so that you can click through the URL to arrive directly at the trace view in Honeycomb!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;tracing:
  stage: tracing
  script:
    - export BUILD_ID=$CI_PIPELINE_ID
    - export BUILD_START_TIME=$(cat ./build_start_time)
    - traceURL=$(.buildevents build $BUILD_ID $BUILD_START_TIME success)
    - echo &amp;quot;Honeycomb Trace $traceURL&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-2-instrumenting-jobs:4402c9a8a44846155fbda4ac86a91fde&#34;&gt;Step 2: Instrumenting jobs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A GitLab build is comprised of multiple jobs. You can create a trace span for each individual GitLab job in your build by doing a bit of work before and after the job. A job template can help with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;.job_template: &amp;amp;traced_job
before_script:
  - date +%s &amp;gt; /tmp/job_start_time
  - apk add bash
  - export BUILD_ID=$CI_PIPELINE_ID
  - export STEP_ID=$CI_JOB_ID-$CI_COMMIT_SHORT_SHA
  - export NAME=$CI_JOB_NAME
after_script:
  - export BUILD_ID=$CI_PIPELINE_ID
  - export STEP_ID=$CI_JOB_ID-$CI_COMMIT_SHORT_SHA
  - export NAME=$CI_JOB_NAME
  - export START_TIME=$(cat /tmp/job_start_time)
  - echo &amp;quot;Sending honeycomb trace for ${NAME} (id= ${STEP_ID}) within ${BUILD_ID} pipeline starting at ${START_TIME}&amp;quot;
  - ./buildevents step $BUILD_ID $STEP_ID $START_TIME $NAME
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this template defined, adding tracing to your job is as simple as adding a YAML anchor at the start of the job definition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;compile:
  &amp;lt;&amp;lt;: *traced_job
  stage: compile
  ...

deploy:
  &amp;lt;&amp;lt;: *traced_job
  stage: deploy
  ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-3-instrumenting-individual-commands:4402c9a8a44846155fbda4ac86a91fde&#34;&gt;Step 3: Instrumenting individual commands&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a job, there may be several commands that get executed. It can be very helpful to see how long certain commands are taking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if the command you&amp;rsquo;re trying to run is &lt;code&gt;mix compile&lt;/code&gt;, you can simply wrap it with a call to &lt;code&gt;buildevents&lt;/code&gt; like so, and supply a name for your trace span:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;./buildevents cmd $BUILD_ID $STEP_ID give_a_name_for_this_trace_span -- mix compile
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will create a trace span around the execution of this command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;limitations:4402c9a8a44846155fbda4ac86a91fde&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This implementation does not trace failed builds, only successes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It won&amp;rsquo;t capture time spent waiting for a GitLab runner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The artifacts in the &lt;code&gt;initialization&lt;/code&gt; stage are set to expire after 3 days. If someone hits &amp;ldquo;Retry&amp;rdquo; on this build after a time period longer than that, these artifacts will no longer be available and so the build will fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;wrap-up:4402c9a8a44846155fbda4ac86a91fde&#34;&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simple approach to tracing builds. Despite its limitations, I have found it&amp;rsquo;s sufficient to get me going with tracing and to start me on the path to optimizing my builds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book: 24/6 The Power of Unplugging One Day a Week</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-24/6-the-power-of-unplugging-one-day-a-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 17:57:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-24/6-the-power-of-unplugging-one-day-a-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/24-6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;24/6&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;24 / 6&lt;/em&gt; Tiffany Shlain proposes an antidote to the burdens of the modern world with a &amp;ldquo;Tech Shabbat&amp;rdquo;, a one-day reprieve from screens of all kind. Rather than define it using a negative, Shlain focuses on the positive by promoting it as a day to do all the things you always wished you had time for. I believe many of us dream of such a possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about this idea from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-139-tiffany-shlain-unplugging-one-day-a-week-tribute-to-paul-krassner&#34;&gt;Shlain&amp;rsquo;s interview on the Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt; and was immediately excited about it. At the time of writing, I have completed my first Tech Shabbat with my family, and we&amp;rsquo;re very happy with how it went. We lit a candle to emphasize the transition. Going to bed early, fancy breakfast, listening to music, reading, thinking, having long conversations, spending time outdoors, napping&amp;hellip; it was glorious. I agree with Shlain when she says her Shabbat always feels longer than one day, it did for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the book is concerned, I was underwhelmed. I did find it useful to be shown specific examples of what Shabbat could entail, and I appreciated the emphasis on everyone defining their own rules and traditions in a way that works for them. Otherwise I found the book repetitive and the science chapters were not rigorous enough for my liking. In other parts I was finding it too autobiographical, I was not interested in the details&amp;hellip; but then I realized that was actually the whole point of Shabbat! Shlain sees the Tech Shabbat as a technology, a tool that extends her purpose into the world and so it&amp;rsquo;s quite impossible for her to talk about her Shabbat without also getting into her own goals and activities. And this insight turns it back onto the reader to decide (which I will do the same to you, dear reader):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your purpose? What are the things you always wished you had time for?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book: Perihelion Summer</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-perihelion-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 13:38:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-perihelion-summer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/perihelionSummer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Perihelion Summer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of &lt;em&gt;Perhihelion Summer&lt;/em&gt; by Greg Egan involves the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit shifting slightly, resulting in an instant climate crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ensuing desperation reminds me of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seveneves&#34;&gt;Seveneves&lt;/a&gt;, another novel dealing with an emergency of astronomical proportions. I love survival stories like these where forward-thinking actors manage to design and execute on an improbable pathway out of doom, and then seeing how existence turns almost exclusively into resourcefulness, and the managing of equipment and knowledge against the perils of time, nature, and human conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it exciting to have this story centered on Australia. In a universe where the Northern hemisphere is again privileged, the author places a fully-developed nation and its citizens in the exact same boat as other climate refugees, giving a direct taste of the crisis to those of us (such as us Canadians), who might otherwise believe ourselves to be insulated from the coming effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the ensuing denial (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we can manage&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we have a year&amp;rsquo;s worth of food in the freezer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;) and the government response (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;more insulation on your house&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;security drones&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;) are a nod to our current times, our inaction, distrust, and feeble measures in the face of the coming threat. By designing the world such that climate change is already visible and strikingly in effect for all to see, it lends the portrayed denials a much more ridiculous air, exposing the folly of these various courses of action quite vividly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accelerating the crisis, and giving a glimpse of the refugee experience, this book turns a mirror on our own responsibility to act in the climate crisis. Hopefully these lessons can help us better empathize with each other and act with the urgency that is required.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap 2020</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/12/27/book-recap-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 12:23:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/12/27/book-recap-2020/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;2020 was a little lighter on reading as I delved a bit more into podcasts and movies, but I did get to some good ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;little-failure:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Little Failure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gary Shteyngart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/littleFailure.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Little Failure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first half was a pretty wild account of growing up in the USSR and lower-class New York, told with a dry humour, the kind I like best! The second half (college onwards) felt more scattered and didn&amp;rsquo;t resonate with me, perhaps I was lacking some cultural context around American colleges and politics, but I lost interest. He mentioned at one point this was his &amp;ldquo;first memoir&amp;rdquo; and I wonder if it might be revisited in a later text to greater effect. Even so, I would be unlikely to pick it up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;jonny-appleseed:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Jonny Appleseed&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joshua Whitehead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/jonnyAppleseed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jonny Appleseed&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book comes at you hard with the sexuality, but after the initial double-take it settles into you with its earnest and honest narration. A window into rez culture and queerness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;an-absolutely-remarkable-thing:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;An Absolutely Remarkable Thing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hank Green&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/anAbsolutelyRemarkableThing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An Absolutely Remarkable Thing&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-beautifully-foolish-endeavor:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;A Beautifully Foolish Endeavor&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hank Green&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/aBeautifullyFoolishEndeavor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Beautifully Foolish Endeavor&#34; /&gt;
Notes coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;antifragile:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Antifragile&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nassim Nicholas Taleb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/antifragile.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Antifragile&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-only-good-indians:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;The Only Good Indians&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stephen Graham Jones&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/onlyGoodIndians.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Only Good Indians&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment partway through this book that had you really questioning everything you thought you knew, and I was really excited to continue along that train of thought. But the mystery was kind of taken away as the story continued on and that made me sad but nevertheless I still enjoyed the rest of the book and would recommend it. Indigenous-authored horror stories are becoming a new favourite for me. The echoes of intergenerational trauma, and hinting at breaking the cycle and new possibilities/hope, are powerful themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;empire-of-wild:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Empire of Wild&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cherie Dimaline&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/empireOfWild.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Empire of Wild&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A horror/thriller that had me laughing out loud within the first couple chapters. Loved the little references to Canada and the phoniness of reconciliation. A story that challenges Western norms by blurring family units, reinforcing wisdom of elders and story. Deals directly with themes of Western entrapment and dispossession; the reverend as the wolf in sheepskin, a vessel to be used for colonization. There is a strong message about not giving up through hardship, even when defeat appears foregone and inevitable, which is a message that is extremely relevant today - because nothing is truly inevitable. And also: don&amp;rsquo;t forget how to treat your relations or you&amp;rsquo;ll turn into a monster :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic movie binge</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/07/25/pandemic-movie-binge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 13:28:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/07/25/pandemic-movie-binge/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With the pandemic preventing us from attending cinemas, I &amp;ldquo;splurged&amp;rdquo; for the HBO+Movies streaming package on Crave TV and spent a whole month binging movies until the subscription expired. It was a lot of fun and I definitely got my fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;5-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;5 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/ask_dr_ruth&#34;&gt;Ask Dr. Ruth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_hate_u_give&#34;&gt;The Hate U Give&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/joker_2019&#34;&gt;Joker&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;excellent movie although I can understand the controversy around it glorifying violence, which is a shame because there was another message in there about mental health patients falling through the cracks due to funding cuts.. and with a few very minor tweaks that could have been the takeaway message&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/james_vs_his_future_self&#34;&gt;James vs His Future Self&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;nerdy, Canadian.. yep I&amp;rsquo;m here for this!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/giant_little_ones&#34;&gt;Giant Little Ones&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;one of my favs so far.. found out afterwards it was also a Canadian movie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/indian_horse&#34;&gt;Indian Horse&lt;/a&gt; - haunting long after the movie is over&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/maiden&#34;&gt;Maiden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;4-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;4 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/men_in_black_international&#34;&gt;MIB International&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;surprisingly quite enjoyed this, went in with zero expectations (that probably helped) but liked the general irreverent tone throughout&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/abominable_2019&#34;&gt;Abominable&lt;/a&gt; (2019) - &lt;em&gt;a good choice if you&amp;rsquo;re in the mood for a kids movie (and aren&amp;rsquo;t we all from time to time?)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_peanut_butter_falcon&#34;&gt;The Peanut Butter Falcon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/isnt_it_romantic_2019&#34;&gt;Isn&amp;rsquo;t It Romantic&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;a rom-com that pokes fun at rom-coms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/us_2019&#34;&gt;Us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/bohemian_rhapsody&#34;&gt;Bohemian Rhapsody&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Mr. Robot as Mr. Mercury&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/bohemian_rhapsody&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;lighthearted fare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;3-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;3 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/blood_quantum&#34;&gt;Blood Quantum&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;was super pumped for this, and it was a 5-star start but didn&amp;rsquo;t sustain, I found out later the filming was &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; finished when they ran out of funds, I guess that might explain it.. still alright for a low budget film if you are type to enjoy zombie violence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_immortal_life_of_henrietta_lacks&#34;&gt;The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/ready_or_not_2019&#34;&gt;Ready or Not&lt;/a&gt; (2019) - &lt;em&gt;would have got 4 from me if it had slanted slightly more to the humour side, but that&amp;rsquo;s more of a personal style preference on my part&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/fast_color&#34;&gt;Fast Color&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;liked the story but it was a tad slow paced for my tastes, wish it were 10 minutes shorter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/once_upon_a_time_in_hollywood&#34;&gt;Once Upon a Time in Hollywood&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;definitely a few LOL moments, but unless you love Tarantino or 1960s nostalgia it&amp;rsquo;s not worth 2h40m of your time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_mustang&#34;&gt;The Mustang&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;nice animal/human connection story without falling into Disney&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/blinded_by_the_light&#34;&gt;Blinded by the Light&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;if you like Springsteen I imagine you&amp;rsquo;d really like this movie&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/good_boys_2019&#34;&gt;Good Boys&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;quite a few LOLs, but I was finding it somewhat tiresome by the end&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/clemency_2019&#34;&gt;Clemency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_miseducation_of_cameron_post_2018&#34;&gt;The Miseducation of Cameron Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/godzilla_king_of_the_monsters_2019&#34;&gt;Godzilla: King of Monsters&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;comes as advertised, if that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for (yes please)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stuber&#34;&gt;Stuber&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;good one for a laugh, for when you don&amp;rsquo;t want to think&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;2-stars:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;2 Stars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/it_chapter_two&#34;&gt;IT Chapter Two&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;chapter 1 was 5 stars for me. I really love the IT franchise and I wanted to like this too.. but can&amp;rsquo;t recommend it, too repetitive especially after the first chapter.. By the end of it you&amp;rsquo;ll be sick of CGI fight scenes in the sewers. The self-aware moments were the best parts but they don&amp;rsquo;t save the movie. Also the gratuitous hate crime against homosexuals to open things was extremely off-putting and in this day and age should have been cut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/climax&#34;&gt;Climax&lt;/a&gt; (2018) - &lt;em&gt;the buildup had me intrigued but the roller coaster ride itself was a letdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_art_of_self_defense_2019&#34;&gt;The Art of Self-Defence&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;was hoping for more of a comedy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;1-star:b32773f8f9928cb7b67688751e34ecfe&#34;&gt;1 Star&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/in_fabric&#34;&gt;In Fabric&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;92% critics score, 48% audience score.. I side with the audience on this one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/alpha_2018&#34;&gt;Alpha&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;a visually pretty movie, but so many small touches felt unrealistic about how a prehistoric culture would have been.. maybe if you turn off your analytical brain it would be enjoyable&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>StudioTax 2019 on Ubuntu</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/05/24/studiotax-2019-on-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2020 14:44:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/05/24/studiotax-2019-on-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.studiotax.com&#34;&gt;StudioTax&lt;/a&gt; is free tax software for Canadians. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty great to have this free way to file your taxes, but the supported operating systems are Windows, Mac, iOS and Android.. unfortunately no Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watering_hole_attack&#34;&gt;security reasons&lt;/a&gt;, I never do work with sensitive/confidential information on the same system I use for browsing/social media/general use.. This rules out doing anything tax-related on my phone. But luckily it&amp;rsquo;s quite easy to spin up a secure Ubuntu system on any old laptop or desktop you may have lying around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how I got StudioTax running on Ubuntu with VirtualBox:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Ubuntu 20.04. Make sure you&amp;rsquo;ll have 20-30 GB free disk space after ubuntu is installed (needed to start windows in VirtualBox).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply all the latest patches on Ubuntu to be sure you have the latest security updates before starting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.virtualbox.org/&#34;&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/software-download/windows10&#34;&gt;Windows 10&lt;/a&gt; ISO file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use VirtualBox to install a Windows 10 system inside of your Ubuntu system. (Link the ISO file into the &amp;ldquo;Storage&amp;rdquo; settings to get the Windows installation going).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once Windows is installed and running, apply all Windows updates to make sure you have the latest security updates before you start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Windows now, you can download StudioTax. Install StudioTax as administrator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good to go!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To transfer files between Ubuntu and Windows, you can do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In VirtualBox menu of the running Windows system, go to &amp;ldquo;Devices -&amp;gt; Insert Guest Additions CD Image&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Windows now, open the File explorer and navigate to the newly added &amp;ldquo;CD Drive&amp;rdquo;. Run the application VBoxWindowsAdditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In VirtualBox menu go to &amp;ldquo;Machine -&amp;gt; Settings -&amp;gt; Shared Folders&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add new shared folder. Select the Ubuntu folder you would like to share, and for the mount point you can just put &lt;code&gt;G:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;G:&lt;/code&gt; location should now appear in Windows File Explorer and you can use it like any other folder. (If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t show, check under the &amp;ldquo;Network&amp;rdquo; section of File Explorer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: 2019</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 09:48:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A year&amp;rsquo;s worth of reading and no book blog posts? Well, better late than never! In addition to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/&#34;&gt;new parent selections&lt;/a&gt;, here are a few of the books I read this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;team-human:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Team Human&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Douglas Rushkoff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/teamHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Team Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt; is a podcast and now a book which I read around the time of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/&#34;&gt;his visit to the Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s well worth a read and captures the main thesis that even more technology won&amp;rsquo;t solve our problems so long as we keep treating problems as unconnected; but as humans we&amp;rsquo;re fully equipped to form communities and launch a modern renaissance that respects humanity - if only we would recognize and choose to do so. Probably the most important book of 2019, in my opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lana-and-lilly-wachowski:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cáel M. Keegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wachowskis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dense academic book within a series on &lt;em&gt;Contemporary Film Directors&lt;/em&gt;, this text looks at the Wachowskis oeuvre through a trans* lens, giving a whole new meaning to &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, one of my favourite movies. It also leads an insightful reading into &lt;em&gt;Sense8&lt;/em&gt;, probably my favourite TV show in recent memory. This book introduced me to &lt;em&gt;Bound&lt;/em&gt;, the Wachowskis&amp;rsquo; first major film, which is excellent and worth watching if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book is a simply terrific interview with Lana Wachowski.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;] A lot of your work seems to be very concerned with the idea of moving through space and time differently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s an opposing narrative. The dominant cultural narrative is that things are static. There&amp;rsquo;s a foundational myth about America, about identity, about heteronormativity. [&amp;hellip;] &amp;ldquo;This is the way it is.&amp;rdquo; This is even the concept of normalcy. Normalcy is non-moving. It&amp;rsquo;s a fixed idea. All of my narratives are an assault against this idea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;Would you describe yourself as utopian, then?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;Obviously I would resist any label&amp;hellip;but I think the making of art is inherently optimistic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-doesn-t-have-to-be-crazy-at-work:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;It Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/itDoesntHaveToBeCrazyAtWork.png&#34; alt=&#34;It Doesn&#39;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manual for setting a &lt;em&gt;calm&lt;/em&gt; work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s constantly crazy at work, we have two words for you: Fuck that. And two more: Enough already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of it all is an unhealthy obsession with rapid growth. Towering, unrealistic expectations drag people down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time for companies to stop asking their employees to breathlessly chase ever-higher, ever-more artificial targets set by ego, not need. It’s time to stop celebrating this way of working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few topics that really resonated with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FOMO? JOMO!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People should be missing out. Most people should be missing out on most things most of the time. [&amp;hellip;] JOMO! The joy of missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be a knee-jerk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person making the pitch has presumably put a lot of time, thought, and energy into gathering their thoughts and presenting them clearly to an audience. But the rest of the people in the room are asked to react. Not absorb, not think it over, not consider - just react. Knee-jerk it. That&amp;rsquo;s no way to treat fragile new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t want reactions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want first impressions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want knee-jerks. We want considered feedback. Read it over. Read it twice, three times even. Sleep on it. Take your time to gather and present your thoughts - just like the person who pitched the original idea took their time to gather and present theirs. That&amp;rsquo;s how you go deep on an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All subject matter experts at Basecamp now publish office hours. [&amp;hellip;] This might seem inefficient at first glance. Bureaucratic, even. But we&amp;rsquo;ve seen otherwise. Office hours have been a big hit at Basecamp. It turns out that waiting is no big deal most of the time. But the time and control regained by our experts is a huge deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your company is a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company is like software. It has to be usable, it has to be useful. And it probably also has bugs, places where the company crashes because of bad organizational design or cultural oversights. When you start to think of your company as a product, all sorts of new possibilities for improvement emerge. When you realize the way you work is malleable, you can start molding something new, something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;prediction-machines:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ajay Agrawal, Joshua Gans, Avi Goldfarb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/predictionMachines.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prediction Machines&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by three economists, &lt;em&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/em&gt; takes the &amp;ldquo;mystery&amp;rdquo; out of AI by re-casting it within an economic framework and simply treating it as cheaper prediction, and then following the consequences of seeing it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t love this book but I don&amp;rsquo;t have much argument with the premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-after-the-end:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Love After the End&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2019)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/loveAfterTheEnd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Love After the End&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sci-fi anthology of short stories about Two-Spirit utopias and dystopias, a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you survive a perfect world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, how do you grow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an imperfect world, how do you resist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]
Imagine the future of our people after the end of colonization. Read stories of survival and love lost and found, across all bodies and genders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered this book through a Kickstarter campaign. The introduction by Joshua Whitehead was a beautiful way to set the context for the reader (probably my favourite part of the book actually, which is not taking anything away from the stories but more a statement on how great of an introduction it was).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite stories were Darcie Little Badger&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Story for a Bottle&lt;/em&gt;, jaye simpson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Ark of the Turtle&amp;rsquo;s Back&lt;/em&gt;, and Adam Garnet Jones&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;The New World&lt;/em&gt;. Highly recommend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;permanent-record:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Permanent Record&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/permanentRecord.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Permanent Record&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am halfway through reading Snowden&amp;rsquo;s autobiography. It&amp;rsquo;s a great read thus far, but I&amp;rsquo;m only just getting to the famous parts of his story. When you know the ending, it&amp;rsquo;s tempting to look back and pick out only the events that supported the outcome (which is of course a common bias). I feel as though that&amp;rsquo;s what Snowden has done with his memoir when describing his early days; probably a more rounded story would be a bit more nuanced, but hey he&amp;rsquo;s writing for an audience after all. And it&amp;rsquo;s all very interesting stuff. Looking forward to the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;democracy-may-not-exist-but-we-ll-miss-it-when-it-s-gone:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Democracy May Not Exist But We&amp;rsquo;ll Miss It When It&amp;rsquo;s Gone&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Astra Taylor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/democracyMayNotExist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Democracy May Not Exist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m only a few chapters into this one and I need to re-request it from the library again to finish it. This is an eye-opening book about how the public doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a good idea of what democracy is (although we think we do) and how it&amp;rsquo;s really more about straight up conflicting principles (eg. equality versus freedom) and how the tensions between these principles are perpetually at play and continuously needing resolution through community. Put in another form: democracy is more of a verb than a noun. I discovered this book through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-130-astra-taylor-democracy-is-a-verb/&#34;&gt;Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m really looking forward to completing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources for New Parents</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 20:11:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Having recently gone through the birth of our first child, the following were helpful resources that I felt worth documenting here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-birth-partner:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;The Birth Partner&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Complete Guide to Childbirth for Dads, Doulas, and All Other Labor Companions&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/birthPartner.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Birth Partner&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommended by our midwife. By far the best reference about what goes on during labour and delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cribsheet:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;Cribsheet&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/cribsheet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cribsheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;A data-driven guide to better, more relaxed parenting&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released this year, this book takes a data-driven approach to answer all kinds of choices facing parents regarding their newborn. We liked this one for the non-judgmental tone and the evidence-based advice. The author also has another book in the same style which covers pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-to-expect-when-you-re-expecting-the-first-year:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;What to Expect (When You&amp;rsquo;re Expecting | The First Year)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/whatToExpect.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;What to Expect&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quintessential classic is a great reference. I use this whenever I want to ask &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;what do most people do&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. It really does cover a lot of ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;24-hour-cribside-assistance:2bf8776aa6ac3a9c0d1bf0301d9e6345&#34;&gt;24 Hour Cribside Assistance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newdadmanual.ca/&#34;&gt;24 Hour Cribside Assistance&lt;/a&gt; is an online guide for new fathers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Douglas Rushkoff at Writersfest</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 10:26:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I had the pleasure of listening to Douglas Rushkoff speak at the spring edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writersfestival.org/&#34;&gt;Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. Rushkoff is one of my favourite thinkers and host of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; podcast, as well as author of the new book &lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very little prompting is needed by the host to set off intriguing ruminations from Rushkoff about technology, media and society. Rushkoff walks us through the medieval inventions of the corporation and growth-based currency (currency that has to be borrowed and paid back with interest), both of which were introduced for the purpose of suppressing the middle class so that the ruling class could preserve their wealth in an increasingly peer-to-peer marketplace environment. These concepts have continued straight through to today and now form the unquestioned &amp;ldquo;operating system&amp;rdquo; upon which our whole economy is built. Rushkoff points to these two as the root cause of many of the strange effects that technology is having on society today, and how tech companies, for all their talk of disruption, have not considered challenging these basic assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff talks about reversals that happen with technology (in his own terms, the &lt;em&gt;figure&lt;/em&gt; vs the &lt;em&gt;ground&lt;/em&gt;), whereby over time the users of a technology become themselves used by it (the book goes into this concept much more). Rushkoff draws a parallel between colonization (a term we are familiar with in Canada to describe the structural violence against Indigenous peoples) and the effect that digital technology is having on us today. There is no denying the harm that technology can cause to our wellbeing and to that of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff points out that the best consumer is an isolated consumer. As such, growth-based technologies act to push us apart. He recalls watching TV together as a family while growing up, and going to the theatres to watch a movie. These days we consume media in individualistic ways designed to make us more susceptible to surveillance and targeted advertising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff warns that we can lose our human souls (or just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/JamesBrownOfficial&#34;&gt;soul&lt;/a&gt; with reference to James Brown, for those who don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the former concept) by profit-focused algorithms that try to &amp;ldquo;auto-tune&amp;rdquo; our behaviour so that we better fit our algorithmically predicted buckets. Weirdness is what makes us human, and should be celebrated. Life is everything that happens in between the &amp;ldquo;notes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are warned to think of digital technologies as drugs - you&amp;rsquo;re on Facebook, on Twitter, on-line.. He quotes Timothy Leary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Before you take a drug, look into the eye of someone who&amp;rsquo;s done that drug. Decide if that&amp;rsquo;s a place you want to be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have the choice not to do so. Rushkoff suggests we try practicing a &lt;em&gt;Tech Sabbath&lt;/em&gt; - consuming no digital technologies on Sundays. Then, level that up further by cutting out cars as well. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple idea but one can easily imagine how that would foster local communities in a serious way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rushkoff peppers the talk with repeated calls to respecting human dignity and human values. He calls on us to make local connections, be a part of &lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;Breathe together&amp;rdquo; he instructs us, explaining how this is literally the etymological basis for the term &lt;em&gt;conspire&lt;/em&gt;. And by connecting and interacting offline, face-to-face we are also &lt;em&gt;conspiring&lt;/em&gt; against the companies that are trying to make a dollar off our interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Smart&#34; City coming to Ottawa?</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 08:50:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was stirred to write a blog post after stumbling across an op-ed titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/index.php/article/op-ed-forget-about-toronto-sidewalk-labs-build-smart-neighbourhood-ottawa-instead&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forget about Toronto, Sidewalk Labs – build a smart neighbourhood in Ottawa instead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been following Toronto&amp;rsquo;s efforts at smart city development for the past 9 months (aka the Sidewalk Labs debacle), and was alarmed to read this same group might bring their bad behaviour to Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sidewalk Labs&amp;rsquo; smart city in Toronto has woeful accountability (and its leaked plans are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalobserver.com/2019/02/15/news/alphabets-sidewalk-labs-was-secretly-considering-big-plans-toronto-neighbourhood&#34;&gt;terrifying&lt;/a&gt;), with high profile &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2018/10/20/privacy-expert-steps-down-from-advisory-role-with-sidewalk-labs.html&#34;&gt;resignations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://business.financialpost.com/technology/sidewalk-labs-advisory-panel-member-saadia-muzaffar-resigns-citing-deep-dismay&#34;&gt;leading tech experts&lt;/a&gt;. And yet they continue to go forward. Explain why would anyone would want that for their city?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The op-ed author says that a data policy is necessary upfront (which I absolutely agree with) while in the same breath telling us we should &amp;ldquo;inform these businesses they could start developing a smart community in Ottawa today&amp;rdquo;. Seems like a contradiction there. A public data policy must be something that is carefully debated and not rushed through. It&amp;rsquo;s exactly this kind of &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out as we go&amp;rdquo; mentality that got Toronto into trouble. It opens the door for corporate definition and interference in policy (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@biancawylie/sidewalk-toronto-gaslighting-toronto-residents-backfired-capacitys-built-and-power-s-shifted-77c455b150a3&#34;&gt;gas lighting&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Toronto&amp;rsquo;s failure, and with many thanks to the citizens advocating in opposition there, here is what Ottawa can and should do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start working on privacy and data governance policies. Today! This needs to happen ASAP or we &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get bullied by corporations into rushed or inadequate policies. This needs to be carefully debated and done so in a fully transparent way.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we have any smart city policies already? I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laughably, Ottawa&amp;rsquo;s published &lt;a href=&#34;https://documents.ottawa.ca/sites/default/files/smart_city_strategy_en.pdf&#34;&gt;Smart City 2.0 Strategy&lt;/a&gt; does not have a single reference to &amp;ldquo;privacy&amp;rdquo; or even &amp;ldquo;data governance&amp;rdquo; in its strategy. (Yes you read that correctly. I wish I was joking.). Really shows where the priorities are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, as a city let&amp;rsquo;s first be explicit about what features we want from our smart city, and debate those features in a public setting. Not all &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; technology is smart for society or the public as a whole. We should not give carte blanche to corporations to &amp;ldquo;disrupt&amp;rdquo; neighbourhoods however they see fit, as if breaking neighbourhoods was even a good thing.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s follow the principle of &lt;a href=&#34;http://spacing.ca/toronto/2019/02/19/did-the-sidewalk-labs-plot-just-thicken-or-is-the-story-coming-to-an-end/&#34;&gt;Consult first, then procure.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to OBJ for the balanced journalism in also including an article on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/article/web-data-collected-smart-city-tech-stokes-privacy-fears&#34;&gt;privacy concerns&lt;/a&gt; surrounding smart city development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blocksidewalk.ca/&#34;&gt;BlockSidewalk&lt;/a&gt; movement to stay up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life Insurance Calculator</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/19/life-insurance-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 20:19:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/19/life-insurance-calculator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With a baby on the way later this year, it&amp;rsquo;s the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve had to contemplate taking care of a dependent (not counting pets of course). One of the duties in this regard is ensuring that your dependent will be financially supported in the event of your death. Not a pleasant topic to think about, unless maybe you are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/travel/story/20150408-bhutans-dark-secret-to-happiness&#34;&gt;from Bhutan&lt;/a&gt;, but a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main question is how much insurance do I need? To answer, I threw together &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/LifeInsuranceCalculator.ods&#34;&gt;this LibreOffice spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; as a &amp;ldquo;back of the napkin&amp;rdquo; type calculator. It is definitely only meant as a rough guide and does not rigorously examine inflation nor taxes to a fine precision (although it does take them into account somewhat). The cells in blue are what you will edit to set the parameters for your specific case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losing a parent is probably not going to easy for a child, so I am erring on the side of overcompensation. Post-secondary education is one such example that others might consider optional, but I wanted to ensure it was fully covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised at the cost of post-secondary education compared to 15-20 years ago. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what form education will even take in 20 years, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to imagine the costs continuing to rise and the value proposition still being there in an age of information abundance. Nevertheless, I am including it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;both parents die&amp;rdquo; case was also interesting to examine. I thought for sure it would be the worst case scenario, financially speaking, but turns out it&amp;rsquo;s a non-issue when both parents have some retirement savings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soundtrack of 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/soundtrack-of-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 21:03:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/soundtrack-of-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Music has a curious way of permeating your life, such that years later a song can stir up forgotten memories and emotions. Each song is precious in a way that only we can fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These songs formed the soundtrack of my life in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-violin-stereotypes-album-2015:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Black Violin - Stereotypes (album 2015)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mix of hip hop and classical, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blackviolin.net/videos/&#34;&gt;Black Violin&lt;/a&gt; pushes the boundaries of each genre. I&amp;rsquo;ve actually been listening to this album for a couple years now and still not tired of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/blackViolin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Stereotypes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-toast-light:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Dr. Toast - Light&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A constant at the yoga studio, this song takes me straight to my centered happy place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://music.drtoast.com/track/light&#34;&gt;https://music.drtoast.com/track/light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonobo-sweetness-bootleg-album-2002:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Bonobo - Sweetness (bootleg album 2002)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my album of choice to listen while coding this year. Enough repetition to let your mind focus, enough complexity to keep things interesting when you surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wdpDtAjZuWQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-balconies-show-you-album-2012:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;The Balconies - Show You (album 2012)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Balconies&#34;&gt;The Balconies&lt;/a&gt; are a local Ottawa rock/pop band who I was into 10 years ago. This album was recorded in 2012 but never released because the band&amp;rsquo;s style had changed in the intervening time, so they kept it hidden away for all these years. I was more a fan of their old style anyway so once the band folded and released the forgotten album I was very happy to have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/8721557&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;various-irish-artists-musical-pub-crawl-album:3b321d1d7fe4b2b31d5166b39ac74672&#34;&gt;Various Irish artists - Musical Pub Crawl (album)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our travels in Ireland this year took as to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.musicalpubcrawl.com&#34;&gt;musical pub crawl&lt;/a&gt; in Dublin. We were able to purchase an album of traditional Irish music which is exceptional but I cannot find it online. It&amp;rsquo;s become our staple soundtrack this year while cooking and doing stuff around the house.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advent of Code 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/advent-of-code-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 13:20:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/02/12/advent-of-code-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This past December I discovered the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://adventofcode.com/2018&#34;&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; challenge, in which you get a different coding puzzle for each day in December leading up to Christmas. The puzzles can be solved in any programming language of your choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to solve the puzzles in Elixir, which is a newer language that I am starting to use at work. The creator of Elixir, José Valim, was solving the puzzles as well and &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.plataformatec.com.br/2018/11/lets-learn-elixir-together-with-advent-of-code/&#34;&gt;live streaming his solutions&lt;/a&gt;. Other Elixir experts were also publishing solutions, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sasa1977/aoc&#34;&gt;Saša Jurić&lt;/a&gt;. This was so cool! A fabulous way to learn a new language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints I only attempted about half of the puzzles with my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chad-g-adams/advent-of-code-2018&#34;&gt;solutions posted here&lt;/a&gt;. I was hoping to go back and finish the rest of the puzzles but that hasn&amp;rsquo;t happened so I&amp;rsquo;m wrapping this up with a blog post now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;commentary:0647481dad1b7f4b21d4a5bad3077cd7&#34;&gt;Commentary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partway through I realized it would be helpful to myself to capture personal insights for each solution, so I left some commentary in the code solutions themselves which I am reproducing here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;

&lt;td style=&#34;width: 20%&#34;&gt;
Day 5 
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
    For this solution, I found that converting each individual character to a String for purpose of doing downcase() 
    was performance impacting (total 30 seconds to solve puzzle). So I switched to using assumption
    that input was only ascii letters (and added a validation check to ensure this assumption holds). 
    Thus I could compare upper/lower case by adding 32 to the value instead of converting to string. Solution runs 15x faster.
    &lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 6
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
The performance of my solution is lacking, it took 30 seconds to solve Part 1 on my laptop.
Part 2 solution was even worse - 2 min 26 s.
If I had more time I would go back and optimize!
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 7
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;sub&gt;
    First part was OK, second part took a long time to solve.
    First puzzle where my code worked for the test data but didn&#39;t work for the full solution.
    (Turned out I read the challenge wrong.. was using wrong number of workers).
    Passing a lot of parameters around. Might be easier to pass state around as a
    single map structure than as individual parameters.
    
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
 Day 8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Got bitten by elixir when doing efficient building a list by appending to the start
    but then forgetting to reverse list at the end (when order became important)!
    This caused some grief. I could have noticed this error sooner if I ran the tests more frequently
    during development.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Nice to use Stream.unfold for the first time, also learned how to sleep in elixir.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
    Things I learned today, you can do pattern matching in anonymous functions!
    Part 1 was solved in a straightforward, albeit not great performance way.
    Part 2 The non-performant solution was no longer reasonable. I tried a few
     optimizations but couldn&#39;t make it fast enough. Then I found this hint:
     https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summed-area_table
     but by that point it was the end of the night and I didn&#39;t feel like implementing it.

&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Day 18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;sub&gt;
  Felt really good about solving this one, my growing familiarity with the elixir
  modules is starting to pay off. Assist to my wife for talking through Part 2 strategy with me.
  
&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up Visual Studio Code for Elixir</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/12/31/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-elixir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 13:50:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/12/31/setting-up-visual-studio-code-for-elixir/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Elixir is a programming language that I am in the process of learning, and which I use at work. This post documents the settings I am using to develop in elixir using the VSCode editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-language-support:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;1. Language Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install extension &lt;code&gt;ElixirLS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the box this gives you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;autocomplete, navigation, dialyzer (aka static analysis/linting) and debugging capabilities. Hooray!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-formatting:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;2. Formatting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elixir is an auto-formatted language for &lt;a href=&#34;https://hashrocket.com/blog/posts/format-your-elixir-code-now&#34;&gt;reasons&lt;/a&gt;, hence &lt;code&gt;mix format&lt;/code&gt; is your friend. In your VSCode Settings, hit the checkbox for &amp;ldquo;Editor: Format on Save&amp;rdquo; to run this on every save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-test-execution:59fcf391e193ccd025a67f034b3ef13d&#34;&gt;3. Test Execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commonly run tests three different ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a single test. Most frequently used while developing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the tests. Used for regression testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run all the tests from a single file. Sometimes useful while developing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set these up as Tasks in your tasks.json as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      }
  },
  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;single test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test ${relativeFile}:${lineNumber}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      },
      &amp;quot;runOptions&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;reevaluateOnRerun&amp;quot;: false
      }
  },
  {
      &amp;quot;label&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test current file&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shell&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test ${relativeFile}&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;group&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;presentation&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;echo&amp;quot;: true,
          &amp;quot;reveal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;focus&amp;quot;: false,
          &amp;quot;panel&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;shared&amp;quot;,
          &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot;: true
      },
      &amp;quot;runOptions&amp;quot;: {
          &amp;quot;reevaluateOnRerun&amp;quot;: false
      }
  }

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also create hotkeys to launch your tests. I do it like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[
   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl-s&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;mix test&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+s&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;single test&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;when&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;editorTextFocus&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+w&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.runTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;args&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;test current file&amp;quot;
   },

   {
       &amp;quot;key&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;ctrl+shift+r&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;command&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;workbench.action.tasks.reRunTask&amp;quot;,
       &amp;quot;when&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;editorTextFocus&amp;quot;
   }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s super easy to run a single test, or all the tests, on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use in combination with the standard &amp;ldquo;Rerun Last Task&amp;rdquo; (new in vscode 1.30) to run your single test over and over again without having to switch windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With credit to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pragdave.me/blog/2018/06/13/visual-studio-code-elixir-tests.html&#34;&gt;https://pragdave.me/blog/2018/06/13/visual-studio-code-elixir-tests.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Way of the Peaceful Warrior</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 15:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This month I read  &lt;em&gt;Way of the Peaceful Warrior&lt;/em&gt; by Dan Millman. In short, it is a story about how to live your best life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because I had pre-internalized several of these ideas already from my own lived experience, I found the first half a slow and painful slog (also because I kind of loathed the main character, but that was mostly by design). It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until around page 100 that I settled in and felt like I was getting something out of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those insights is a way of looking at emotions. Here I pulled three separate quotes from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to control emotion &amp;hellip; The key is to transform the energy of emotion into constructive action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger is a powerful tool to transform old habits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear and sorrow inhibit action; anger generates it. When you learn to make proper use of your anger, you can change fear and sorrow to anger, then turn anger to action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is to use your emotions with intention. Take a moment to acknowledge the emotion, then turn around and use it for whatever help it can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another insight is that action is the way of the warrior. Knowledge and meditation only go so far. Turning your knowledge into action is what counts. This is a good reminder for me, that a quiet life of learning is entirely insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some more nuggets of wisdom from the book that I am recording here so that I can come back to later from time to time to remind myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any unconscious, compulsive ritual is a problem.&lt;/em&gt; [&amp;hellip;] &lt;em&gt;Responsibility means recognizing both pleasure and price, action and consequence, then making a choice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My actions are conscious, spontaneous, intentional, and complete.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t live according to anyone&amp;rsquo;s expectations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are no ordinary moments&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extend razor-sharp attention to every moment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The mind stores tension in the body. Worries, anxieties, and other mental debris are stored as chronic tension&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meditating an action is different from doing it. To do, there is a doer, a self-conscious &amp;lsquo;someone&amp;rsquo; performing. But when you meditate an action, you&amp;rsquo;ve released attachment to outcomes. There&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;lsquo;you&amp;rsquo; left to do it. In forgetting yourself, you become what you do, so your action is free, spontaneous, without ambition, inhibition, or fear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The secret of happiness, you see, is not found in seeking more, but in developing the capacity to enjoy less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find the book a roundabout way of sharing this wisdom. Having to slog through the experience of Danny is, I guess, one example for readers to work with. But I found so many more examples in my own lived experience to relate to that I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to be guided this way. And there was a strange side-story about a woman named Joy which became a weird metaphor that felt awkward and unnecessary. As such, I felt the presentation of these ideas overall did not resonate well for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However one thing I did like was how these ideas were presented without any religious context. I have a vague sense that many of them could be compatible with Taoist ideas, however not being very well-versed in that domain myself I cannot comment much further (it does remind me that I am overdue to read a different book involving Taoism that my sister gave me: &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Names for Joy&lt;/em&gt;). On his Q&amp;amp;A webpage, Millman states that many readers have found religious teachings in his work but that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t subscribe &amp;ldquo;to any other philosophical stool, but to simple humanity&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite part of the book is the challenge to the reader to &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;be unreasonably happy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. I do believe happiness is a choice, so this resonates with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feelings change &amp;hellip; Sometimes sorrow, sometimes joy. But beneath it all remember the innate perfection of your life unfolding. That is the secret of unreasonable happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a master at anything, and there are always ways to improve, but this is one lesson, at least, worth taking to heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three sequels were written to this book, including one that come out just last year (&lt;em&gt;The Hidden School&lt;/em&gt;). I don&amp;rsquo;t feel the urge to read further, but if anyone else has then I&amp;rsquo;m interested to hear what you thought about them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>