<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Indigenous on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/indigenous/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Indigenous on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 09:48:55 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/indigenous/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: 2019</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 09:48:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A year&amp;rsquo;s worth of reading and no book blog posts? Well, better late than never! In addition to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/&#34;&gt;new parent selections&lt;/a&gt;, here are a few of the books I read this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;team-human:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Team Human&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Douglas Rushkoff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/teamHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Team Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt; is a podcast and now a book which I read around the time of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/&#34;&gt;his visit to the Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s well worth a read and captures the main thesis that even more technology won&amp;rsquo;t solve our problems so long as we keep treating problems as unconnected; but as humans we&amp;rsquo;re fully equipped to form communities and launch a modern renaissance that respects humanity - if only we would recognize and choose to do so. Probably the most important book of 2019, in my opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lana-and-lilly-wachowski:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cáel M. Keegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wachowskis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dense academic book within a series on &lt;em&gt;Contemporary Film Directors&lt;/em&gt;, this text looks at the Wachowskis oeuvre through a trans* lens, giving a whole new meaning to &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, one of my favourite movies. It also leads an insightful reading into &lt;em&gt;Sense8&lt;/em&gt;, probably my favourite TV show in recent memory. This book introduced me to &lt;em&gt;Bound&lt;/em&gt;, the Wachowskis&amp;rsquo; first major film, which is excellent and worth watching if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book is a simply terrific interview with Lana Wachowski.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;] A lot of your work seems to be very concerned with the idea of moving through space and time differently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s an opposing narrative. The dominant cultural narrative is that things are static. There&amp;rsquo;s a foundational myth about America, about identity, about heteronormativity. [&amp;hellip;] &amp;ldquo;This is the way it is.&amp;rdquo; This is even the concept of normalcy. Normalcy is non-moving. It&amp;rsquo;s a fixed idea. All of my narratives are an assault against this idea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;Would you describe yourself as utopian, then?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;Obviously I would resist any label&amp;hellip;but I think the making of art is inherently optimistic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-doesn-t-have-to-be-crazy-at-work:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;It Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/itDoesntHaveToBeCrazyAtWork.png&#34; alt=&#34;It Doesn&#39;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manual for setting a &lt;em&gt;calm&lt;/em&gt; work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s constantly crazy at work, we have two words for you: Fuck that. And two more: Enough already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of it all is an unhealthy obsession with rapid growth. Towering, unrealistic expectations drag people down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time for companies to stop asking their employees to breathlessly chase ever-higher, ever-more artificial targets set by ego, not need. It’s time to stop celebrating this way of working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few topics that really resonated with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FOMO? JOMO!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People should be missing out. Most people should be missing out on most things most of the time. [&amp;hellip;] JOMO! The joy of missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be a knee-jerk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person making the pitch has presumably put a lot of time, thought, and energy into gathering their thoughts and presenting them clearly to an audience. But the rest of the people in the room are asked to react. Not absorb, not think it over, not consider - just react. Knee-jerk it. That&amp;rsquo;s no way to treat fragile new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t want reactions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want first impressions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want knee-jerks. We want considered feedback. Read it over. Read it twice, three times even. Sleep on it. Take your time to gather and present your thoughts - just like the person who pitched the original idea took their time to gather and present theirs. That&amp;rsquo;s how you go deep on an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All subject matter experts at Basecamp now publish office hours. [&amp;hellip;] This might seem inefficient at first glance. Bureaucratic, even. But we&amp;rsquo;ve seen otherwise. Office hours have been a big hit at Basecamp. It turns out that waiting is no big deal most of the time. But the time and control regained by our experts is a huge deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your company is a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company is like software. It has to be usable, it has to be useful. And it probably also has bugs, places where the company crashes because of bad organizational design or cultural oversights. When you start to think of your company as a product, all sorts of new possibilities for improvement emerge. When you realize the way you work is malleable, you can start molding something new, something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;prediction-machines:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ajay Agrawal, Joshua Gans, Avi Goldfarb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/predictionMachines.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prediction Machines&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by three economists, &lt;em&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/em&gt; takes the &amp;ldquo;mystery&amp;rdquo; out of AI by re-casting it within an economic framework and simply treating it as cheaper prediction, and then following the consequences of seeing it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t love this book but I don&amp;rsquo;t have much argument with the premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-after-the-end:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Love After the End&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2019)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/loveAfterTheEnd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Love After the End&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sci-fi anthology of short stories about Two-Spirit utopias and dystopias, a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you survive a perfect world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, how do you grow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an imperfect world, how do you resist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]
Imagine the future of our people after the end of colonization. Read stories of survival and love lost and found, across all bodies and genders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered this book through a Kickstarter campaign. The introduction by Joshua Whitehead was a beautiful way to set the context for the reader (probably my favourite part of the book actually, which is not taking anything away from the stories but more a statement on how great of an introduction it was).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite stories were Darcie Little Badger&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Story for a Bottle&lt;/em&gt;, jaye simpson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Ark of the Turtle&amp;rsquo;s Back&lt;/em&gt;, and Adam Garnet Jones&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;The New World&lt;/em&gt;. Highly recommend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;permanent-record:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Permanent Record&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/permanentRecord.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Permanent Record&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am halfway through reading Snowden&amp;rsquo;s autobiography. It&amp;rsquo;s a great read thus far, but I&amp;rsquo;m only just getting to the famous parts of his story. When you know the ending, it&amp;rsquo;s tempting to look back and pick out only the events that supported the outcome (which is of course a common bias). I feel as though that&amp;rsquo;s what Snowden has done with his memoir when describing his early days; probably a more rounded story would be a bit more nuanced, but hey he&amp;rsquo;s writing for an audience after all. And it&amp;rsquo;s all very interesting stuff. Looking forward to the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;democracy-may-not-exist-but-we-ll-miss-it-when-it-s-gone:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Democracy May Not Exist But We&amp;rsquo;ll Miss It When It&amp;rsquo;s Gone&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Astra Taylor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/democracyMayNotExist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Democracy May Not Exist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m only a few chapters into this one and I need to re-request it from the library again to finish it. This is an eye-opening book about how the public doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a good idea of what democracy is (although we think we do) and how it&amp;rsquo;s really more about straight up conflicting principles (eg. equality versus freedom) and how the tensions between these principles are perpetually at play and continuously needing resolution through community. Put in another form: democracy is more of a verb than a noun. I discovered this book through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-130-astra-taylor-democracy-is-a-verb/&#34;&gt;Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m really looking forward to completing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: My Conversations With Canadians</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 16:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/MyConversationsWithCanadians.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My Conversations With Canadians&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Conversations With Canadians&lt;/em&gt; by Lee Maracle is a thoughtful journey across many topics central to Canada-Indigenous relations (or to use Maracle&amp;rsquo;s suggested term: Canada-&lt;em&gt;Turtle Islander&lt;/em&gt; relations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; this book. It was super approachable and a great education for a non-Turtle Islander like myself, challenging many preconceived ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle recounts conversations she has shared with Canadians ranging in time from the 1970s to the present. She will often linger over questions posed to her by non-Indigenous Canadians, turning the question around for the reader and instead exploring the biases of the questioner - what assumptions do they already have in place, in order to even ask that question? Really eye-opening and I enjoyed this style thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many questions, I also enjoyed how she would confess to the reader how she really wanted to reply, then share what she actually responded with. I admire her grace in what must have been some astonishingly ignorant or rude questions! (And I confess to being one of those ignorant people myself who might be heading along those same lines)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I have come to through all of these experiences is that Canadians don&amp;rsquo;t know much about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education is a cultural process and, of course, the education citizens receive in Canada is all about British contact with Indigenous people and the development and maintenance of Canada. No one studies what was here before in any serious way. It is as though the 150-year history of Canada is far more significant than the 15,000 years previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a sobering thought and so very true. I certainly did not retain much in the way of Indigenous history or knowledge from my Canadian education. That probably means there are at least a generation of people, if not more, who likely have no clue, really (other than stereotypes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle does a good job of imparting the full richness of Turtle Islander culture to her readers, a culture dismissed by settlers, but nevertheless whose influence can be seen on today&amp;rsquo;s world (although that goes unacknowledged).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s humbling to think of all the things we missed learning about in school. What a curriculum it would have made!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was brought up in story. No one disciplined me by spanking or scoldings; rather the old people watching me told a story and I was expected to figure out my behavioural issues from the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I was raised on story, I brought my children up on story. We work with story. We begin with an old tale and, as we progress through the story, we tell it back different but the same, changing it so it becomes a modern new story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle also makes clear that being nice people doesn&amp;rsquo;t give Canadians a pass; she drives home that we are all actively complicit in the genocide of Turtle Islanders, quoting articles from the UN Genocide Convention to support her case. Ignorance may be bliss for some, but morally that stance just doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold up. We have a responsibility to educate ourselves on affairs that are being conducted in our name. It&amp;rsquo;s time for Canadians to get with it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase a statement in the book: de-colonization is not about how the Indigenous world fits into ours, but how we fit into theirs. With this in mind, I sample from Chapter 12 which describes the Turtle Islander belief system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humility is critical to recognizing and examining our failures, our mistakes, our contribution to broken relations [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage gives us the determination to overcome our fear of self-examination, of admitting to our neglect. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honesty teaches us to own our self&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the above be a guide to us Canadians as we reach to build true relations with Turtle Islanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would urge all non-Indigenous folk to pick up this book and see Canada differently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Wrist</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 18:48:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/24/book-review-wrist/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wrist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrist-by-nathan-niigan-noodin-adler:be8d3886104ef6a4ba40f052b87ecea4&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; by Nathan Niigan Noodin Adler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt; is an Anishinaabe-inspired horror story that I picked up at the Ottawa &lt;em&gt;Writersfest&lt;/em&gt; last year. One of the fun things about this book is that you&amp;rsquo;re never totally certain if the monsters are real. Adler keeps you guessing about whether this is playing out in the imagination of Church, the protagonist, even going so far as to include other characters who themselves don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the monsters. As Adler states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I]t will still devour you, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t believe.
Things that are real don&amp;rsquo;t need you to believe in them, they&amp;rsquo;ll consume you just the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we learn that Church is the son of a Residential school survivor on one side, and a Holocaust survivor on the other, we begin to recognize that perhaps the true horror story being told is the evil of intergenerational trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it was just a delusion [&amp;hellip;], it was real in every sense that mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about this book is that it&amp;rsquo;s not over-edited, so the voice of the author shines through unobscured, almost as though he&amp;rsquo;s reading aloud to you in the oral tradition of the First Nations. In fact, he provides substantial Anishinaabemowin dialog and terminology throughout the book, giving mild language lessons to his readers. I enjoyed reading the Anishinaabek words aloud softly as I went along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique aspect is the scientific emphasis throughout the story. Adler firmly places Indigenous lore within a natural, scientific world, for example beautifully comparing the hunger of the wiindigo to a black hole. Not only does this make the book feel real, almost alive, in a living, breathing kind of way, but also serves as a nice counterpoint to how colonialist society tends to portray Indigenous culture as cliché and static (&lt;em&gt;The Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt;*). Here we are given very much the opposite of that, with a cultural viewpoint that follows along with our evolving understanding of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunger is the central theme in this story, and Adler invites us to consider hunger as something abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we are driven to eat to fill other hungers that can&amp;rsquo;t be filled with food&amp;hellip;Loneliness, sadness, trauma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading this book during a period of personal grief, had me relating to this. Even though hunger is pain, hunger should not be indulged too deeply, but neither should it be ignored. Excess in either direction will turn one into a monster. That is the warning delivered in &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;. However hunger is also what makes us who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Church is not always sure exactly who he is supposed to be, yet he&amp;rsquo;s proof that one can derive tremendous power and self-worth out of personal beliefs and life experiences, even if many of those are hard experiences. And proof that nobody should be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;wrist&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is given in a preface to the book, with a secondary definition being &lt;em&gt;sleight-of-hand&lt;/em&gt;. So what sleight-of-hand is the author pulling with this novel &lt;em&gt;Wrist&lt;/em&gt;?  For me, it was filling my spirit with nature, language and appreciation for all that life has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a unique and very original book with many layers to unpack. I look forward to reading more of Adler&amp;rsquo;s work in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Dead Indian&lt;/em&gt; per Thomas King&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Inconvenient Indian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wristTwitter.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>