<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 17:57:57 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book: 24/6 The Power of Unplugging One Day a Week</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-24/6-the-power-of-unplugging-one-day-a-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 17:57:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-24/6-the-power-of-unplugging-one-day-a-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/24-6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;24/6&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;24 / 6&lt;/em&gt; Tiffany Shlain proposes an antidote to the burdens of the modern world with a &amp;ldquo;Tech Shabbat&amp;rdquo;, a one-day reprieve from screens of all kind. Rather than define it using a negative, Shlain focuses on the positive by promoting it as a day to do all the things you always wished you had time for. I believe many of us dream of such a possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about this idea from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-139-tiffany-shlain-unplugging-one-day-a-week-tribute-to-paul-krassner&#34;&gt;Shlain&amp;rsquo;s interview on the Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt; and was immediately excited about it. At the time of writing, I have completed my first Tech Shabbat with my family, and we&amp;rsquo;re very happy with how it went. We lit a candle to emphasize the transition. Going to bed early, fancy breakfast, listening to music, reading, thinking, having long conversations, spending time outdoors, napping&amp;hellip; it was glorious. I agree with Shlain when she says her Shabbat always feels longer than one day, it did for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the book is concerned, I was underwhelmed. I did find it useful to be shown specific examples of what Shabbat could entail, and I appreciated the emphasis on everyone defining their own rules and traditions in a way that works for them. Otherwise I found the book repetitive and the science chapters were not rigorous enough for my liking. In other parts I was finding it too autobiographical, I was not interested in the details&amp;hellip; but then I realized that was actually the whole point of Shabbat! Shlain sees the Tech Shabbat as a technology, a tool that extends her purpose into the world and so it&amp;rsquo;s quite impossible for her to talk about her Shabbat without also getting into her own goals and activities. And this insight turns it back onto the reader to decide (which I will do the same to you, dear reader):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your purpose? What are the things you always wished you had time for?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book: Perihelion Summer</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-perihelion-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 13:38:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-perihelion-summer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/perihelionSummer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Perihelion Summer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of &lt;em&gt;Perhihelion Summer&lt;/em&gt; by Greg Egan involves the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit shifting slightly, resulting in an instant climate crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ensuing desperation reminds me of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seveneves&#34;&gt;Seveneves&lt;/a&gt;, another novel dealing with an emergency of astronomical proportions. I love survival stories like these where forward-thinking actors manage to design and execute on an improbable pathway out of doom, and then seeing how existence turns almost exclusively into resourcefulness, and the managing of equipment and knowledge against the perils of time, nature, and human conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it exciting to have this story centered on Australia. In a universe where the Northern hemisphere is again privileged, the author places a fully-developed nation and its citizens in the exact same boat as other climate refugees, giving a direct taste of the crisis to those of us (such as us Canadians), who might otherwise believe ourselves to be insulated from the coming effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the ensuing denial (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we can manage&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; / &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we have a year&amp;rsquo;s worth of food in the freezer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;) and the government response (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;more insulation on your house&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;security drones&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;) are a nod to our current times, our inaction, distrust, and feeble measures in the face of the coming threat. By designing the world such that climate change is already visible and strikingly in effect for all to see, it lends the portrayed denials a much more ridiculous air, exposing the folly of these various courses of action quite vividly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accelerating the crisis, and giving a glimpse of the refugee experience, this book turns a mirror on our own responsibility to act in the climate crisis. Hopefully these lessons can help us better empathize with each other and act with the urgency that is required.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap 2020</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/12/27/book-recap-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 12:23:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2020/12/27/book-recap-2020/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;2020 was a little lighter on reading as I delved a bit more into podcasts and movies, but I did get to some good ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;little-failure:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Little Failure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gary Shteyngart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/littleFailure.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Little Failure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first half was a pretty wild account of growing up in the USSR and lower-class New York, told with a dry humour, the kind I like best! The second half (college onwards) felt more scattered and didn&amp;rsquo;t resonate with me, perhaps I was lacking some cultural context around American colleges and politics, but I lost interest. He mentioned at one point this was his &amp;ldquo;first memoir&amp;rdquo; and I wonder if it might be revisited in a later text to greater effect. Even so, I would be unlikely to pick it up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;jonny-appleseed:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Jonny Appleseed&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joshua Whitehead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/jonnyAppleseed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jonny Appleseed&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book comes at you hard with the sexuality, but after the initial double-take it settles into you with its earnest and honest narration. A window into rez culture and queerness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;an-absolutely-remarkable-thing:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;An Absolutely Remarkable Thing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hank Green&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/anAbsolutelyRemarkableThing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An Absolutely Remarkable Thing&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-beautifully-foolish-endeavor:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;A Beautifully Foolish Endeavor&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hank Green&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/aBeautifullyFoolishEndeavor.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Beautifully Foolish Endeavor&#34; /&gt;
Notes coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;antifragile:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Antifragile&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nassim Nicholas Taleb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/antifragile.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Antifragile&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes coming soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-only-good-indians:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;The Only Good Indians&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stephen Graham Jones&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/onlyGoodIndians.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Only Good Indians&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment partway through this book that had you really questioning everything you thought you knew, and I was really excited to continue along that train of thought. But the mystery was kind of taken away as the story continued on and that made me sad but nevertheless I still enjoyed the rest of the book and would recommend it. Indigenous-authored horror stories are becoming a new favourite for me. The echoes of intergenerational trauma, and hinting at breaking the cycle and new possibilities/hope, are powerful themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;empire-of-wild:54f6d87bf91ea0ebe2c4754c99771b41&#34;&gt;Empire of Wild&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cherie Dimaline&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/empireOfWild.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Empire of Wild&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A horror/thriller that had me laughing out loud within the first couple chapters. Loved the little references to Canada and the phoniness of reconciliation. A story that challenges Western norms by blurring family units, reinforcing wisdom of elders and story. Deals directly with themes of Western entrapment and dispossession; the reverend as the wolf in sheepskin, a vessel to be used for colonization. There is a strong message about not giving up through hardship, even when defeat appears foregone and inevitable, which is a message that is extremely relevant today - because nothing is truly inevitable. And also: don&amp;rsquo;t forget how to treat your relations or you&amp;rsquo;ll turn into a monster :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: 2019</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 09:48:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/12/31/book-recap-2019/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A year&amp;rsquo;s worth of reading and no book blog posts? Well, better late than never! In addition to my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/10/24/resources-for-new-parents/&#34;&gt;new parent selections&lt;/a&gt;, here are a few of the books I read this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;team-human:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Team Human&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Douglas Rushkoff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/teamHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Team Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Human&lt;/em&gt; is a podcast and now a book which I read around the time of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/05/11/douglas-rushkoff-at-writersfest/&#34;&gt;his visit to the Ottawa Writersfest&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s well worth a read and captures the main thesis that even more technology won&amp;rsquo;t solve our problems so long as we keep treating problems as unconnected; but as humans we&amp;rsquo;re fully equipped to form communities and launch a modern renaissance that respects humanity - if only we would recognize and choose to do so. Probably the most important book of 2019, in my opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lana-and-lilly-wachowski:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cáel M. Keegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/wachowskis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lana and Lilly Wachowski&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dense academic book within a series on &lt;em&gt;Contemporary Film Directors&lt;/em&gt;, this text looks at the Wachowskis oeuvre through a trans* lens, giving a whole new meaning to &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, one of my favourite movies. It also leads an insightful reading into &lt;em&gt;Sense8&lt;/em&gt;, probably my favourite TV show in recent memory. This book introduced me to &lt;em&gt;Bound&lt;/em&gt;, the Wachowskis&amp;rsquo; first major film, which is excellent and worth watching if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book is a simply terrific interview with Lana Wachowski.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;] A lot of your work seems to be very concerned with the idea of moving through space and time differently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s an opposing narrative. The dominant cultural narrative is that things are static. There&amp;rsquo;s a foundational myth about America, about identity, about heteronormativity. [&amp;hellip;] &amp;ldquo;This is the way it is.&amp;rdquo; This is even the concept of normalcy. Normalcy is non-moving. It&amp;rsquo;s a fixed idea. All of my narratives are an assault against this idea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMK: &amp;ldquo;Would you describe yourself as utopian, then?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lana Wachowski: &amp;ldquo;Obviously I would resist any label&amp;hellip;but I think the making of art is inherently optimistic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-doesn-t-have-to-be-crazy-at-work:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;It Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/itDoesntHaveToBeCrazyAtWork.png&#34; alt=&#34;It Doesn&#39;t Have to Be Crazy at Work&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manual for setting a &lt;em&gt;calm&lt;/em&gt; work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s constantly crazy at work, we have two words for you: Fuck that. And two more: Enough already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of it all is an unhealthy obsession with rapid growth. Towering, unrealistic expectations drag people down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time for companies to stop asking their employees to breathlessly chase ever-higher, ever-more artificial targets set by ego, not need. It’s time to stop celebrating this way of working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few topics that really resonated with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FOMO? JOMO!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People should be missing out. Most people should be missing out on most things most of the time. [&amp;hellip;] JOMO! The joy of missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be a knee-jerk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person making the pitch has presumably put a lot of time, thought, and energy into gathering their thoughts and presenting them clearly to an audience. But the rest of the people in the room are asked to react. Not absorb, not think it over, not consider - just react. Knee-jerk it. That&amp;rsquo;s no way to treat fragile new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t want reactions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want first impressions. We don&amp;rsquo;t want knee-jerks. We want considered feedback. Read it over. Read it twice, three times even. Sleep on it. Take your time to gather and present your thoughts - just like the person who pitched the original idea took their time to gather and present theirs. That&amp;rsquo;s how you go deep on an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All subject matter experts at Basecamp now publish office hours. [&amp;hellip;] This might seem inefficient at first glance. Bureaucratic, even. But we&amp;rsquo;ve seen otherwise. Office hours have been a big hit at Basecamp. It turns out that waiting is no big deal most of the time. But the time and control regained by our experts is a huge deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your company is a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company is like software. It has to be usable, it has to be useful. And it probably also has bugs, places where the company crashes because of bad organizational design or cultural oversights. When you start to think of your company as a product, all sorts of new possibilities for improvement emerge. When you realize the way you work is malleable, you can start molding something new, something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;prediction-machines:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ajay Agrawal, Joshua Gans, Avi Goldfarb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/predictionMachines.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prediction Machines&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by three economists, &lt;em&gt;Prediction Machines&lt;/em&gt; takes the &amp;ldquo;mystery&amp;rdquo; out of AI by re-casting it within an economic framework and simply treating it as cheaper prediction, and then following the consequences of seeing it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t love this book but I don&amp;rsquo;t have much argument with the premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-after-the-end:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Love After the End&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2019)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/loveAfterTheEnd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Love After the End&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sci-fi anthology of short stories about Two-Spirit utopias and dystopias, a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you survive a perfect world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, how do you grow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an imperfect world, how do you resist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]
Imagine the future of our people after the end of colonization. Read stories of survival and love lost and found, across all bodies and genders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered this book through a Kickstarter campaign. The introduction by Joshua Whitehead was a beautiful way to set the context for the reader (probably my favourite part of the book actually, which is not taking anything away from the stories but more a statement on how great of an introduction it was).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite stories were Darcie Little Badger&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Story for a Bottle&lt;/em&gt;, jaye simpson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Ark of the Turtle&amp;rsquo;s Back&lt;/em&gt;, and Adam Garnet Jones&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;The New World&lt;/em&gt;. Highly recommend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;permanent-record:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Permanent Record&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/permanentRecord.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Permanent Record&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am halfway through reading Snowden&amp;rsquo;s autobiography. It&amp;rsquo;s a great read thus far, but I&amp;rsquo;m only just getting to the famous parts of his story. When you know the ending, it&amp;rsquo;s tempting to look back and pick out only the events that supported the outcome (which is of course a common bias). I feel as though that&amp;rsquo;s what Snowden has done with his memoir when describing his early days; probably a more rounded story would be a bit more nuanced, but hey he&amp;rsquo;s writing for an audience after all. And it&amp;rsquo;s all very interesting stuff. Looking forward to the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;democracy-may-not-exist-but-we-ll-miss-it-when-it-s-gone:be6ccc2544e6f56c8500ac258c32c4c1&#34;&gt;Democracy May Not Exist But We&amp;rsquo;ll Miss It When It&amp;rsquo;s Gone&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Astra Taylor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/democracyMayNotExist.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Democracy May Not Exist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m only a few chapters into this one and I need to re-request it from the library again to finish it. This is an eye-opening book about how the public doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a good idea of what democracy is (although we think we do) and how it&amp;rsquo;s really more about straight up conflicting principles (eg. equality versus freedom) and how the tensions between these principles are perpetually at play and continuously needing resolution through community. Put in another form: democracy is more of a verb than a noun. I discovered this book through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-130-astra-taylor-democracy-is-a-verb/&#34;&gt;Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m really looking forward to completing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Way of the Peaceful Warrior</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 15:17:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/09/03/book-review-way-of-the-peaceful-warrior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This month I read  &lt;em&gt;Way of the Peaceful Warrior&lt;/em&gt; by Dan Millman. In short, it is a story about how to live your best life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because I had pre-internalized several of these ideas already from my own lived experience, I found the first half a slow and painful slog (also because I kind of loathed the main character, but that was mostly by design). It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until around page 100 that I settled in and felt like I was getting something out of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those insights is a way of looking at emotions. Here I pulled three separate quotes from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to control emotion &amp;hellip; The key is to transform the energy of emotion into constructive action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger is a powerful tool to transform old habits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear and sorrow inhibit action; anger generates it. When you learn to make proper use of your anger, you can change fear and sorrow to anger, then turn anger to action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is to use your emotions with intention. Take a moment to acknowledge the emotion, then turn around and use it for whatever help it can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another insight is that action is the way of the warrior. Knowledge and meditation only go so far. Turning your knowledge into action is what counts. This is a good reminder for me, that a quiet life of learning is entirely insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some more nuggets of wisdom from the book that I am recording here so that I can come back to later from time to time to remind myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any unconscious, compulsive ritual is a problem.&lt;/em&gt; [&amp;hellip;] &lt;em&gt;Responsibility means recognizing both pleasure and price, action and consequence, then making a choice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My actions are conscious, spontaneous, intentional, and complete.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t live according to anyone&amp;rsquo;s expectations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are no ordinary moments&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extend razor-sharp attention to every moment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The mind stores tension in the body. Worries, anxieties, and other mental debris are stored as chronic tension&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Meditating an action is different from doing it. To do, there is a doer, a self-conscious &amp;lsquo;someone&amp;rsquo; performing. But when you meditate an action, you&amp;rsquo;ve released attachment to outcomes. There&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;lsquo;you&amp;rsquo; left to do it. In forgetting yourself, you become what you do, so your action is free, spontaneous, without ambition, inhibition, or fear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The secret of happiness, you see, is not found in seeking more, but in developing the capacity to enjoy less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find the book a roundabout way of sharing this wisdom. Having to slog through the experience of Danny is, I guess, one example for readers to work with. But I found so many more examples in my own lived experience to relate to that I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to be guided this way. And there was a strange side-story about a woman named Joy which became a weird metaphor that felt awkward and unnecessary. As such, I felt the presentation of these ideas overall did not resonate well for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However one thing I did like was how these ideas were presented without any religious context. I have a vague sense that many of them could be compatible with Taoist ideas, however not being very well-versed in that domain myself I cannot comment much further (it does remind me that I am overdue to read a different book involving Taoism that my sister gave me: &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Names for Joy&lt;/em&gt;). On his Q&amp;amp;A webpage, Millman states that many readers have found religious teachings in his work but that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t subscribe &amp;ldquo;to any other philosophical stool, but to simple humanity&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite part of the book is the challenge to the reader to &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;be unreasonably happy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. I do believe happiness is a choice, so this resonates with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feelings change &amp;hellip; Sometimes sorrow, sometimes joy. But beneath it all remember the innate perfection of your life unfolding. That is the secret of unreasonable happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to be a master at anything, and there are always ways to improve, but this is one lesson, at least, worth taking to heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three sequels were written to this book, including one that come out just last year (&lt;em&gt;The Hidden School&lt;/em&gt;). I don&amp;rsquo;t feel the urge to read further, but if anyone else has then I&amp;rsquo;m interested to hear what you thought about them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recap: Spring/Summer 2018</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 20:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/08/15/book-recap-spring/summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It has been a busy time but I am still reading! Here is a quick recap of memorable books finished in Spring and Summer 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/books2018.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Books in 2018&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;49th-parallels:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;49th Parallels&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published during Canada&amp;rsquo;s 150-year celebration, a compilation of short stories and alternative histories involving Canada and our place in the world. Example: what if Canada had been first to develop the atomic bomb? I supported this publication through crowdfunding, and am quite pleased with the result: uniquely Canadian! Re-imagining our story helps answer questions about who we are and who we could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;love-beyond-body-space-time:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Love Beyond Body, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Various authors (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Indigenous LGBT sci-fi short story compilation. It&amp;rsquo;s a rare intersection to find in one publication and worth checking out for that alone. In particular I really enjoyed Cherie Dimaline&amp;rsquo;s and Nathan Adler&amp;rsquo;s stories and still find myself thinking about them from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-marrow-thieves:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;The Marrow Thieves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cherie Dimaline (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A genius premise. Brings Indigenous history and culture to the forefront. Very well done! I only wish Rose was a more interesting character&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;legacy-of-heorot:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Legacy of Heorot&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Larry Niven, Jerry Pournelle, Steven Barnes (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;200 pioneers arrive to colonize a new planet, but things start to go wrong. I remember enjoying this one as a teenager so thought I&amp;rsquo;d see how it holds up today. Reads like an 80s action movie. Still love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;watch:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;Watch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert Sawyer (2010)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion about the origin and implications of consciousness, told through an array of interesting characters such as an ape, an emergent AI, a blind teenager who has regained her sight, and an autistic man. Optimistic take on what technology might do for humanity, we need more like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-reconciliation-manifesto:aa17d3187dfd5d55db643c6ead0a7b7f&#34;&gt;The Reconciliation Manifesto&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Arthur Manuel (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A straight-forward overview of the legal situation of Indigenous nations in Canada: how we arrived in this situation, and where to go next. The three phases of colonialism: dispossession, dependency, oppression. Manuel argues that pressing for progress in international forums will be more effective than any resolutions being proposed by Canada which are more about extinguishment of Indigenous land title than about rights. Grassroots involvement will be necessary as so-called indigenous &amp;ldquo;leaders&amp;rdquo; have been compromised due to the systemic nature of dependency on government funds. It makes me angry to realize the extent of how Canada is an abuser of human rights. We need more people to understand this now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: My Conversations With Canadians</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 16:24:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2018/02/26/book-review-my-conversations-with-canadians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/MyConversationsWithCanadians.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My Conversations With Canadians&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Conversations With Canadians&lt;/em&gt; by Lee Maracle is a thoughtful journey across many topics central to Canada-Indigenous relations (or to use Maracle&amp;rsquo;s suggested term: Canada-&lt;em&gt;Turtle Islander&lt;/em&gt; relations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; this book. It was super approachable and a great education for a non-Turtle Islander like myself, challenging many preconceived ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle recounts conversations she has shared with Canadians ranging in time from the 1970s to the present. She will often linger over questions posed to her by non-Indigenous Canadians, turning the question around for the reader and instead exploring the biases of the questioner - what assumptions do they already have in place, in order to even ask that question? Really eye-opening and I enjoyed this style thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many questions, I also enjoyed how she would confess to the reader how she really wanted to reply, then share what she actually responded with. I admire her grace in what must have been some astonishingly ignorant or rude questions! (And I confess to being one of those ignorant people myself who might be heading along those same lines)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I have come to through all of these experiences is that Canadians don&amp;rsquo;t know much about us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education is a cultural process and, of course, the education citizens receive in Canada is all about British contact with Indigenous people and the development and maintenance of Canada. No one studies what was here before in any serious way. It is as though the 150-year history of Canada is far more significant than the 15,000 years previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a sobering thought and so very true. I certainly did not retain much in the way of Indigenous history or knowledge from my Canadian education. That probably means there are at least a generation of people, if not more, who likely have no clue, really (other than stereotypes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle does a good job of imparting the full richness of Turtle Islander culture to her readers, a culture dismissed by settlers, but nevertheless whose influence can be seen on today&amp;rsquo;s world (although that goes unacknowledged).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s humbling to think of all the things we missed learning about in school. What a curriculum it would have made!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was brought up in story. No one disciplined me by spanking or scoldings; rather the old people watching me told a story and I was expected to figure out my behavioural issues from the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I was raised on story, I brought my children up on story. We work with story. We begin with an old tale and, as we progress through the story, we tell it back different but the same, changing it so it becomes a modern new story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maracle also makes clear that being nice people doesn&amp;rsquo;t give Canadians a pass; she drives home that we are all actively complicit in the genocide of Turtle Islanders, quoting articles from the UN Genocide Convention to support her case. Ignorance may be bliss for some, but morally that stance just doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold up. We have a responsibility to educate ourselves on affairs that are being conducted in our name. It&amp;rsquo;s time for Canadians to get with it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase a statement in the book: de-colonization is not about how the Indigenous world fits into ours, but how we fit into theirs. With this in mind, I sample from Chapter 12 which describes the Turtle Islander belief system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humility is critical to recognizing and examining our failures, our mistakes, our contribution to broken relations [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courage gives us the determination to overcome our fear of self-examination, of admitting to our neglect. [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honesty teaches us to own our self&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the above be a guide to us Canadians as we reach to build true relations with Turtle Islanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would urge all non-Indigenous folk to pick up this book and see Canada differently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Dirt Cure</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:15:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/dirtCure.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dirt-cure-by-maya-shetreat-klein:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; by Maya Shetreat-Klein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this book awhile ago with my wife, and wanted circle back and do a recap. &lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; argues that far from being something harmful to be avoided, dirt is actually rather healthy - more specifically, the microbes living in the dirt. This basic premise leads to insights into diet and illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maya’s philosophy is that the health of our inner terrain —our bodies– is a reflection of the health of our outer terrain, the natural world around us. Gut, immune and nervous system — and the many microbes therein — are a direct reflection of the food we eat and where that food comes from, from the soil it’s grown in to the water it swims in to the synthetic chemicals that it’s bathed in.
dirtcure.com/about/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems the scientific references may have been exaggerated in places (my wife is one to fact-check academic studies), there were still enough persuasive arguments in the book to influence how we do things around our household. Here are the key takeaways for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-microbiome-that-we-eat-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The microbiome that we eat, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of consuming bacteria in food I mainly think of probiotics like yogurt. But of course all the food we eat have microbes living in them. Now consider: what if those microbes matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something of a new way of looking at things for me. You&amp;rsquo;re not just sourcing nutrients from the food you eat, you&amp;rsquo;re sourcing microbes. In which case, it follows that where or how your food is grown can impact how healthy it is for you. Was the tomato grown in biodiverse soil? Was the tomato grown in depleted soil? They might look the same to the eye but one might have more benefit to your body. (I look forward to a time when technology is good enough to differentiate these two tomatoes for us in the grocery store!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-terrain-that-we-live-in-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The terrain that we live in, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t live in a vacuum. It was noted that people who grew up on farms had less allergies/asthma than city folks, likely due to the diversity of microbes they are exposed to. &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/804022/health-benefits-japanese-forest-bathing/&#34;&gt;Forest bathing&lt;/a&gt; is also a proven immune-boosting and healing activity. The benefits of being outdoors, especially in nature, are not to be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illness:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Illness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, bad terrain increases susceptibility to illness. The book introduces an analogy that I quite liked: the basin. When toxins (or viruses, germs, etc) enter our system, they go into our basin. Our body flushes the basin to clear the toxins. When the rate at which toxins enter exceeds the rate the body can clear them, the basin overflows. This results in illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a simple analogy but it explains how the cumulative effects of multiple exposures (each maybe harmless on its own) could affect your health. Reduction of a seemingly innocuous exposure (eg. eliminating a processed food from your diet) can have huge impacts when you are currently at, or close to, the tipping point. Even if you are not near the tipping point, you want to keep your basin as clear as possible so that when you do happen to catch a virus, your body has full power to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-book-changed-for-us-personally:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;What this book changed for us personally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think we were already practicing an approximation of the lifestyle promoted by this book. As CSA members we get the bulk of our veggies from local farms, picked the day before, often arriving with the dirt still clinging to them. We live across the street from a forest. Nevertheless, the book spurred us to make a few adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pantry-cleanout:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Pantry cleanout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this was the kick in the butt we needed to review our pantry and clear out a number of dubious foods. Anything processed, anything with additives (artificial sweeteners, food dyes, unpronounceable ingredients) was basically cut. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a strict elimination diet for us and we&amp;rsquo;ll happily enjoy some of those foods, but they don&amp;rsquo;t need to be in our main rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting thing we found is that sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll be using processed foods without even realizing it. Consider cocoa powder. Everyone knows that chocolate (the raw stuff) is healthy for you, so we had been using cocoa powder quite regularly. But look at the difference in nutrients between 20g of a &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; cocoa powder (Fry&amp;rsquo;s brand) vs Organic Traditions brand cacao powder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fry&amp;rsquo;s cocoa powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;140 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organic Traditions cacao powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought these were equivalent but clearly not. One must be more highly processed than the other (the internet seems to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.paleohacks.com/cacao-vs-cocoa/#&#34;&gt;confirm this&lt;/a&gt;). When you consume something regularly, it pays to check. What do you have in your pantry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-foods:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;New foods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was adding new foods into our rotation. Many foods were suggested by the book, but as mentioned we already had a pretty good diet. However, there are a few new items that stuck with us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kefir (loads of diverse microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kimchi (again microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blackstrap molasses (more antioxidants than blueberries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;soups / bone broths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also dabbled in growing our own sprouts, but that was put on hold once we got our CSA and had more than enough greens to consume each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing we&amp;rsquo;ve been doing is making our own stocks, rather than using bouillon cubes. It&amp;rsquo;s super easy to do and a great way to use all the ends of your veggies rather than throwing away those nutrients in the garbage. We collect them in a container in the freezer, then every couple of weeks boil them into a stock that gets used in our soups and other recipes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;has-it-helped:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Has it helped?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not being scientific about it, but my wife was often one to fall sick with colds. It&amp;rsquo;s been more than half a year and she has not had a serious cold yet, which must be a record. I have only taken one sick day over the same period. So far, at least, it seems to be helping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would be interesting to check back a year from now and see how we&amp;rsquo;re doing. I will try to post an update here if I remember&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Do Not Say We Have Nothing</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 16:31:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/doNotSayWeHaveNothing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-not-say-we-have-nothing-by-madeleine-thien:c82c375baf10ac0da7e6de1e08fcf4ef&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do Not Say We Have Nothing&lt;/em&gt; by Madeleine Thien&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess this one took me a while to sink into. There came a point early on when I happened to pause the book and I almost never picked it up again. It sat there on my night table, a reminder, but I&amp;rsquo;d find something else to occupy my time with. Eventually I did continue and I&amp;rsquo;m glad for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is a history of modern China told from the perspective of an everyday family comprising of artists and musicians. One of the fascinating things to me was the role of music in this story. How can an author, any author, truly describe music in a language such as English? It&amp;rsquo;s a tough challenge, but Thien really did justice to it. However the idea of translating one language to another is bound to leave omissions; a more considered reading of this book would involve listening to these pieces yourself (unfortunately I was not committed enough for that, although I am listening as I write this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting topic was seeing how different people react when externally imposed pressures are applied on them from society at large. Some can&amp;rsquo;t go on, some conform, some thrive in resistance. At times I could see myself in Sparrow. I have been known to become a bit of a chameleon of sorts. But if you can&amp;rsquo;t do the things you love, the things you were meant to do.. who are you, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this book won me over by creating very real characters who behaved in ways I did not understand at all. It&amp;rsquo;s powerful to live in someone else&amp;rsquo;s place and be reminded that your way of looking at things is not the only or the best way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Project Animal Farm</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/02/04/book-review-project-animal-farm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 21:10:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/02/04/book-review-project-animal-farm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.soniafaruqi.com/wp-content/themes/sonia/images/book-home.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most people, myself included, ignorance is bliss when it comes to meat. We prefer to pick up our vacuum wrapped cuts from the grocery stores with only a cursory thought to its journey there. So it was with some trepidation that I picked up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.soniafaruqi.com/book/&#34;&gt;Project Animal Farm&lt;/a&gt; by Sonia Faruqi. It&amp;rsquo;s the story of a Wall Street banker who followed her curiosity into the dark world of animal farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a very personal journey and mainly anecdotal, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t take away from it; in fact it enhances the connection with the reader. But it also means the reader needs to be careful about broad generalizations from her stories. Her statements on Malaysia, for example, are quite different than my experience of that country. Nevertheless, she takes the reader through a large cross-section of the farming industry, across many countries all over the world, providing personal accounts of everything she witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it comes as no surprise that current farming practices are downright unconscionable regarding animal welfare and it&amp;rsquo;s a real tragedy if you ask me. The factory farming industry is simply revolting. Unfortunately that&amp;rsquo;s where most of the food in our grocery stores come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to learn was that these farming practices are just as bad for society as they are for the animals. Public health is at risk due to increased communicable diseases and outbreaks, as well as the long-term threat of antibiotic resistance. Workers are at risk due to terrible working environments, being exposed to basically unbreathable air filled with ammonia. And the environment is at risk due to dumping of hormones and refuse, as well as carbon dioxide emissions. So even if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about animal welfare, you should be concerned about the side effects of this method of farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this book, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably come away convinced that as a society we can, and should, do better. Why do we put up with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrap it in a nice package, it seems, and the consumer doesn&amp;rsquo;t care to look any deeper. What can be done? Faruqi has a few ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-shop-at-farmer-s-markets:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;1) Shop at farmer&amp;rsquo;s markets.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now our food chain is so far removed from the actual producers, that ignorance reigns while profit becomes the driving force. But if you source your food from someone local, whose farm you can visit if you choose to, and who you can ask questions directly.. then there&amp;rsquo;s a much better chance that farmer will be following good practices on their farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few years I have been buying meat and vegetables from a CSA, whose farm I visit every week to collect my food, and let me tell you it&amp;rsquo;s a wonderful feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-read-the-labels:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;2) Read the labels.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following labels are useless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;family farm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural, or naturally raised&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grain-fed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organic is one of the better labels when it comes to dairy and meat. It means the animals are mandated a minimum of 120 days per year outside, which is not much, but still much better than the requirements for non-organic (0 days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-research:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;3) Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you buy at the grocery store, do some basic research on the companies you usually buy from. Visit their website and email/call with questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they permit public visits (it&amp;rsquo;s a good test, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t actually intend to visit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much space are animals allotted?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they go outdoors and if so how much?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are any mutilations done (castration, declawing, de-beaking, tail-docking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are animals confined to cages, crates or stalls? Are they chained?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Faruqi says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not receive a reply, you will have your reply. This legwork is easier than it looks, because once you find a company you&amp;rsquo;re comfortable with, you can stay with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you with a final statement from Faruqi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With every visit to a cash counter, we, consumers, cast votes for certain values over others. In democracies, politicians are beholden to their voters; in free-market economies, companies are beholden to their customers. It&amp;rsquo;s we who have immeasurable power, if only we choose to wield it. We must have opinions and we must express them loud and clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Into the Silence</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 16:20:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/into-the-silence.png&#34; alt=&#34;Into the Silence&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-great-war-mallory-and-the-conquest-of-everest:430078025ad00d05681f6e91e31d9b31&#34;&gt;The Great War, Mallory, and the Conquest of Everest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; by Wade Davis recounts the failed 1920s Everest expeditions, the first ever attempts on the mountain. But it&amp;rsquo;s much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the climbers were shaped by the Great War, and so the book begins there. This leads into an engrossing look at the chaos, the folly, and the haunting reality of a generation of men who would return from war with wounds that could never heal. If the book had been solely these initial chapters on the war, and that was it, I would have been perfectly satisfied. What a treat to realize this was only the introduction, a springboard for what was still yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that stood out to me while reading this book is how these events were happening in a fairly modern, yet entirely different time. From a sensibilities point of view, the Great War had largely broken the spell of idealism, nobility, and purpose in many. Yet for others, it spurred a retreat away from the misery of daily life and towards a more idealistic meaning. The Everest expeditions could be seen as an outlet for the latter, and the men who volunteered were sometimes spiritual, sometimes adventure seekers, always in pursuit of something bigger than themselves. Davis does a nice job of interpreting these distinctions for the modern reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to tell you were being transported into another time is the wonderful collection of correspondence (yes, letter writing was a daily thing!) and it was at times extremely eloquent.. This was a vast wealth of primary material which Davis spent a decade researching, and it led to convincing character portraits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Death&amp;rsquo;s power lies in fear, which flourishes in the imagination and the unknown. For Wheeler there was nothing more that death could show him, short of his own.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tricky things as a reader is dealing with the large cast of characters involved, spanning three expeditions, and I admit to having some difficulty keeping all the persons straight in my head. In the first expedition, Davis had you cheering for the Canadian surveyor Wheeler who was not originally participating in a climbing role but nevertheless won over Mallory and the rest of the team and was ultimately appointed to the climbing party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the storylines in the second expedition, none resonated more than George Finch, the skinny scientist whose revolutionary tactics about bottled oxygen led him to achieve a new height record, despite far worse support than the main climbing party.  A Mallory/Finch climbing tandem is one of those &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; the reader can only wonder about..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that over the course of the book, neither through the author&amp;rsquo;s lens nor through Mallory&amp;rsquo;s personal writings, did I ever fully connect or empathize with Mallory. Hence the fateful end was not a tear jerker for me in the same way as other Everest &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Into_Thin_Air&#34;&gt;stories have been&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, Davis delivers an extremely powerful conclusion to the book. In stark contrast to all the earlier climbing activities, where every action can be analyzed and scrutinized through the heaps of correspondence, private writings, and post reflections by the principle actors, at the moment when Mallory and Irvine depart up the mountain together never to return, the author and his readers are left with a big hole of information to wonder about. We&amp;rsquo;re simply left with&amp;hellip; the silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s powerful and it will have your imagination running in overdrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the recounting of this climbing history leaves the reader a lasting impression of &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What If&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; as each expedition made mistakes (either through membership composition or on the mountain itself) or suffered unpreventable setbacks that taxed the climbers, preventing them from reaching their full potential. In ideal conditions, who can say how far they would have climbed? Or so the book suggests. But I think the real lesson of Everest, clear even in these first attempts at the mountain, is how normal this kind of result is. Sure you may be fit enough to climb the mountain, but count on dealing with any two or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;altitude sickness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inadequate support/teammates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avalanche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;illness/lack of nutrition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unforgiving weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical malfunction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of these obstacles, the early 1920&amp;rsquo;s expeditions were indisputably heroic achievements. From the personalities involved, to the politics of the region, to the sensibilities of the time, &lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; is a very human look at mount Everest and pushing into new frontiers. It is told through Davis&amp;rsquo; flowing prose, and it is a beautiful read. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mindset</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 23:11:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carol Dweck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Success-Carol-Dweck/dp/0345472322&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindset: The New Psychology of Success&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; summarizes the ground-breaking research she and others have been leading on the subjects of motivation, identity, self-awareness and ability. All of these, it turns out, can be influenced significantly by one&amp;rsquo;s mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her most famous experiment involves taking two groups of kids and giving each kid an easy puzzle to solve. She then praised one group of kids for being smart, but praised the other group for their effort. Then she observed how the performance of these two groups differed over time, and they did dramatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those praised for being smart were less willing to take on harder challenges, did worse on subsequent administered challenges (even when a challenge similar to the original in difficulty was re-administered), and even lied about their performance scores. She was quite surprised to find that her praise transformed kids into liars! The book was written a decade ago, with over a million copies sold, so I&amp;rsquo;m hoping this has become more common knowledge now to many people as it&amp;rsquo;s quite important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first group, as a result of the praise, the children were nudged into taking a &lt;em&gt;fixed mindset&lt;/em&gt; about intelligence. This is the idea that your natural abilities are permanent. In this view, while anybody can learn new things, the overall intelligence (or ability) that you bring to the table is fixed. Similar to thinking that everyone has pretty much one IQ score and it won&amp;rsquo;t change. Do you share this mindset?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other group was nudged into the &lt;em&gt;growth mindset&lt;/em&gt;. That is, believing that our abilities can be developed through experience - including our intelligence. It is the belief that by working through difficult things we can improve ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might find you have a fixed mindset about some things and not others. Consider the two paragraphs above, but what if you replace &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;artistic ability&amp;rdquo;? &amp;hellip;sports? &amp;hellip;leadership?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has since done all kinds of experiments on people of all ages to test these beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that people who have a growth mindset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more willing, even eager, to take on harder challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tend to view mistakes as learning opportunities rather than attacks on their identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more resilient when hit by negative labels, negative stereotyping, or depression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have more accurate estimations about their own abilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generally end up succeeding/performing better over time, even showing bumps in IQ in some studies on kids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems the growth mindset is the way to go, no? Trouble is you might have one mindset or the other and not even be aware of it. Luckily, it is possible to switch mindsets. The scary thing to me is just how easy it can be to do so at times. Many of the mentioned studies were able to switch their subjects into one mindset or the other before evaluating them (as she demonstrated with those kids). Makes you wonder how we all individually and as a society contribute towards inadvertently conjuring one mindset over the other in those around us. This truly has serious implications on parenting, teaching and coaching. Never call your kids smart! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all really interesting for sure, but how about the book itself? Dweck begins by presenting the mindset concepts to the reader (so far so good), but then she takes us on a journey of looking at the world through a &amp;ldquo;mindset&amp;rdquo; lens. She focuses on celebrities in history across various domains (business, sports, coaching), and shows us examples of both fixed mindset and growth mindset people. For example, she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s who she thinks hold a fixed mindset and explains how this contributed to their failure at business. Then she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s with a growth mindset and shows how it contributed to their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the book at its worst, in my opinion. This is anecdotal evidence at best. She is making assumptions about their mindsets based on observed behaviour, but she has not actually tested these people, or if she did she does not mention it. Anyone can cherry pick examples to prove a point, and I quickly got frustrated and fed up of reading these anecdotal examples that weren&amp;rsquo;t adding any substance to the argument. Unfortunately these are &lt;em&gt;littered&lt;/em&gt; throughout the book. She has a tendency to follow up each proposition with an anecdote. This shows up in the form: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A study by ABC has shown that fixed mindset people are less resilient to XYZ. For example, Billy was an elementary school student and&amp;hellip; [Billy&amp;rsquo;s story goes here]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I am more technically-inclined than most, but these anecdotes are fluff and I would prefer if she had included more experiment details and their specific results. She also avoided almost any discussion of quantitative results, perhaps thinking percentages and the like might scare aware her audience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the sheer significance of the research being shared here overcomes any failings in the presentation. &lt;strong&gt;Read this book&lt;/strong&gt; if you have the chance. My recommendation is to read the first couple of chapters on the basic concepts, then &lt;strong&gt;skip entirely&lt;/strong&gt; the fluff chapters on business, sports, and coaching (you can return to them later if you really want to). Instead proceed straight to the parenting and teaching chapter, which is the most important I think.  Also feel free to skip any anecdotal stories if you are getting fed up with them, you won&amp;rsquo;t miss anything! I read the book aloud this way to my wife as she drove us across the Yukon, and we both enjoyed the book much better that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has written a few articles since the book was published. Further reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-secret-to-raising-smart-kids1/&#34;&gt;The Secret to Raising Smart Kids - Scientific American article by Carol Dweck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edweek.org/ew/articles/2015/09/23/carol-dweck-revisits-the-growth-mindset.html&#34;&gt;Carol Dweck Revisits the &amp;lsquo;Growth Mindset&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Quantum Night</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 17:02:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/1/18/Quantum_Night_by_Robert_J._Sawyer_Book_Cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_Night&#34;&gt;Quantum Night&lt;/a&gt; is the latest from Canadian sci-fi author Robert Sawyer. In it, two researchers independently discover two techniques to identify psychopaths objectively, and they come together to try and figure out the implications of their discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting themes raised in the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are the ethics for research on human subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;why are there so many people all over the world doing terrible things, all the time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are people still responsible for their actions even if they are physically &amp;ldquo;hard-wired&amp;rdquo; to be that way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;herd mentality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tensions between tribal loyalty and the greater good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me about this book is how &amp;ldquo;un-fictiony&amp;rdquo; it felt for sci-fi. I am glad that Sawyer took on the topic of psychology which is extremely relevant in today&amp;rsquo;s society.. In the age of Brexit and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://qz.com/723537/in-the-post-factual-democracy-politicians-win-by-getting-feelings-right-and-facts-wrong/&#34;&gt;post-factual democracy&lt;/a&gt;, human psychology has been harnessed/exploited by corporations, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.ca/Enlightenment-2-0-Restoring-Politics-Economy/dp/0062342894&#34;&gt;politicians&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rushkoff.com/staying-human-machine-age-interview-douglas-rushkoff/&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, military, and on and on.. It can get a little depressing to think about, knowing we are mostly helpless agents against ourselves. Of course there are good guys working other angles too (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nudge_(book)&#34;&gt;Nudge&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is possible to become self-aware of our own individual psychological tendencies, and to recognize if someone is using questionable tactics to convince us of something, this takes &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&#34;&gt;a lot of effort&lt;/a&gt;, and thus it&amp;rsquo;s practically impossible to completely eliminate our innate tendencies entirely. Even if one person could do it, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly not possible to achieve this at the larger level of a society. Ultimately, then, I think our society is bound to suffer further Brexit and Trump-like eventualities, until such time we consciously reorganize our institutions (political systems, corporations, etc) to properly take into account the fallibilities of human psychology and put in guards against their exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds a bit crazy, but machines might actually be able to help us here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pzs:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;PZs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another topic raised in the book is the concept of &amp;ldquo;pz&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; as Sawyer called them, people who act and behave just like normal people but internally (unbeknownst to anyone), are not actually conscious. While these people were viewed with horror and disdain (at least by the characters in the novel), it did occur to me that this notion of a clear mind / living entirely in the moment, is something of an achievement if you are an existentialist or a Buddhist. There are people actively trying to blot out their consciousness for a few moments of zen. So maybe a lifetime of pz would represent the ultimate fulfillment? Or does it only count if you consciously surrender your consciousness? ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really enjoyed the book although the ending felt a little rushed, and I kept hoping for one final twist that never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I love about Sawyer&amp;rsquo;s novels are the education factor. While you keep turning the pages to see how the story unfolds, there are plenty of interesting ideas and references scattered throughout, bread crumbs to return to later and revisit should you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/quantumNightTwitter.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: What Does It Mean To Be Human</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/06/29/book-review-what-does-it-mean-to-be-human/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 19:49:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/06/29/book-review-what-does-it-mean-to-be-human/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/whatDoesItMeanToBeHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;What Does It Mean to Be Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.ca/books?id=DgE8ITskDEcC&#34;&gt;What Does it Mean to be Human&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the companion book for the Smithsonian Natural History Museum&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://humanorigins.si.edu/&#34;&gt;Human Origins&lt;/a&gt; initiative. The book takes the reader on a breathtaking journey through our ancient past to explain when and how we acquired the traits we most closely associate with modern humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-of-these-are-human-but-not-homo-sapiens:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;All of these are human, but not &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Although you could be forgiven for mistaking one!)
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/humans.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Humans&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book covers many topics on the history of our species, I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on three of the items that I found most fascinating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Eating meat was a factor in our advanced intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Climate change made us who we are&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. We almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meat-fuels-our-brains:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Meat Fuels Our Brains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important aspect of our ancestry is that we became heavy meat eaters. Stone tools (used for over a million years) let us hunt and carve up bigger game. As our meat consumption increased, our digestive system evolved and shortened in order to rapidly extract nutrients from meat, as opposed to taking days to digest plants as they pass through a long intestine. This reduction in gut size allowed humans to divert precious energy to other organs in the body, such as the brain, which today uses as much as 25% of our total energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The dietary shift toward meat and the reduction in gut size are likely to have proved crucial in fueling the evolution of an enlarged brain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that eating meat caused our brains to grow, but rather as other stresses pushed us toward a need for greater intelligence, meat gave us the means to evolve our bodies in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While meat is now classified a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.who.int/features/qa/cancer-red-meat/en/&#34;&gt;probable carcinogen&lt;/a&gt;, and limited consumption is suggested for both health and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cowspiracy.com/infographic&#34;&gt;environmental&lt;/a&gt; reasons, it was nevertheless a key factor in getting us where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climate-change-made-us-human:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Climate Change Made Us Human&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans developed in one of the most geologically volatile eras of the Earth. Wild fluctuations from cold to hot, wet to dry, and back meant that survival was always dependent on being adaptable. In the last 100,000 years for example the Earth went from hippos living in England to permafrost covering almost all of Europe. Even the cold-hardened Neanderthals had to retreat all the way down to Gibraltar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fluctuations in climate led us to where we are today. The ability to stand upright gave us the opportunity to travel long distances efficiently, allowing us to move with, and according, to the changing environment. The stresses of continuous climate change led to advances in imagination, planning, symbols and memory as our mental and social tools evolved to better respond to change and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A species that does a lot of things well retains more options when its surroundings change.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, our species &lt;strong&gt;optimized itself for change&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as for our ancestors, climate change continues to be a hot topic for us today, this time through our own actions. Fittingly, solving today&amp;rsquo;s problem will require us to attain a new level of humanity - large-scale co-operation is now required on a global scale. Just as before, the challenges we face define who we will become as a species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-almost-didn-t-make-it:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;We Almost Didn&amp;rsquo;t Make It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; is but one species in a large human family tree. Most branches led to evolutionary dead ends, including 20+ other hominid species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our closest evolutionary cousins - species that also walked upright, made tools, and had large brains - went extinct, even though these basic characteristics were at one time considered to be the hallmarks of evolutionary success in human beings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sorely wish that at least &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; other species in the &lt;em&gt;Homo&lt;/em&gt; group had survived to the present day. Most of us have likely heard about the existence of other human species (such as Neanderthals), along with the fact we actually share DNA with our cousin species (my immediate family is 2.1% Neanderthal for example, roughly average for those of non-African ethnicity). Yet these links do not feel as immediate as they might if there were a living breathing community sharing the Earth with us. Imagine the new perspective this would inform, about our place in the universe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Or not - on the other hand I shudder to think how we would have treated our cousin species, given how poorly we behave to members of our own species who are merely different.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, just like our cousin species, Homo sapiens almost went extinct in our own right. DNA evidence suggests that at one point our breeding population may have been as low as 2,000 people, possibly even as few as 600 individuals. It makes you realize how much of our success was left to chance, as it could easily have been another hominid species, perhaps the Neanderthals or some new descendent, writing the history books about us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What Does it Mean to be Human&lt;/em&gt; tells us that we are a species very much in flux; not a polished product but a moment in time. We have a long history. Older than culture, spanning species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book is focused solely on the past, it cannot help but lead to questions about our future. If part of being human means innovating, or having an imagination, as these distinguish us from earlier species - then what happens when machines can also innovate and dream? Will some different human characteristic take larger significance to us in the future and provide deep meaning to our descendants, such as perhaps, death? What does it really mean to be human, after all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you find yourself in Washington DC, check out the exhibit at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://humanorigins.si.edu/&#34;&gt;Smithsonian Natural History museum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/&#34;&gt;Genographic Project&lt;/a&gt; by National Geographic is an interesting way to learn about your own personal lineage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>