<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ottawa on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/ottawa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ottawa on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 08:50:50 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/ottawa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Smart&#34; City coming to Ottawa?</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 08:50:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2019/03/22/smart-city-coming-to-ottawa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was stirred to write a blog post after stumbling across an op-ed titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/index.php/article/op-ed-forget-about-toronto-sidewalk-labs-build-smart-neighbourhood-ottawa-instead&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forget about Toronto, Sidewalk Labs – build a smart neighbourhood in Ottawa instead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been following Toronto&amp;rsquo;s efforts at smart city development for the past 9 months (aka the Sidewalk Labs debacle), and was alarmed to read this same group might bring their bad behaviour to Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sidewalk Labs&amp;rsquo; smart city in Toronto has woeful accountability (and its leaked plans are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalobserver.com/2019/02/15/news/alphabets-sidewalk-labs-was-secretly-considering-big-plans-toronto-neighbourhood&#34;&gt;terrifying&lt;/a&gt;), with high profile &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/2018/10/20/privacy-expert-steps-down-from-advisory-role-with-sidewalk-labs.html&#34;&gt;resignations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://business.financialpost.com/technology/sidewalk-labs-advisory-panel-member-saadia-muzaffar-resigns-citing-deep-dismay&#34;&gt;leading tech experts&lt;/a&gt;. And yet they continue to go forward. Explain why would anyone would want that for their city?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The op-ed author says that a data policy is necessary upfront (which I absolutely agree with) while in the same breath telling us we should &amp;ldquo;inform these businesses they could start developing a smart community in Ottawa today&amp;rdquo;. Seems like a contradiction there. A public data policy must be something that is carefully debated and not rushed through. It&amp;rsquo;s exactly this kind of &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out as we go&amp;rdquo; mentality that got Toronto into trouble. It opens the door for corporate definition and interference in policy (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@biancawylie/sidewalk-toronto-gaslighting-toronto-residents-backfired-capacitys-built-and-power-s-shifted-77c455b150a3&#34;&gt;gas lighting&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning from Toronto&amp;rsquo;s failure, and with many thanks to the citizens advocating in opposition there, here is what Ottawa can and should do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start working on privacy and data governance policies. Today! This needs to happen ASAP or we &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get bullied by corporations into rushed or inadequate policies. This needs to be carefully debated and done so in a fully transparent way.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we have any smart city policies already? I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laughably, Ottawa&amp;rsquo;s published &lt;a href=&#34;https://documents.ottawa.ca/sites/default/files/smart_city_strategy_en.pdf&#34;&gt;Smart City 2.0 Strategy&lt;/a&gt; does not have a single reference to &amp;ldquo;privacy&amp;rdquo; or even &amp;ldquo;data governance&amp;rdquo; in its strategy. (Yes you read that correctly. I wish I was joking.). Really shows where the priorities are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, as a city let&amp;rsquo;s first be explicit about what features we want from our smart city, and debate those features in a public setting. Not all &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; technology is smart for society or the public as a whole. We should not give carte blanche to corporations to &amp;ldquo;disrupt&amp;rdquo; neighbourhoods however they see fit, as if breaking neighbourhoods was even a good thing.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s follow the principle of &lt;a href=&#34;http://spacing.ca/toronto/2019/02/19/did-the-sidewalk-labs-plot-just-thicken-or-is-the-story-coming-to-an-end/&#34;&gt;Consult first, then procure.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to OBJ for the balanced journalism in also including an article on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://obj.ca/article/web-data-collected-smart-city-tech-stokes-privacy-fears&#34;&gt;privacy concerns&lt;/a&gt; surrounding smart city development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blocksidewalk.ca/&#34;&gt;BlockSidewalk&lt;/a&gt; movement to stay up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>