<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Password Manager on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/tags/password-manager/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Password Manager on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 15:39:27 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://cadams.ca/blog/tags/password-manager/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up a (free) Password Manager</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/05/07/setting-up-a-free-password-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 15:39:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/05/07/setting-up-a-free-password-manager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of remaining skeptical about password managers (do I really want to put all my eggs in one basket?), I finally caved after realizing that (a) there were simply too many accounts to remember and (b) my email is effectively a basket holding all the eggs already (anyone who gains access to your email account can use the password reset feature to access your other accounts). With that in mind a password manager didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to increase my risk profile any further from it&amp;rsquo;s current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like the popular &lt;em&gt;1Password&lt;/em&gt; offer cloud-based password management across all your devices.. at a cost. $3/month for their basic plan. I was looking for something cheaper than that. Free, ideally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://keepass.info/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;KeePass&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a lightweight open source password manager. The Windows client is so lightweight you don&amp;rsquo;t even have to install it. It&amp;rsquo;s just an &lt;code&gt;exe&lt;/code&gt; file that sits in a folder. After opening KeePass, you add new entries for each of your passwords, or you can import passwords from other password managers (although I was starting from scratch so I didn&amp;rsquo;t explore this further). The resulting password database is just an encrypted file that is safe to move around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to make your passwords available to other devices, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to share this file with those devices. For my purposes, my phone is the only other device I deal with. I installed the Android app &lt;em&gt;KeePassDroid&lt;/em&gt;, copied over the password database by USB, and now I&amp;rsquo;m set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawback with this approach is it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have cloud sync. I could have hosted my password database in my own cloud if I really wanted to, but actually I&amp;rsquo;ve found a simpler way to sync. These days, I always have my phone nearby! Hence the password database on my phone becomes my primary database, and all edits are done in my phone (it&amp;rsquo;s pretty rare that I have to add or change a password anyway). Then periodically about once a month or so, when I normally backup my phone I also transfer my password database over at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple approach to password management, but it meets my needs. I guess you can look at it as a cheap alternative to the pay services out there.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>