<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Enterprise on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/social-enterprise/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Enterprise on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 16:57:08 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/social-enterprise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Enterprise Unleashed 2017</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 16:57:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday I was invited by &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; to attend the Social Enterprise Unleashed conference in Ottawa. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-procurement:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Social procurement:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procurement generally follows the &amp;ldquo;Lowest Price Wins&amp;rdquo; model, which misses opportunities to benefit communities and can even cause harm by not respecting the environment nor paying living wages. The triple-bottom-line approach of social enterprise (People, Planet, Profit) needs to be the ultimate goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inroads have been made in recent years on the &amp;ldquo;Planet&amp;rdquo; portion of this - when one thinks &amp;ldquo;sustainable&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s often environmental sustainability that comes to mind, however the &amp;ldquo;People&amp;rdquo; component is what needs focus next to make it truly sustainable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hospitals and police have been promoting social enterprise because they understand that social factors are required to keep people healthy and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.winnipegfreepress.com/opinion/analysis/social-solution-to-budget-woes-a-job-instead-of-prison-414837654.html&#34;&gt;reduce incarceration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should be aiming for a requirement such that when public money is spent on procurement it should include some form of social impact. Scotland is leading the way by requiring all government contracts to add social impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;storytelling-for-impact:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Storytelling for Impact:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General fundamentals of a story involve:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a character (the customer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who has a problem (villain, internal, external, philosophical)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who meets a guide (empathy/trust, authority)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who gives them a plan (process, agreement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and calls them to action (direct call, transitional call)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that ends in a success and helps them avoid failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and also results in a character transformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer is the hero, not your brand. Brands that position themselves as heroes unknowingly compete with the customer. Position your brand in terms of what your customers want, not what you&amp;rsquo;re about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good story can not only promote the company externally but have transformational impact on employee engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78mNZeDaMtk?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the customer trust you? The answer is emotional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People want to be taken somewhere - transformation of character. Who does your customer want to become?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clusters-and-accelerators:637e07495f69ae8d8a86bb7ea4b890de&#34;&gt;Clusters and Accelerators:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we stimulate demand?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we &amp;ldquo;pull&amp;rdquo; social enterprises in rather than enterprises having to push their product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clusters - why?

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joint tendering (teaming up with other enterprises to deliver on large opportunities)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;purchasing power, economies of scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shared resources (space, transport, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;promotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning from each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food cluster in Ottawa is 30 enterprises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RiseToTheOccasion.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 14:53:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/risetotheoccasion.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/rtto.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;
A directory I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://RiseToTheOccasion.ca&#34;&gt;RiseToTheOccasion.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a provincial directory of social enterprises for the event planning sector. If you&amp;rsquo;re planning to put on an event in Ontario, you might like to see what&amp;rsquo;s available, with over 80 enterprises currently listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding on the product delivered by our previous project (the Ottawa directory &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt;), the new directory adds the following enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bilingual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location-based searching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;administrative interface, so that individual enterprises as well as directory administrators can control content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directory was officially launched at the &lt;em&gt;#SEUnleashed&lt;/em&gt; social enterprise conference in Ottawa on November 16th. As a contributor I was invited to attend the conference. I had a great time and gained valuable insights into the social enterprise sector. I posted more about the conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/11/19/social-enterprise-unleashed-2017/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WeAllProfit.ca Launched!</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/12/13/weallprofit.ca-launched/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 07:03:15 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/12/13/weallprofit.ca-launched/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A website I have been helping to build for &lt;a href=&#34;http://csedottawa.ca/&#34;&gt;CSED&lt;/a&gt; has officially launched!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;WeAllProfit.ca&lt;/a&gt; is a directory of social enterprises in Ottawa. A &lt;em&gt;social enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is a venture which has a  mission that goes beyond profit. This can mean offering employment to vulnerable or disabled people, protecting the environment, or passing their profits on to a charitable organization. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://WeAllProfit.ca&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; for many examples of social enterprises in Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website will serve customers of the social enterprise sector by gathering all the local enterprises listings in one place, where a potential customer such as yourself can discover and browse the offerings. We hope this will inspire you to shop in the social enterprise sector, and we are looking forward to adding many more enterprises as we go!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Hacks of Kindness 2016</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/06/25/random-hacks-of-kindness-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 21:28:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/06/25/random-hacks-of-kindness-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I participated in a hackathon for &lt;a href=&#34;http://rhok.ca/&#34;&gt;Random Hacks of Kindness&lt;/a&gt; where the goal is to support community organizations with tech solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the project for the Centre for Social Enterprise Development (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cised.ca/&#34;&gt;CISED&lt;/a&gt;). A &lt;em&gt;social enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is a venture whose purpose is to achieve a social mission. There are about 150 social enterprises in Ottawa, which includes ventures such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ReStore - accepts donated home products then refurbishes and resells them in their retail stores with all proceeds going to Habitat for Humanity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laundry Matters - employees with developmental disabilities provide residential and commercial laundry services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good Nature Groundskeeping:  provides professional landscape maintenance services while also providing employment to people who are economically disadvantaged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge for CISED is to grow the social enterprise sector. While there is increasing awareness about social enterprises and a willingness on the purchasing side to procure their services, currently the main challenges are the lack of awareness of what services are available (for example I had only heard of about 3 of the 150 companies myself), and the ability to connect the buyers with the sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hackathon began with an energizing discussion with the stakeholders from CISED about how to connect purchasers and suppliers in an online marketplace. We went into details such as the three main types of purchasers involved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large business procurement (government or companies looking to support social enterprises, perhaps to meet internal procurement targets)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small to medium independent business owners (perhaps looking to reinforce their brands or support the community)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The general public (people like you and me who would like to have their snow cleared all the while knowing the proceeds will support people in need in the community)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While CISED felt that the large procurers would be the most important clients to focus on as it would be the best shot at growing the social enterprise sector, the use cases involved with these purchasers were rather complex, such as dealing with scenarios where demand outstrips supply. Since social enterprises often have limited resources, if an order came in from a big client, such as a catering order, it might require two different catering companies to satisfy. It would be rather involved to support this kind of order on an online system, but could perhaps be achieved by allowing buyers to post RFPs or a similar concept (kind of like wanted ads on kijiji).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, we knew we could not build an online marketplace in 24 hours. However, there was something we could do to further the cause for all types of purchasers: build an online directory of social enterprises in Ottawa. This would satisfy an immediate need, as CISED often gets asked about what services are on offer, and currently this info is only available in a spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals of the directory would be online, public, fully searchable, and managed by CISED. New enterprises would apply to CISED for inclusion, and get vetted before being accepted. The directory would replace the current spreadsheet tracking system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we decided that Wordpress was a good technology choice for this problem. A CMS system would allow CISED to manage the list of social enterprises on an ongoing basis with minimal technical expertise required. Plugins could be used to import and export the database as needed. We could deliver the solution in 24 hours in a state that was actually useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivered code is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rhok2016-cised/cised-directory&#34;&gt;https://github.com/rhok2016-cised/cised-directory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that CISED will find this useful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>