<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/categories/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:15:02 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://cadams.ca/blog/categories/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Dirt Cure</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 20:15:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/09/06/book-review-the-dirt-cure/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/dirtCure.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dirt-cure-by-maya-shetreat-klein:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; by Maya Shetreat-Klein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this book awhile ago with my wife, and wanted circle back and do a recap. &lt;em&gt;The Dirt Cure&lt;/em&gt; argues that far from being something harmful to be avoided, dirt is actually rather healthy - more specifically, the microbes living in the dirt. This basic premise leads to insights into diet and illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maya’s philosophy is that the health of our inner terrain —our bodies– is a reflection of the health of our outer terrain, the natural world around us. Gut, immune and nervous system — and the many microbes therein — are a direct reflection of the food we eat and where that food comes from, from the soil it’s grown in to the water it swims in to the synthetic chemicals that it’s bathed in.
dirtcure.com/about/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it seems the scientific references may have been exaggerated in places (my wife is one to fact-check academic studies), there were still enough persuasive arguments in the book to influence how we do things around our household. Here are the key takeaways for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-microbiome-that-we-eat-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The microbiome that we eat, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of consuming bacteria in food I mainly think of probiotics like yogurt. But of course all the food we eat have microbes living in them. Now consider: what if those microbes matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something of a new way of looking at things for me. You&amp;rsquo;re not just sourcing nutrients from the food you eat, you&amp;rsquo;re sourcing microbes. In which case, it follows that where or how your food is grown can impact how healthy it is for you. Was the tomato grown in biodiverse soil? Was the tomato grown in depleted soil? They might look the same to the eye but one might have more benefit to your body. (I look forward to a time when technology is good enough to differentiate these two tomatoes for us in the grocery store!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-terrain-that-we-live-in-matters:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;The terrain that we live in, matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t live in a vacuum. It was noted that people who grew up on farms had less allergies/asthma than city folks, likely due to the diversity of microbes they are exposed to. &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/804022/health-benefits-japanese-forest-bathing/&#34;&gt;Forest bathing&lt;/a&gt; is also a proven immune-boosting and healing activity. The benefits of being outdoors, especially in nature, are not to be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illness:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Illness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, bad terrain increases susceptibility to illness. The book introduces an analogy that I quite liked: the basin. When toxins (or viruses, germs, etc) enter our system, they go into our basin. Our body flushes the basin to clear the toxins. When the rate at which toxins enter exceeds the rate the body can clear them, the basin overflows. This results in illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a simple analogy but it explains how the cumulative effects of multiple exposures (each maybe harmless on its own) could affect your health. Reduction of a seemingly innocuous exposure (eg. eliminating a processed food from your diet) can have huge impacts when you are currently at, or close to, the tipping point. Even if you are not near the tipping point, you want to keep your basin as clear as possible so that when you do happen to catch a virus, your body has full power to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-book-changed-for-us-personally:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;What this book changed for us personally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think we were already practicing an approximation of the lifestyle promoted by this book. As CSA members we get the bulk of our veggies from local farms, picked the day before, often arriving with the dirt still clinging to them. We live across the street from a forest. Nevertheless, the book spurred us to make a few adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pantry-cleanout:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Pantry cleanout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this was the kick in the butt we needed to review our pantry and clear out a number of dubious foods. Anything processed, anything with additives (artificial sweeteners, food dyes, unpronounceable ingredients) was basically cut. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a strict elimination diet for us and we&amp;rsquo;ll happily enjoy some of those foods, but they don&amp;rsquo;t need to be in our main rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting thing we found is that sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll be using processed foods without even realizing it. Consider cocoa powder. Everyone knows that chocolate (the raw stuff) is healthy for you, so we had been using cocoa powder quite regularly. But look at the difference in nutrients between 20g of a &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; cocoa powder (Fry&amp;rsquo;s brand) vs Organic Traditions brand cacao powder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fry&amp;rsquo;s cocoa powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;140 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;16%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organic Traditions cacao powder&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Sodium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40 mg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;20%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Magnesium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Zinc&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Vitamin C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Calcium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought these were equivalent but clearly not. One must be more highly processed than the other (the internet seems to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.paleohacks.com/cacao-vs-cocoa/#&#34;&gt;confirm this&lt;/a&gt;). When you consume something regularly, it pays to check. What do you have in your pantry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-foods:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;New foods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was adding new foods into our rotation. Many foods were suggested by the book, but as mentioned we already had a pretty good diet. However, there are a few new items that stuck with us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kefir (loads of diverse microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kimchi (again microbes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blackstrap molasses (more antioxidants than blueberries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;soups / bone broths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also dabbled in growing our own sprouts, but that was put on hold once we got our CSA and had more than enough greens to consume each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing we&amp;rsquo;ve been doing is making our own stocks, rather than using bouillon cubes. It&amp;rsquo;s super easy to do and a great way to use all the ends of your veggies rather than throwing away those nutrients in the garbage. We collect them in a container in the freezer, then every couple of weeks boil them into a stock that gets used in our soups and other recipes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;has-it-helped:fa94b92770d2954e9b683c25401a912e&#34;&gt;Has it helped?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not being scientific about it, but my wife was often one to fall sick with colds. It&amp;rsquo;s been more than half a year and she has not had a serious cold yet, which must be a record. I have only taken one sick day over the same period. So far, at least, it seems to be helping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would be interesting to check back a year from now and see how we&amp;rsquo;re doing. I will try to post an update here if I remember&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Do Not Say We Have Nothing</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 16:31:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/08/12/book-review-do-not-say-we-have-nothing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/doNotSayWeHaveNothing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-not-say-we-have-nothing-by-madeleine-thien:c82c375baf10ac0da7e6de1e08fcf4ef&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do Not Say We Have Nothing&lt;/em&gt; by Madeleine Thien&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess this one took me a while to sink into. There came a point early on when I happened to pause the book and I almost never picked it up again. It sat there on my night table, a reminder, but I&amp;rsquo;d find something else to occupy my time with. Eventually I did continue and I&amp;rsquo;m glad for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is a history of modern China told from the perspective of an everyday family comprising of artists and musicians. One of the fascinating things to me was the role of music in this story. How can an author, any author, truly describe music in a language such as English? It&amp;rsquo;s a tough challenge, but Thien really did justice to it. However the idea of translating one language to another is bound to leave omissions; a more considered reading of this book would involve listening to these pieces yourself (unfortunately I was not committed enough for that, although I am listening as I write this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting topic was seeing how different people react when externally imposed pressures are applied on them from society at large. Some can&amp;rsquo;t go on, some conform, some thrive in resistance. At times I could see myself in Sparrow. I have been known to become a bit of a chameleon of sorts. But if you can&amp;rsquo;t do the things you love, the things you were meant to do.. who are you, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this book won me over by creating very real characters who behaved in ways I did not understand at all. It&amp;rsquo;s powerful to live in someone else&amp;rsquo;s place and be reminded that your way of looking at things is not the only or the best way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Project Animal Farm</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/02/04/book-review-project-animal-farm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 21:10:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2017/02/04/book-review-project-animal-farm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.soniafaruqi.com/wp-content/themes/sonia/images/book-home.png&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most people, myself included, ignorance is bliss when it comes to meat. We prefer to pick up our vacuum wrapped cuts from the grocery stores with only a cursory thought to its journey there. So it was with some trepidation that I picked up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.soniafaruqi.com/book/&#34;&gt;Project Animal Farm&lt;/a&gt; by Sonia Faruqi. It&amp;rsquo;s the story of a Wall Street banker who followed her curiosity into the dark world of animal farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a very personal journey and mainly anecdotal, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t take away from it; in fact it enhances the connection with the reader. But it also means the reader needs to be careful about broad generalizations from her stories. Her statements on Malaysia, for example, are quite different than my experience of that country. Nevertheless, she takes the reader through a large cross-section of the farming industry, across many countries all over the world, providing personal accounts of everything she witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it comes as no surprise that current farming practices are downright unconscionable regarding animal welfare and it&amp;rsquo;s a real tragedy if you ask me. The factory farming industry is simply revolting. Unfortunately that&amp;rsquo;s where most of the food in our grocery stores come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to learn was that these farming practices are just as bad for society as they are for the animals. Public health is at risk due to increased communicable diseases and outbreaks, as well as the long-term threat of antibiotic resistance. Workers are at risk due to terrible working environments, being exposed to basically unbreathable air filled with ammonia. And the environment is at risk due to dumping of hormones and refuse, as well as carbon dioxide emissions. So even if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about animal welfare, you should be concerned about the side effects of this method of farming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this book, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably come away convinced that as a society we can, and should, do better. Why do we put up with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrap it in a nice package, it seems, and the consumer doesn&amp;rsquo;t care to look any deeper. What can be done? Faruqi has a few ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-shop-at-farmer-s-markets:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;1) Shop at farmer&amp;rsquo;s markets.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now our food chain is so far removed from the actual producers, that ignorance reigns while profit becomes the driving force. But if you source your food from someone local, whose farm you can visit if you choose to, and who you can ask questions directly.. then there&amp;rsquo;s a much better chance that farmer will be following good practices on their farm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few years I have been buying meat and vegetables from a CSA, whose farm I visit every week to collect my food, and let me tell you it&amp;rsquo;s a wonderful feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-read-the-labels:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;2) Read the labels.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following labels are useless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;family farm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;natural, or naturally raised&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grain-fed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organic is one of the better labels when it comes to dairy and meat. It means the animals are mandated a minimum of 120 days per year outside, which is not much, but still much better than the requirements for non-organic (0 days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-research:07024bcfe3baf3767ac110a4ebe54c22&#34;&gt;3) Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you buy at the grocery store, do some basic research on the companies you usually buy from. Visit their website and email/call with questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they permit public visits (it&amp;rsquo;s a good test, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t actually intend to visit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much space are animals allotted?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they go outdoors and if so how much?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are any mutilations done (castration, declawing, de-beaking, tail-docking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are animals confined to cages, crates or stalls? Are they chained?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Faruqi says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not receive a reply, you will have your reply. This legwork is easier than it looks, because once you find a company you&amp;rsquo;re comfortable with, you can stay with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you with a final statement from Faruqi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With every visit to a cash counter, we, consumers, cast votes for certain values over others. In democracies, politicians are beholden to their voters; in free-market economies, companies are beholden to their customers. It&amp;rsquo;s we who have immeasurable power, if only we choose to wield it. We must have opinions and we must express them loud and clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Into the Silence</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 16:20:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/11/13/book-review-into-the-silence/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/into-the-silence.png&#34; alt=&#34;Into the Silence&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-great-war-mallory-and-the-conquest-of-everest:430078025ad00d05681f6e91e31d9b31&#34;&gt;The Great War, Mallory, and the Conquest of Everest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; by Wade Davis recounts the failed 1920s Everest expeditions, the first ever attempts on the mountain. But it&amp;rsquo;s much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the climbers were shaped by the Great War, and so the book begins there. This leads into an engrossing look at the chaos, the folly, and the haunting reality of a generation of men who would return from war with wounds that could never heal. If the book had been solely these initial chapters on the war, and that was it, I would have been perfectly satisfied. What a treat to realize this was only the introduction, a springboard for what was still yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that stood out to me while reading this book is how these events were happening in a fairly modern, yet entirely different time. From a sensibilities point of view, the Great War had largely broken the spell of idealism, nobility, and purpose in many. Yet for others, it spurred a retreat away from the misery of daily life and towards a more idealistic meaning. The Everest expeditions could be seen as an outlet for the latter, and the men who volunteered were sometimes spiritual, sometimes adventure seekers, always in pursuit of something bigger than themselves. Davis does a nice job of interpreting these distinctions for the modern reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to tell you were being transported into another time is the wonderful collection of correspondence (yes, letter writing was a daily thing!) and it was at times extremely eloquent.. This was a vast wealth of primary material which Davis spent a decade researching, and it led to convincing character portraits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Death&amp;rsquo;s power lies in fear, which flourishes in the imagination and the unknown. For Wheeler there was nothing more that death could show him, short of his own.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tricky things as a reader is dealing with the large cast of characters involved, spanning three expeditions, and I admit to having some difficulty keeping all the persons straight in my head. In the first expedition, Davis had you cheering for the Canadian surveyor Wheeler who was not originally participating in a climbing role but nevertheless won over Mallory and the rest of the team and was ultimately appointed to the climbing party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the storylines in the second expedition, none resonated more than George Finch, the skinny scientist whose revolutionary tactics about bottled oxygen led him to achieve a new height record, despite far worse support than the main climbing party.  A Mallory/Finch climbing tandem is one of those &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; the reader can only wonder about..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that over the course of the book, neither through the author&amp;rsquo;s lens nor through Mallory&amp;rsquo;s personal writings, did I ever fully connect or empathize with Mallory. Hence the fateful end was not a tear jerker for me in the same way as other Everest &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Into_Thin_Air&#34;&gt;stories have been&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, Davis delivers an extremely powerful conclusion to the book. In stark contrast to all the earlier climbing activities, where every action can be analyzed and scrutinized through the heaps of correspondence, private writings, and post reflections by the principle actors, at the moment when Mallory and Irvine depart up the mountain together never to return, the author and his readers are left with a big hole of information to wonder about. We&amp;rsquo;re simply left with&amp;hellip; the silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s powerful and it will have your imagination running in overdrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the recounting of this climbing history leaves the reader a lasting impression of &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What If&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; as each expedition made mistakes (either through membership composition or on the mountain itself) or suffered unpreventable setbacks that taxed the climbers, preventing them from reaching their full potential. In ideal conditions, who can say how far they would have climbed? Or so the book suggests. But I think the real lesson of Everest, clear even in these first attempts at the mountain, is how normal this kind of result is. Sure you may be fit enough to climb the mountain, but count on dealing with any two or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;altitude sickness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inadequate support/teammates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avalanche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;illness/lack of nutrition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unforgiving weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical malfunction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of these obstacles, the early 1920&amp;rsquo;s expeditions were indisputably heroic achievements. From the personalities involved, to the politics of the region, to the sensibilities of the time, &lt;em&gt;Into the Silence&lt;/em&gt; is a very human look at mount Everest and pushing into new frontiers. It is told through Davis&amp;rsquo; flowing prose, and it is a beautiful read. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mindset</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 23:11:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/08/09/book-review-mindset/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Carol Dweck&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Mindset-Psychology-Success-Carol-Dweck/dp/0345472322&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mindset: The New Psychology of Success&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; summarizes the ground-breaking research she and others have been leading on the subjects of motivation, identity, self-awareness and ability. All of these, it turns out, can be influenced significantly by one&amp;rsquo;s mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her most famous experiment involves taking two groups of kids and giving each kid an easy puzzle to solve. She then praised one group of kids for being smart, but praised the other group for their effort. Then she observed how the performance of these two groups differed over time, and they did dramatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those praised for being smart were less willing to take on harder challenges, did worse on subsequent administered challenges (even when a challenge similar to the original in difficulty was re-administered), and even lied about their performance scores. She was quite surprised to find that her praise transformed kids into liars! The book was written a decade ago, with over a million copies sold, so I&amp;rsquo;m hoping this has become more common knowledge now to many people as it&amp;rsquo;s quite important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first group, as a result of the praise, the children were nudged into taking a &lt;em&gt;fixed mindset&lt;/em&gt; about intelligence. This is the idea that your natural abilities are permanent. In this view, while anybody can learn new things, the overall intelligence (or ability) that you bring to the table is fixed. Similar to thinking that everyone has pretty much one IQ score and it won&amp;rsquo;t change. Do you share this mindset?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other group was nudged into the &lt;em&gt;growth mindset&lt;/em&gt;. That is, believing that our abilities can be developed through experience - including our intelligence. It is the belief that by working through difficult things we can improve ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might find you have a fixed mindset about some things and not others. Consider the two paragraphs above, but what if you replace &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;artistic ability&amp;rdquo;? &amp;hellip;sports? &amp;hellip;leadership?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has since done all kinds of experiments on people of all ages to test these beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that people who have a growth mindset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more willing, even eager, to take on harder challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tend to view mistakes as learning opportunities rather than attacks on their identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are more resilient when hit by negative labels, negative stereotyping, or depression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have more accurate estimations about their own abilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;generally end up succeeding/performing better over time, even showing bumps in IQ in some studies on kids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems the growth mindset is the way to go, no? Trouble is you might have one mindset or the other and not even be aware of it. Luckily, it is possible to switch mindsets. The scary thing to me is just how easy it can be to do so at times. Many of the mentioned studies were able to switch their subjects into one mindset or the other before evaluating them (as she demonstrated with those kids). Makes you wonder how we all individually and as a society contribute towards inadvertently conjuring one mindset over the other in those around us. This truly has serious implications on parenting, teaching and coaching. Never call your kids smart! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all really interesting for sure, but how about the book itself? Dweck begins by presenting the mindset concepts to the reader (so far so good), but then she takes us on a journey of looking at the world through a &amp;ldquo;mindset&amp;rdquo; lens. She focuses on celebrities in history across various domains (business, sports, coaching), and shows us examples of both fixed mindset and growth mindset people. For example, she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s who she thinks hold a fixed mindset and explains how this contributed to their failure at business. Then she picks three CEO&amp;rsquo;s with a growth mindset and shows how it contributed to their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the book at its worst, in my opinion. This is anecdotal evidence at best. She is making assumptions about their mindsets based on observed behaviour, but she has not actually tested these people, or if she did she does not mention it. Anyone can cherry pick examples to prove a point, and I quickly got frustrated and fed up of reading these anecdotal examples that weren&amp;rsquo;t adding any substance to the argument. Unfortunately these are &lt;em&gt;littered&lt;/em&gt; throughout the book. She has a tendency to follow up each proposition with an anecdote. This shows up in the form: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;A study by ABC has shown that fixed mindset people are less resilient to XYZ. For example, Billy was an elementary school student and&amp;hellip; [Billy&amp;rsquo;s story goes here]&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I am more technically-inclined than most, but these anecdotes are fluff and I would prefer if she had included more experiment details and their specific results. She also avoided almost any discussion of quantitative results, perhaps thinking percentages and the like might scare aware her audience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the sheer significance of the research being shared here overcomes any failings in the presentation. &lt;strong&gt;Read this book&lt;/strong&gt; if you have the chance. My recommendation is to read the first couple of chapters on the basic concepts, then &lt;strong&gt;skip entirely&lt;/strong&gt; the fluff chapters on business, sports, and coaching (you can return to them later if you really want to). Instead proceed straight to the parenting and teaching chapter, which is the most important I think.  Also feel free to skip any anecdotal stories if you are getting fed up with them, you won&amp;rsquo;t miss anything! I read the book aloud this way to my wife as she drove us across the Yukon, and we both enjoyed the book much better that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck has written a few articles since the book was published. Further reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-secret-to-raising-smart-kids1/&#34;&gt;The Secret to Raising Smart Kids - Scientific American article by Carol Dweck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edweek.org/ew/articles/2015/09/23/carol-dweck-revisits-the-growth-mindset.html&#34;&gt;Carol Dweck Revisits the &amp;lsquo;Growth Mindset&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Quantum Night</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 17:02:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/07/06/book-review-quantum-night/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/1/18/Quantum_Night_by_Robert_J._Sawyer_Book_Cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_Night&#34;&gt;Quantum Night&lt;/a&gt; is the latest from Canadian sci-fi author Robert Sawyer. In it, two researchers independently discover two techniques to identify psychopaths objectively, and they come together to try and figure out the implications of their discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting themes raised in the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are the ethics for research on human subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;why are there so many people all over the world doing terrible things, all the time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are people still responsible for their actions even if they are physically &amp;ldquo;hard-wired&amp;rdquo; to be that way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;herd mentality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tensions between tribal loyalty and the greater good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me about this book is how &amp;ldquo;un-fictiony&amp;rdquo; it felt for sci-fi. I am glad that Sawyer took on the topic of psychology which is extremely relevant in today&amp;rsquo;s society.. In the age of Brexit and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://qz.com/723537/in-the-post-factual-democracy-politicians-win-by-getting-feelings-right-and-facts-wrong/&#34;&gt;post-factual democracy&lt;/a&gt;, human psychology has been harnessed/exploited by corporations, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.ca/Enlightenment-2-0-Restoring-Politics-Economy/dp/0062342894&#34;&gt;politicians&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rushkoff.com/staying-human-machine-age-interview-douglas-rushkoff/&#34;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, military, and on and on.. It can get a little depressing to think about, knowing we are mostly helpless agents against ourselves. Of course there are good guys working other angles too (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nudge_(book)&#34;&gt;Nudge&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is possible to become self-aware of our own individual psychological tendencies, and to recognize if someone is using questionable tactics to convince us of something, this takes &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&#34;&gt;a lot of effort&lt;/a&gt;, and thus it&amp;rsquo;s practically impossible to completely eliminate our innate tendencies entirely. Even if one person could do it, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly not possible to achieve this at the larger level of a society. Ultimately, then, I think our society is bound to suffer further Brexit and Trump-like eventualities, until such time we consciously reorganize our institutions (political systems, corporations, etc) to properly take into account the fallibilities of human psychology and put in guards against their exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds a bit crazy, but machines might actually be able to help us here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pzs:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;PZs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another topic raised in the book is the concept of &amp;ldquo;pz&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; as Sawyer called them, people who act and behave just like normal people but internally (unbeknownst to anyone), are not actually conscious. While these people were viewed with horror and disdain (at least by the characters in the novel), it did occur to me that this notion of a clear mind / living entirely in the moment, is something of an achievement if you are an existentialist or a Buddhist. There are people actively trying to blot out their consciousness for a few moments of zen. So maybe a lifetime of pz would represent the ultimate fulfillment? Or does it only count if you consciously surrender your consciousness? ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:b5829c54e94c1b05f613748b35307c5f&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really enjoyed the book although the ending felt a little rushed, and I kept hoping for one final twist that never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I love about Sawyer&amp;rsquo;s novels are the education factor. While you keep turning the pages to see how the story unfolds, there are plenty of interesting ideas and references scattered throughout, bread crumbs to return to later and revisit should you wish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: What Does It Mean To Be Human</title>
      <link>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/06/29/book-review-what-does-it-mean-to-be-human/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 19:49:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cadams.ca/blog/post/2016/06/29/book-review-what-does-it-mean-to-be-human/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/whatDoesItMeanToBeHuman.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;What Does It Mean to Be Human&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.ca/books?id=DgE8ITskDEcC&#34;&gt;What Does it Mean to be Human&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the companion book for the Smithsonian Natural History Museum&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://humanorigins.si.edu/&#34;&gt;Human Origins&lt;/a&gt; initiative. The book takes the reader on a breathtaking journey through our ancient past to explain when and how we acquired the traits we most closely associate with modern humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-of-these-are-human-but-not-homo-sapiens:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;All of these are human, but not &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Although you could be forgiven for mistaking one!)
&lt;img src=&#34;http://cadams.ca/blog/images/humans.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Humans&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book covers many topics on the history of our species, I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on three of the items that I found most fascinating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Eating meat was a factor in our advanced intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Climate change made us who we are&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. We almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meat-fuels-our-brains:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Meat Fuels Our Brains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important aspect of our ancestry is that we became heavy meat eaters. Stone tools (used for over a million years) let us hunt and carve up bigger game. As our meat consumption increased, our digestive system evolved and shortened in order to rapidly extract nutrients from meat, as opposed to taking days to digest plants as they pass through a long intestine. This reduction in gut size allowed humans to divert precious energy to other organs in the body, such as the brain, which today uses as much as 25% of our total energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The dietary shift toward meat and the reduction in gut size are likely to have proved crucial in fueling the evolution of an enlarged brain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that eating meat caused our brains to grow, but rather as other stresses pushed us toward a need for greater intelligence, meat gave us the means to evolve our bodies in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While meat is now classified a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.who.int/features/qa/cancer-red-meat/en/&#34;&gt;probable carcinogen&lt;/a&gt;, and limited consumption is suggested for both health and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cowspiracy.com/infographic&#34;&gt;environmental&lt;/a&gt; reasons, it was nevertheless a key factor in getting us where we are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climate-change-made-us-human:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Climate Change Made Us Human&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans developed in one of the most geologically volatile eras of the Earth. Wild fluctuations from cold to hot, wet to dry, and back meant that survival was always dependent on being adaptable. In the last 100,000 years for example the Earth went from hippos living in England to permafrost covering almost all of Europe. Even the cold-hardened Neanderthals had to retreat all the way down to Gibraltar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fluctuations in climate led us to where we are today. The ability to stand upright gave us the opportunity to travel long distances efficiently, allowing us to move with, and according, to the changing environment. The stresses of continuous climate change led to advances in imagination, planning, symbols and memory as our mental and social tools evolved to better respond to change and uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A species that does a lot of things well retains more options when its surroundings change.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, our species &lt;strong&gt;optimized itself for change&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as for our ancestors, climate change continues to be a hot topic for us today, this time through our own actions. Fittingly, solving today&amp;rsquo;s problem will require us to attain a new level of humanity - large-scale co-operation is now required on a global scale. Just as before, the challenges we face define who we will become as a species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-almost-didn-t-make-it:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;We Almost Didn&amp;rsquo;t Make It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; is but one species in a large human family tree. Most branches led to evolutionary dead ends, including 20+ other hominid species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our closest evolutionary cousins - species that also walked upright, made tools, and had large brains - went extinct, even though these basic characteristics were at one time considered to be the hallmarks of evolutionary success in human beings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sorely wish that at least &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; other species in the &lt;em&gt;Homo&lt;/em&gt; group had survived to the present day. Most of us have likely heard about the existence of other human species (such as Neanderthals), along with the fact we actually share DNA with our cousin species (my immediate family is 2.1% Neanderthal for example, roughly average for those of non-African ethnicity). Yet these links do not feel as immediate as they might if there were a living breathing community sharing the Earth with us. Imagine the new perspective this would inform, about our place in the universe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Or not - on the other hand I shudder to think how we would have treated our cousin species, given how poorly we behave to members of our own species who are merely different.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, just like our cousin species, Homo sapiens almost went extinct in our own right. DNA evidence suggests that at one point our breeding population may have been as low as 2,000 people, possibly even as few as 600 individuals. It makes you realize how much of our success was left to chance, as it could easily have been another hominid species, perhaps the Neanderthals or some new descendent, writing the history books about us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts:9e193303cf8ae8cc1645a18b7f1c1e48&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What Does it Mean to be Human&lt;/em&gt; tells us that we are a species very much in flux; not a polished product but a moment in time. We have a long history. Older than culture, spanning species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book is focused solely on the past, it cannot help but lead to questions about our future. If part of being human means innovating, or having an imagination, as these distinguish us from earlier species - then what happens when machines can also innovate and dream? Will some different human characteristic take larger significance to us in the future and provide deep meaning to our descendants, such as perhaps, death? What does it really mean to be human, after all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you find yourself in Washington DC, check out the exhibit at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://humanorigins.si.edu/&#34;&gt;Smithsonian Natural History museum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/&#34;&gt;Genographic Project&lt;/a&gt; by National Geographic is an interesting way to learn about your own personal lineage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>