<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>24/6 on Chad Adams</title>
    <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/24/6/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 24/6 on Chad Adams</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Chad Adams</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 17:57:57 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://cadams.ca/blog/tags/24/6/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book: 24/6 The Power of Unplugging One Day a Week</title>
      <link>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-24/6-the-power-of-unplugging-one-day-a-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 17:57:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cadams.ca/blog/post/2021/01/17/book-24/6-the-power-of-unplugging-one-day-a-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cadams.ca/blog/images/24-6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;24/6&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;24 / 6&lt;/em&gt; Tiffany Shlain proposes an antidote to the burdens of the modern world with a &amp;ldquo;Tech Shabbat&amp;rdquo;, a one-day reprieve from screens of all kind. Rather than define it using a negative, Shlain focuses on the positive by promoting it as a day to do all the things you always wished you had time for. I believe many of us dream of such a possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about this idea from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.teamhuman.fm/episodes/ep-139-tiffany-shlain-unplugging-one-day-a-week-tribute-to-paul-krassner&#34;&gt;Shlain&amp;rsquo;s interview on the Team Human podcast&lt;/a&gt; and was immediately excited about it. At the time of writing, I have completed my first Tech Shabbat with my family, and we&amp;rsquo;re very happy with how it went. We lit a candle to emphasize the transition. Going to bed early, fancy breakfast, listening to music, reading, thinking, having long conversations, spending time outdoors, napping&amp;hellip; it was glorious. I agree with Shlain when she says her Shabbat always feels longer than one day, it did for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the book is concerned, I was underwhelmed. I did find it useful to be shown specific examples of what Shabbat could entail, and I appreciated the emphasis on everyone defining their own rules and traditions in a way that works for them. Otherwise I found the book repetitive and the science chapters were not rigorous enough for my liking. In other parts I was finding it too autobiographical, I was not interested in the details&amp;hellip; but then I realized that was actually the whole point of Shabbat! Shlain sees the Tech Shabbat as a technology, a tool that extends her purpose into the world and so it&amp;rsquo;s quite impossible for her to talk about her Shabbat without also getting into her own goals and activities. And this insight turns it back onto the reader to decide (which I will do the same to you, dear reader):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your purpose? What are the things you always wished you had time for?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>